<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE><DATE>8-30-16</DATE><RESPSTMT><NAME>lattaj</NAME><RESP>MURP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Added TEMPHEAD, checked ID, and added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Proofed title page. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure; changed sub HEADs to HEADNOTE Ps; changed DATELINE to SIGNED; changed two SALUTEs to SIGNEDs; changed some oe's to ae's; added numerous DIV3s; changed MILESTONEs to TAILNOTE Ps; changed several Ps to CLOSER DATEs; removed fragment from middle of text; restructured TABLE. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected [dollar]s. Checked for &amp;cs with incorrect spacing. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs and endqs, abq's, oes, qs, Ae's, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections. Checked italic I / J and U / V. Checked for missing page GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTS. Checked CLOSERs, OPENERs, SIGNEDs, SALUTEs, TRAILERs, BYLINEs. Checked decorated initials. Checked FIGUREs. Sample: 2 minutes. Proofing: 0 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 50 minutes. DONE.</ITEM></CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="CME00131">
<STC T="M">131</STC>
<BIBNO T="mec">CME00131</BIBNO>
<VID>CME00131</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="enm">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>A VOLUME OF ENGLISH MISCELLANIES ILLUSTRATING THE HISTORY AND LANGUAGE OF THE NORTHERN COUNTIES OF ENGLAND.</P>
<P>Published for the Society BY ANDREWS &amp; CO., DURHAM; WHITTAKER &amp; CO., 2, WHITE HART STREET, PATERNOSTER SQUARE; BERNARD QUARITCH, 15. PICCADILLY; BLACKWOOD &amp; SONS, EDINBURGH.</P>
<P>1890</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="collection of miscellanies">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>ENGLISH MISCELLANIES.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="account">
<HEAD>I. AN ACCOUNT OF THE PROCEEDINGS IN A REMARKABLE CASE OF ADULTERATION AT YORK.</HEAD>
<HEADNOTE><P><HI REND="italic">[Reg. Civ. Ebor.</HI> A. Y. 255.]</P></HEADNOTE>
<P>IN ye name of God, Amen. Yt ys to hafe in mynde yat <NOTE PLACE="marg">1428.</NOTE> whare yar <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">The y represents the so-called thorn letter, which is generally used in this document.</NOTE> ys a Constitucion in ye crafte of Girdelers in ye cite of York, yat nane of yat crafte wirke any lede amang other metaill, bot yf yt be in souldour, for deceyvyng of ye kyng'ys people, of perill of a certayn payne, apon thys ane of ye Serche∣ours, sworn of ye sayd crafte, come befor John Aldstanemor, Mair of ye kynge's cite of Yorke, and other many, and be ye vertu of hys athe he present in a forfet of John Fysshe girdeler, made in hys crafte, for stuthes of xxxiij gyrdels of menged metaill agayn ye ordenaunce of hys crafte, and in deceyvyng of ye kynge's people, ye whilk John Fysshe, impeched befor ye Mair of yis trespasse, sayd yat he boght yat metaill of yase stuthes of John Lyllyng, whilk was proved and founden fals, for tin and lede was menged togedyr; and, wyth thys, grete rumour sprang in the people, yat yar was in cite of York now makers and utterers of fals osmundes, and yat Burn, smyth in Bouthum, and John Holgate, marsshall in the suburbe of Walmegate in York, suld make yam. And so John Burn come before ye sayde Mayr, and be hys athe, made opon the haly Evangill, he sayde yat he cutted aboute xxvj peces of fals Inglysh iryn of John Lyllyng of York mercer, at ye byddyng of hym, and made yam in shappe of osmundes, and als he sayd he wold
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
noght hafe had a pece of yam for a nother wyrkyng, and yay war made to blend with gude osmundes.</P>
<P>And ye sayd John Holgate come befor the sayd Mayr, and he, sworn apon a buke, sayd yat John Lyllyng sent hym with hys awen cariage iij<SUP>c</SUP> &amp; di. of landyren, and iiij<SUP>c</SUP> and mo peces of fals drosseyren, every hundreth of vj<SUP>xx</SUP> peces, to make in osmundes to menge with other, for ye whilk ye sayd John Holgate when he had wrought, he sayd he wald noght hafe gyfen iij d. for iiij stane of yam. He sayd, forther mar, yat the sayd John Lyllyng delyvered hym a osmund to make all other of the same shappe.</P>
<P>Item ye sayd John Lyllyng, when he was first examined of thys mater, he wald hafe sworn apon a buke befor ye sayd Mayr and other, had noght Thomas Bracebrygg counseld hym nay and lettid hym, yat he gart make bot xxvj peces, nor yat had na ma fals osmundes in hys house. And than ye sayd Mayr, after ye custume of ye cite, sent to ye Sercheours of ye Iren∣mangers of the cite of York yat John Stertavant Esquier, the Mayr Sergeant, and thay suld wend in to ye house of the sayd John Lyllyng to serche what osmundes he had with in hym at yat tyme; and so, att ye commandment of ye Mayr, yai yode, and serched, and yai fand yar ij barels of new made osmundes of drosse menged with gude osmundes, and other fals osmundes oute of barells. And the Mayr sent of yam to smyths to se be yayr crafte if yai war abill to putt in werk, and yar yai myght noght abyde ye hamer, bot brake in small peces. And also yai fand certein smale peces multen tyn menged with other metall, als wele is to shewe in ye chambre.</P>
<P>And, after this, come William Kyam of York merchaunt, and sayd to ye sayd Mayr and other that he was late at Hull, and come to John Bower stathe, and thar John Bower proferd to sell hym a laste of osmundes, and yar this William Kyam saw ij barells of osmundes market with ye marke of John Lyllyng, and he tuke uppe ye heued of a barell and yt semed gude abouen, and he opend ye heued of ye other barell and yt was bot drosse in pecys, and he come to John Bower and told hym lyke als he fand, and John Bower sayd hym yat he had sald sex barells of John Lyllyng's of yat same sorte, every barell for xij s.</P>
<P><PB N="3" REF="4"/>
Here apon, in ye Vigill of Peter and Paule Apostells, in ye yer of ye regne of Kyng Henre Sext after ye Conqueste fyft, the sayd John Lyllyng come befor ye sayd John Aldestanemore Mayr of York, Richard Russell newly Mayr of ye Staple and Calyse, William Bowes, John of Moreton, Thomas Gare, Henre Preston, Thomas Esyngwald, Thomas Bracebryg, William Ormesheued, Piers Bukcy, John Bolton, Aldermen, Guy Rou∣clyff Recorder, William Gryllyngton ane of ye Shirrefes, Thomas Doncastre, Geffray Sauvage, Robert Yarom, Th. Snawden, John Lofthouse, John Gascoyngne, Thomas Aton, Thomas Kyrham, William Bedall, William Gaytesheued, Thomas Davy, William Craven of ye xxiiij, and thar he was empeched of forgeyng of fals osmundes of drosse and of landyren, and of utteryng of yam in foule deceyte and ryght grete harme of ye kynge's people, and ryght gret sklaundre of ye cite of York, and agayne ye course of trewe marchandise; and to thys he answerd and sayd yat he perceyved wele yat iren waxed skant and dere, and he had mykyll with in hym of dross and land∣iren; and tharfor he gart forge yt in shapp of osmundes for utteryng of his iren so into Iseland and so he gart yarof, als he graunted, ix<SUP>xx</SUP> peces &amp; xij, and utterd many of yam at Hull and oyer places: and for this defaute he submit hym to abyde and fulfill ye jugement of ye Mayr and ye Counsell of ye chambre; and be ye avyse of ye Mayr and ye befor sayd Consell yt was awarded yat John Lyllyng suld fynd seurte of v<SUP>c</SUP> marke yat he suld abyde thaward of ye Mayr an ye Counseyll of ye chambre what tyme he war warned for tres∣passes abouensayd, als fer als fell to yair power or auctorite. And apon yis John Gascoigne and William Bedale become pleges and seurte for ye sayd John Lyllyng, yat he suld abyde and fulfill ye awarde of ye Mayr and ye Counsell what tyme he was warned. And als for a parcell of yair jugement and yair awarde at yat tyme, yai charged ye sayd John Lyllyng yat fra yan furth he suld bere ye kynge's pease to John Holgate mersshall and John Bron smyth abouensayd, wham he thret with bodily harme, for yai bar recorde agayne hym, and to all ye kynge's people, of payne of v<SUP>c</SUP> marke, to be raysed of ye landes and tenementes of ye sayd John Lyllyng, to ye oeps of
<PB N="4" REF="5"/>
our soverayne lorde ye kyng, yf he did any thyng agayne ye kynge's pease yat myght be proved apon hym lawfully in tyme comyng. And, over this, ye sayd Mayr and ye Counsell of ye sayd cite discharged ye said John Lyllyng of ye Counsell of the chambre, and of hys fredom of franchise of ye cite, and charged hym yat he suld noght occupy in bying nor in sellyng als a concitezin, bot als a straunger, nor yat he suld hald na shopp of his opyn within ye fraunchise of ye cite unto ye tyme yat ye Mayr and ye Counsell of ye chambre war in oyer maner avysed, and yat all hys fals osmundes in his house suld be broght in to ye chambre of counsell of ye sayd cite.</P>
<P>And wyth yis ye sayd John Lyllyng was accused and noysed amang mercers and other men, yat girdelers of ye citee had in thar houses fals tyn mengyd wyth other metaill yat was boght of hym, and so the Sercheours of ye Girdelers of yis cite, be commandement of ye Mayr, serched, be vertu of yair office, after ye custume of ye cite, and yai fand in yair crafte certayn peces in shappe and fourme of harowes, multen of tyn &amp; lede and pewtre to gedir, yat was selled for clene tyn, agayne course of clene marchandise, whilk was boght of John Lyllyng, and yase peces yai broght to ye Mayr in to ye chambre, and yat was wele funden and proved y<SUP>t</SUP> John Lyllyng had salde mykell swylk deceyvable tyn to bellemakers in to ye cuntre and other men, whar' thurgh ye cite was gretely greved, sclandered, and yai harmed.</P>
<P>And her' apon ye sayd John Lyllyng was examynd befor' John Aldestanemore Mair', Richard Russell, William Bowes, John Moreton, Thomas Gar', Henry Preston, Thomas Brace∣brygg, William Ormesheued, Piers Bukcy, aldermen, Guy Rouclif recordour, John Bromflet, William Grillyngton, shirrefs, John Hewik, Thomas Doncastre, Thomas More, Thomas Snawdon, Robert Yarom, Th. Davy, Thomas Aton, Thomas Kyrkham, William Bedale, William Gaytesheued, John Gas∣coigne, William Craven, Richard Louthe of ye xxiiij<SUP>or</SUP>, ye last day of Juyll, in ye yer' of ye kyng beforsayde, bathe of fals osmundes makyng and utteryng, &amp; castyng of fals tyn menged with lede and pewer', and sellyng of yt deceyvabely for gude tyn to girdelers and to bellemakers and other persons, and to yis
<PB N="5" REF="6"/>
poyntes John Lyllyng sayd yat he bad John Holgate mersshall make hym ploghstrakes of drosse and landyren yat he sent hym and na osmundes, and yat John Holgate, beyng thar' present befor ye sayd Mair' and Counsell in presence of John Lyllyng, swor' apon a buke and sayd yat John Lyllyng bad hym yat he suld make hym osmundes of ye drosse and landyren yat he sent hym and na plughstrakes, and delyvered hym a osmund to make yam aft', and the same John Holgate sayd yat ye same day he was arested John Lyllyng come unto hym and promped hym, and bad hym say yat he cutt hym bot a hundreth of landyren yat he sent hym, and bot yf he sayd so he myght na langer abyde in ye sayd citee, and yat this was trew ye sayd John Holgate proferd to prove yt wyth hys handes apon John Lyllyng, yf he wald agaynesay this. And so John Lyllyng, seand yat he myght na langer be ryght deny nor defend this mater na langer, he knawleged and graunted his trespas of forgeyng and utteryng of fals osmunds and castyng of fals tyn, in deceyvyng and harmyng of ye kynge's people, and singuler lucre to hym self, and ryght grete sclander to ye said cite, lyked als yt is reherced befor; and in hegh and lawe he submyt hym to ye grace and awarde of ye Mayr and Counsell of ye chambre how yai wald ordayne hym to do for all his trespas reherced abouen; And so ye Mayr and ye Counsell of ye chambre, con∣sideryng ye law submission of ye sayd John Lyllyng, yat tha tuke hym to yair grace in all poyntes yat pertiend to yair power and auctoryte, and yarfor John Lyllyng prayed ye Mayr and ye Consell yat yai wald hafe hym fro open shame and velany, and restor hym to hys franchise of ye cite, and asked what yai wald aske hym yar for; and yt was answerd by yat yai wald aske hym no peny. And yan John Lyllyng tuke avysement, and of his free and propre will he prayed yam yat yai wald vouchesaufe to restor hym to hys fredom of ye cite, and take of hym yarfor c li. to ye oeps and profet of ye co'alte of ye cite, and, if yt lyket yam to take yat of hym, he wald hald hym ryght wele content, and yat yai wald be gude lordes, maisters, and frendes to hym; and whar yai myght be custum of ye cite hafe brynte his fals chafer openly in syght of ye people, to his overe mykell shame and reprove, yai takyng tendyr hede to ye lawly
<PB N="6" REF="7"/>
submission and his besy prayers, yai restor hym agayne to his franches for c li. yat he proferd, wyth yis yat yf any girdeler, or any oyer man compleynd of hym for any fals osmundes, or fals tyn, or any oyer fals marchandise, yat he had sald yam, yat he suld ac∣cord wyth yam and make yam amendes; and ye Mayr hyght hym yat yf he wald lait yam wytt to helpe to trete wyth yam to make end, yf any compleyned of hym: and ye same John Lyllyng was charged to send all ye fals osmundes and fals tyn yat was in his house at yat tyme in to ye chambre, and so he sent in ij barels of fals osmundes, and sythen was funden half a duzan fals tyn of ye same John Lyllyng in handes of ye shirrefs whilk are brogh into ye chambre.</P>
<P>Forthermar', ye sayd John Lyllyng was noysed yat he suld hafe blended plaster or lyme amang his alom, and so seld yt furth deceyvabilly to lytsters, and, in especial, to John Kyrkby and Robert Dowfe, lytsters of York, and so yai war' sent for and examynyd of yis mater; and John Kyrkby sayd yat he boght of John Lyllyng a porcion of alom, and fand yar' in lyke als yt had beyn plaster and lyme, and if he had wrogh yt in yat kynd yt suld hafe brynt oute his lede bothom, of ye whilk plaster and lyme a sample ys redy in ye chambre to shew.</P>
<P>And Robert Dowfe lytster sais yat he boght of John Lyllyng a c alom, and he syfted oute of yt half a bushell of plaster and lyme and kest yt away for yt wald hafe brynt his lede and he had wroght yt.</P>
<P>And also yar ar in ye chambre xxxiij girdils harnassed as fals tyne, agains ye ordenance of ye Girdelers, ye whilk tyn was boght of John Lyllyng for clene tyn a gude als ys rehersid befor'; and when John Lyllyng was examynid and blamed for yat fals tyn, he answerd and sayd he boght yt of a man in London in ye same kynde, and yar' he was asked of what man of London he boght yt, he sayd he wist noght what his name was; and so he counseld and biddyn noght to sclandyr in na maner bot say fully ye treuthe and let for na shame, and yan he submytt hym, als ys reherced abouen.</P>
<P>And after y<SUP>t</SUP>, ye xij day of August, ye yer abouen sayde, John Aldestanemor' Mayr, Ric' Russell, John Moreton, Thomas Esyngwald, Th. Bracebryg, Piers Bukcy, John Bolton, aldermen,
<PB N="7" REF="8"/>
John Hewyt, Thomas Doncastre, Th. More, Robert Yarum, Thomas Aton, William Bedall, William Craven, John Doding∣ton, of xxiiij, John Bronnflete and William Stillyngton shirrefs, and John Pygott man of law wythalden of ye counsell of ye chambre, war gedird to ye chambre, and yar att yat tyme come Maistre John Selow chanon residencier of ye kyrk of Yorke, Maistre John Carleton, Th. Haselay clerk of ye crown, and Robert Manfeld marsshall in ye kynge's hostell, and yar made grete instance and prayers to ye Mair and gude men to doo ease and favor to ye sayd John Lyllyng, at ye reverence of our soverane lady ye quene, and of ye archibisshopp of York, wham ye quene had spoken to first, and sythen writen unto for yat same mater, and als at ye reverence of ye Lord Beaumont, whilk had writen to Maister John Selowe to pray in his name for ease of ye sayd John Lyllyng, and yar' ye Mairr and ye gudemen abouen sayd gaf yam to answer yat yis mater touched all ye gude men of ye consell of ye chambre, and ye coīalte of yis cite, and many of ye consell of ye chambre at yat tyme war absent, with oute wham yai myght gif yam nane answer at yt tyme, and yar for yai wald gedir to gedir mare fully ye Counsell of ye citee, and gif yam an answer, and yat yai suld send upon Monday next folowyng certen gude men of ye chambre to Cawod, to common with ye archibisshop for yis mater, and be his con∣sell and ye consell of ye citee yai suld so doo yat our soverrayn lady ye quene, and ye archibisshopp, and y<SUP>e</SUP> Lord Beaumont, and Haseley suld well understand, and for y<SUP>t</SUP> yair praiers suld stand John Lyllyng to availl.</P>
<P>And yan, in ye Vigil of ye Assumpcion of our Lady, ye yer beforesayd, John Aldestonemor Mair, Richardus Russell, John Moreton, Thomas Gare, Thomas Esyngwalde, Thomas Brace∣brig, Piers Bukcy, John Bolton, aldermen, Guy Rouclyf re∣cordour, John Bromflete, William Gril[ing]ton shirrefs, John Hewyk, Thomas Doncastre, Thomas More, Gefferay Sauvage, Thomas Snaudon, Robert Yarum, John Loftehouse, John Gas∣coigne, Thomas Aton, William Craven, Th. Kyrkeham, John Louthe, John Warde, William Bedale, William Gaytesheued, Ric' Louth of ye numbre of xxiiij, Thomas Gare ye yonger, Richard Russell, Nicholas Usflete, chambirlanes, and Thomas
<PB N="8" REF="9"/>
Ward, war assembled her' in the chambre, and yar Thomas Haseley, clerke of the crown, and Robert Manfeld, be fore sayd, made grete instance and prayers eftesones for ease of the sayd John Lyllyng, and yat mater was putt in respite to that tyme.</P>
<P>And yan, apon ye morn of ye feste of ye Assumpcion of oure Ladye next efter, yar' was gedyrde in ye chambre, John Aldestanemore Mayre, Richard Russell, William Bowes, John of Moreton, Thomas Gare, Henry Preston, Thomas Esyngwald, Thomas Bracebryg, Piers Bukcy, John Bolton, aldermen, John Pygot man of lawe, John Brounflete, William Grillyngton, shirrefs, John Hewyk, Thomas Doncastre, Thomas More, Geffray Sauvage, Thomas Snaudon, Robert Yarum, John Gas∣coigne, William Craven, Thomas Aton, Thomas Kyrkeham, William Bedale, William Gaytesheued, John Warde, Richard Louth, of the numbre of xxiiij, and yar befor yam come ye beforsayd John Lyllyng, and in yar presence and Haseley's the clerke of the croun and Robert Manfeld, cosyn to ye same John Lyllyng, he knawleged and, witht oute distresse or fere done to hym in worde or in dede, he wilfully and openly confessed yat he was gylty and coulpabyll of all ye trespasse abouen sayd yat he was impeched of befor, and for yas trespasse he besoght ye Maire and ye gude men of ease of his paymentȝ, and yar [and] yan he was asked yf he couth or wald say or compleyne yat the Mair and ye Counsell of the chambre had done hym any wrong in yis matiers, and he sayd nay, nor yat he couth noght, nor wald noght say yat ye Mair and ye Consell of the chambre had done hym any manere of wrang in yis matiere, bot y<SUP>t</SUP> he is wele paied of all yat yai had done; and so ye sayd John Lyllyng was voided; and yan Thomas Haseley and Robert Manfeld made grete prayers for lessenyng of ye sumes of ye paymentȝ of ye sayd John Lyllyng. And her apon avyce taken, yt was gifen yam for answer at yat tyme yat ye Mair and ye gude men sulde send certeyn men of ye chambre to the archibisshopp vnto Cawod on Monday yan nexte commyng to commone with hym in yis mater, and take his consell and avys yar in; and, after yat, yai suld so doo yat the parties yat melled for John Lyllyng suld hald yam plesed. And her apon yai chesed Richard Russell, Thomas Bracebryg, aldermen, Gui Rouclyff, recordour, William
<PB N="9" REF="10"/>
Craven, Thomas Aton, to wend to Cawod for yat cause to commone w<SUP>t</SUP> ye archibisshopp on Monday yan next folowyng; and in ye mene tyme ye Mair and ye gude men war enfourmed yat yat Monday ye archibisshopp myght noght be at Cawod for other occupacions yat he had to doo utteward, and yerfor he assigned yam ye Wednesday next after to be befor hym at Cawod. At the whylk Wednesday Richard Russell and oyer per∣sones next befor nevend, yay war at Cawod for yis mater, and yai war thar honorabely receyved be the archibisshopp, and commond wyth him of ye maters abouen sayd; apon whylk commonyng, when yai come hame, was done afterwarde als her fast folowys.</P>
<P>The xxj day of August, ye yer of the kyng befor sayd fifte, John Aldestanemor Maire, Richard Russell, William Bowes, John of Moreton, Henry Preston, Thomas Esyngewald, Thomas Bracebryg, Piers Bukcy, John of Bolton, aldermen, Guy Rouclyf recordour, John Brounflete, William Grillyngton, shirrefs, John Hewyk, Thomas Mor, John Waghen, Robert Yarum, John Gascoigne, William Craven, Thomas Aton, Thomas Kyrkeham, William Bedale, William Gaytesheued, John Warde, of the xxiiij, war assembled her in the chambre of Counsell, whar ye sayd Richard Russell, Thomas Bracebryg, Guy Rouclif, William Craven and Thomas Aton declared yar commyng to Cawod, and ye fourme of yar commyng yar wyth to the archebisshopp, and of yar departyng fra hym. And apon yis declaracion made, ye Consell of ye chambre tuke yar avyse what yam semed and lykyd best to do in yis mater, and yar ye Mair and ye Consell tenderli considred ye lettres and prayers of our soveran lady ye quene, whilk sho had sent to ye arche∣bisshopp for John Lyllyng, and ye bysy prayers of ye arche∣bisshopp, als of Haseley and Robert Manfeld, yai assented yat ane obligacion of ye said John Lyllyng and of John Gascon of xl marc, whylke suld hafe ben payed at ye fest of Seint Hillare next commyng, and also an obligacyon of a statute merchant of fyfe hundreth mark, in ye whilk ye forsayd John Lyllyng was bundon to Richard Russell, William Bowes and to oyer, to be payed at ye fest of Michelmes yan next folowyng, and a defesance made yer apon yat ye sayd John Lyllyng fra yan furth suld be of gude governaunce and trew in all hys bying
<PB N="10" REF="11"/>
and hys sellyng wyth outen any gylory, fraude, or deceyt, als falleȝ a trew merchaunt to doo and by and sell after treu cource of merchantdyse, suld be delyverd to Haseley and Robert Manfelde, and so John Lyllyng be quyt of yam. And her apon even furth wyth yais ij obligacions and ye defesance was taken and delyverd to Haseley and Robert Manfeld and cancelled, and yai thanked ye Mayr and all ye gudemen hertly for y<SUP>t</SUP> yay had done be reverence of ye quene's prayers and ye archi∣bisshopp, and yairs, and behight sothely yat yai suld make relacion to ye quene, and yai suld wele see and knawe yat ye quene sulde thanke yam yerfor in tyme comyng. And her apon John of Bolton, alderman, at his first commyng fra ye parle∣ment, delyvered a lettre fra ye quene to ye Mair, in ye whilk lettre sho thanked ye Mair and all ye gudemen of yis citee of ease and favour yai had shewed at the reverence of hir prayer to John Lyllyng, mercer of York, etc.</P>
<P>'Vnto his wirshipfull Mair, and ye Aldermen, and all ye wirshipfull Counsell of ye cite of York shewes, if it lyke vn to youre wirshipfull and wyse discrecion, your concitezin, John Lyllyng, yat it was never my wyll forto offend ne forto attempte any thyng yat langeȝ to yis wirshipfull cite; and, wirshipfull sires, what at has bene done or sayd touchyng my person it is noght vn knawen vnto you, bot I put na defaute in nane yat langes to yis wirshipfull citee, ne noght wyll, bot neveryeles ye charge is to me full hevy and grevous forto ber yat is put vnto me, after ye grete losses yat I have had and sustened be diverses ways, als it is wele knawen to diverses gude men of yis cite; whafore I pray you and besekes you for the grete mercie of God, yat yhe will deme yis matier after gude con∣science, and as yhe trow yat God wyll yerof be most plesed, for I am hee that wyll noght offend your wyll, ne your ordinance, nor na nother suyte make be fully forto be demed be you in hegh and in laghe; besekyng you alway wyth al my hert to be gude maisters and frendes to me, and gif me your gude worde and to graunt me your gude hertes for the werke of the haly charite. In ye witnes of ye whilk thynge, to yis byll I have put to my seal; writen ye last day of January, in ye yer of ye reigne of Kyng Henri sext after ye conquest of Ingland sext'</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="collection of documents">
<PB N="11" REF="12"/>
<HEAD>II. VERDICTS OF THE SEARCHERS CALLED IN TO DECIDE ABOUT ENCROACHMENTS, ETC., IN THE CITY OF YORK.</HEAD>
<HEADNOTE><P>[From the York City Books.]</P></HEADNOTE>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<HEAD>Judicium Scrutatorum de terris et tenementis domus Sancti Leonardi, et Roberti Feriby, ex opposito cimiterii Omnium Sanctorum super Pavimentum, ex parte boriali.</HEAD>
<P>For als mykill als we John Ampilford, John Thorp, masons, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Mar., 1417.</NOTE> William Cunsby and John Mosse, wryghts, sercheours of our craftes wyth in the franchise of York, fyndes that a party of the ferrest post of Robert of Feriby standys on Seint Leonard grunde, and that thar ys a cruke of Robert Feriby grund, fra the prive un to the streteward, and a nother cruke of Seint Leonard's fra abouen the myddilpost un to the thrid post, tharfor we award that fra the sole end of the frunt before in to the streteward, un to the third post on the base stane of Robert of Feriby, be drawen a lyne just, and set just Seint Leonard grunde, after that betwix party and party.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">Reg. Civ. Ebor.</HI> A. Y. 173.]</P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>John Ampilford, John Thorp, masons, William Cunsby and John Mosse, wryghts, sercheours of masons and wryghts in the citee of York, chosen be the assent of partys for to dissevir a grounde of a tenement anent Al Halow Kyrk garth wall on the Pament, betwix the Dene and the Chapitre of the Kyrk of York of the ta party, and the Maistre and the Freres of the Hospitale of Seynt Leonard's of York on the other party, demys that a lyne be drawen fra the fore poste before fra the oute syde of the poste before to the oute syde of the poste behynd of Seynt Leonard's in to thair garthwarde, and set Seynt Leonard wall apon thair awen ground, fra post to post, for we fynde well that the mynster beres the ta syde of Seynt Leonard flore. And we demys that the stane that ys taken doun be departyd in twa, and gyf half un to the ta party and the other half un to other party.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<PB N="12" REF="13"/>
<P>John Ampilford, John of Thorp, William Cunsby, and John Mosse, sercheours of the masons and the wryghtes, chosen be the assent of partys to dyssever ground bitwix the Maister and the Freres of the Hospitall of Seynt Leonard's of York of a party, and Sir John Esyngwald, preste of the chauntery of Seynt Nicholas in the parysh kyrk of Seynt Trinite in Gothrom∣gate, of the other party, awardes and demys that the postys of the alde house of Seynt Leonard's be set in be tham of Seynt Leonard's, so that a lyne may be layde to the oute syde of the poste of the newe howse of Sir John Esyngwald, and drawen lyne ryght un to the poste of the kylne howse of the same Sir John of hys tenement in Gothromgate.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>John Ampilford, John of Thorp, William Cunsby, and John Mosse, serchours of the masons and wryghtes, chosen to dissever grounde in Peseholm betwix Sir Robert Irton, prest of a chauntery in Seint Savourkirk, and Thomas Duffeld, sonne and ayre un to Richard Duffeld Esquier, demys that the hedge fra the corner of the foresayd Sir Robert house un to Fosse syde be Thomas Duffeld, als the stakes are dryfen; and that Thomas Duffeld hafe sextene yerdys over thwart of the garthe fra the wall of Sir John Darthington, person of the chauntery of Seynt Mary Magdalayn in the mynster of York, un to the netherest stake safe ane; and that the foresayd Sir Robert hafe fra the same stake fyfe yerdys of garth, over thwart un tyll hys awen hedge, that standys on the weste syde.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>We, sercheours of the masons and wryghtes of the cite of <NOTE PLACE="marg">Sept. 22, 1417.</NOTE> York, demys that John Hesill sall ga lyne right fra the bak syde of hys post that standys in hys hall hend un to hys sole in hys house that he byggys. And that John of Langton sall set in hys poste fote that Hesyll may hafe rowme thar to lay hys sole, and rayse hys house in North strete.—</P><TAILNOTE><P><HI REND="italic">Id.</HI> 177<HI REND="italic">b.</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
<CLOSER><DATE>Fest. S. Maurice, 6th Hen. V.</DATE></CLOSER>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>We, serchours of the masons and the wrightes, demys, for ease <NOTE PLACE="marg">Oct. 9, 1417.</NOTE>
<PB N="13" REF="14"/>
of bathe partyes, to take that stuffe of the gutters of lede that thar ys for the ta party the tane hafe, and for the othere party the other half, and that the water be ledde downe of thair bather coste, fra the thrid poste of the house of Dame Alice Plumpton fra the waterward of Use, be a pype of lede closed wyth a loker, and that for cause that John Talkan walles the forsayd Alice all endelang thurgh and thurgh.—</P><TAILNOTE><P><HI REND="italic">Id.</HI> 178<HI REND="italic">a.</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
<CLOSER><DATE>Fest. S. Dennis, 6th Hen. V.</DATE></CLOSER>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>We, serchours of the masons and wryghts of the cite of York, awarde that Thomas Bernard gutter of hys costage betwix his tenement that William Garnet dwellys in, endelyng fra the newe poste of Durant chauntery in Crouce kirk, als ferre als that newe house of that chauntery lastys, and bryng of his coste the watergate overthwarte at the ende of the same newe house, so that the water comme downe in a pipe of lede by the alde poste that standys by the walle of John of Moreton; and that the same Thomas Bernard hafe all the alde stuffe of lede that lay thare before, endelang and overthwart, and y<SUP>t</SUP> the fore∣sayd Thomas walle hys awen house behynd the dese of the hall of the foresayd chauntery for als mykill that the chauntery gutters lyin thare. And also yat the foresayd Thomas make hys pryve fensilble als it awe to be.—</P><TAILNOTE><P><HI REND="italic">Id.</HI> 178<HI REND="italic">b.</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>We, sercheours of the masons and the wryghtes of the citte <NOTE PLACE="marg">11 Feb., 1419.</NOTE> of York, at the assignement of the Mair, awarde and deme that John of Langton hafe even uppe thurgh oute als mykyll ground in breide als he hafes in the frount before at his tenement in the parysh of Seint Laurence wyth oute Walmegate barr in the suburbes of York, that ys in the holdyng of Robert Duffeld, cordewaner, als that tenement and the gardyn lyse thare betwix the grounde of Sir William Ottelay, the maistre of the Trinites' at Fossebryg hende on the a syde, and the grounde of Nicholas Northfolk on the other syde, and buttes apon the kynge's strete of Walmegate before, and on the north felde behynd.—</P><TAILNOTE><P><HI REND="italic">Id.</HI> 181<HI REND="italic">a.</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
<CLOSER><DATE>11 Feb, 6th Hen. V.</DATE></CLOSER>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<PB N="14" REF="15"/>
<P>For als mykill als Maister Thomas Haxey, Tresorer of the <NOTE PLACE="marg">Feb., 1419.</NOTE> Cathedrale Kirk of Seint Peter of York, and other Chanons of the same kirk compleyned un to the Meir and un to the gude men of the cite of York that the kynge's dyke betwix Bouthum∣barr and Munkbarr was so stopped, that the water myght noght hafe issue, for the whilk defaute a close of the erche∣bisshope was drowned yerly, and also, diverse tymes, thaire gardyns in the self manere, and also thaire halles and thaire houses of office of som of tham; and than, be the assent of the Meir and the chanons and the gude men thay went bathe the partys to gyder to se the defautes, and when thay had seen the defautes, it was accorded and assented be bathe the partys that the sercheours of the masons and of the wryghtes of this cite of York suld ga and see what were ryght for ayther party; and, apon thys, the sercheours was warned that they suld ga serche and see and do ryght to ayther party, and that thay went and serched, and demed, and awarded that the Tresorer and the person of Seint John kyrk of Pyke gar remove thayre pryves that standys upon the kynge's dyke, and all other also that hafes any pryves standyng thare apon, betwene the barrys beforesayd; and that thay and all other gar clense of thaire costages all the foresayd pryves and rutes, wedys and erthe, that hafes ben casten thar out of thaire gardyns or thayre houses be any of thaire servants, the whilk lettys the water to hafe the ryght issue; and that all dores that opyns apon the dyke be closed, and all the bryggys taken away that na man hafe na entre un to the kynge's walles bot at bathe the endys; and that nane entir, neyther at the endys na ellys whare, to defoule the walles na the motes, bot thay that has taken tham to ferme, the whilke sall kytte the herbage that grewys apon the mote.—</P><TAILNOTE><P><HI REND="italic">Id.</HI> 181<HI REND="italic">a.</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
<CLOSER><DATE>Ult. Feb. 6, Hen. V.</DATE></CLOSER>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<HEAD>Judicium Johannis Ampilford, Johannis Thorp, Willelmi Cun∣nesby, et Johannis Mosse, scrutatorum cementariorum et carpentariorum Ebor., redditum xxj<SUP>mo</SUP> die Maii anno regni regis Henrici Quinti septimo.</HEAD>
<P>We awarde that a lyne be drawen lyneryght, thre inches <NOTE PLACE="marg">May 22, 1419.</NOTE> wyth in the poste of John Brynnand, that standes to the strete∣ward,
<PB N="15" REF="16"/>
un to the myddys of William of Seleby poste, that standys at the ende of the werkhouse, and that twa postes of John Brynnand be set in of hys coste by Tyseday nexte, that ys fled once, so that William of Seleby may rayse up hys howe besyde hym, als custume and maner ys in the cite of York.—</P><TAILNOTE><P><HI REND="italic">Id.</HI> 182<HI REND="italic">b.</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>We sercheours of the masons and of the wryghts of the citee of York, awarde that William Acom wryght make of hys cost the wryght note of a gutter betwix the newe house of Robert Hovyngham in Boutham that William Acom made, and the hall; and y<SUP>t</SUP> thare be a gutter made betwix the tenement of Seynt Mary abbay, and the forsayd house of Robert Hovyng∣ham, of the abbay's coste and Robert Hovyngham, so y<SUP>t</SUP> the water may rynne betwix the abbay grunde and Robert Hovyngham; and y<SUP>t</SUP> Robert Hovyngham sall make, of hys propre coste, at the other ende of hys house, a knyttyng; and that the hedge of the este syde of Hovyngham house be Robert Hovyngham.—</P><TAILNOTE><P><HI REND="italic">Id.</HI> 184<HI REND="italic">b.</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>Sercheours of the masons and of the wryghtes awardes <NOTE PLACE="marg">Nov. 18, 1420.</NOTE> betwix William of Alne of the a perty, and the executors, heirs and assignes of William Pountfreyt, of the other party, that for als mykyll that William of Alne in hys tenement in Coppergate in York walles even uppe thurgh fra the grunde uppe to the panne, that yerfore the executors, heirs, and the assignes of William Pountfreyt make the gutter of lede fra the newe house of William of Alne, that ys nowe hys buttre, endelang downe un to a newe house of William of Alne toward Fosse; and that William of Alne, of his costes, sall fynde the brygges, the scaches, nayles, and all the tymbre that sall ga un to the gutter; and the executors, heirs, or assignes of William Pountfreyt sall pay for the werkemanshippe of the gutter makyng; and thay sall hafe all the lede that ys thare nowe, and perfourmys the remenand of thayr costes, and fra thys tyme that gutter sall be the heirs and the assignes of William of Pountfreyt; and thay
<PB N="16" REF="17"/>
sall uppehalde it alleway of thayre coste; and also that at the hall head to the kyrkward the heirs and the assignes of William Pountfreyt, als farre als thayre syde house gas, sall bryng furthe, all of thayre coste, thayre water into the foresayd gutter, for William of Alne hafes a upperyghte gavell.—</P><TAILNOTE><P><HI REND="italic">Id.</HI> 189<HI REND="italic">a.</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
<CLOSER><DATE>18 Nov., 1420.</DATE></CLOSER>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>Johannes Ampilford mason, serchour, sworn of the masons <NOTE PLACE="marg">Aug. 4, 1422.</NOTE> wyth in the cite of York, John Hexham, Thomas Cunnysburgh serchours of the wryghtes, and William Cunnysby, wryght.</P>
<P>The assent of the partyes before the Maire to deme of certayne thynge under writyn, thay awarde and deme that the perclose that standys betwix the entre and the shop, and all other percloses, the pryve wyth the closet, and the selours, the trelys wyndowe at the somer hall, the glasse wyndows, the bynkes, the paved flore, the herth yt are in the house whare the wyfe of Symond of Stele dwellys in, and the falle wyndow to ye streteward abyde still wyth the place, als byggyngs and purtenance of the same place, and yat the lede pype and the shelfs be the wyfe's of Symond of Stele.—</P><TAILNOTE><P><HI REND="italic">Id.</HI> 192<HI REND="italic">b.</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
<CLOSER><DATE>4 Aug., 8th Hen. V.</DATE></CLOSER>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>Memorandum, that thys ys the award and the jugement of <NOTE PLACE="marg">Aug. 12, 1420.</NOTE> John Ampilford, John of Thorp, John Hexham, and Thomas Cunsburgh sercheours, sworne of the masons and of the wryghts, in the cite of York, assigned and lymyt by Thomas of Gare, Mayr of the same cite, wyth the full assent of bathe partyes, to serche and to deme of a stane walle that lyggys in lengthe fra the kynge's strete of Conyngstrete bifore downe thurgh un to the water of Ouse bihynd, betwix a tenement of Sir John of Langton Knyght in the haldyng of John Rumby, of the a party, and a tenement of William Selby, in the haldyng of John of Sutton lytster, of the other partye: that the walle of the werk∣house of John of Sutton ys William Selby awen, fra the water of Ouse un to the post that standys thare and reches to the grounde anent the lede in the same werkhouse, and fra theyn all uppe
<PB N="17" REF="18"/>
thurgh in to the strete, that William Selby hafe rowme and space abouen on the walle of stane to hys tenement ward to ryste hys tymbre apon, als he has done before tyme; and that Sir John Langton hafe rowme and space abouen the same stane walle to hys tenement ward to ryste hys tymbre apon, als it has bene in tymes before. And als farre als Sir John Langton has byggyd a newe house betwix the werkhouse beforesayd and the stane house toward the kynge's strete, yay awarde and deme that William Selby hafe abouen the same walle space to ryst hys walleplat apon, als he dyd before, als wele at the ta nende als at the other; and that hathe the stanewerk and tymberwerk that John Rumby had gart newe sette abouen the same stane walle at that hend towarde the stone house be taken away, so that yt lette noght William Selby to herber hys tymber apon the same walle; and that bathe the partyes make and uppehalde the gutter, als ferre als yt reches, of thayre bather costages, and that the stuffe of lede that ys thare nowe be ayther partyes. </P><TAILNOTE><P><HI REND="italic">Id.</HI> 192-3</P></TAILNOTE>
<CLOSER><DATE>12 Aug., 1420.</DATE></CLOSER>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>We, serchours of the masons and wryghtes of the cite of York, assigned be William Ormesheued, mayr of ye same cite, lyke als we hafe bene assigned, charged, and commaunded be other Maires to serche, deme, and dyssever ye grunde of Kalom hall in ye haldyng of John of Preston irenmangar fra ye grunde of Margaretes y<SUP>t</SUP> was ye wyfe of Adam Hetche, and how y<SUP>t</SUP> ye ta grunde sall be closed fra ye tother, awarde and deme y<SUP>t</SUP> a lyne be drawn stryght fra ye corner of ye stathe of ye chauntery of Syr Thomas Pynchebek, un to ye nexte corner of ye stathe of ye common place, in ye haldyng of Ainderby sadler &amp; Wyntryngham smyth; and y<SUP>t</SUP> at ye middeward of yat lyne be set a stake, and fra y<SUP>t</SUP> stake drawe a lyne even uppe un to an ald poste of a house at ye over ende of ye hedge of Mergaretes Hetche, and y<SUP>t</SUP> yan John Preston close hym als y<SUP>t</SUP> lyne delys fra ye ta nende un to ye tother.—</P><TAILNOTE><P><HI REND="italic">Id.</HI> 198</P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<PB N="18" REF="19"/>
<P>31 Jan. 20th Hen. VI.—M<SUP>d</SUP> yat yis is jugementes &amp; award <NOTE PLACE="marg">Jan. 31, 1442.</NOTE> of John Ampilford, John Bould, masons, John Bolron &amp; William Warter, cappenters, &amp; serchours of ye same craftes, yat is to say, yat ye stone wall bitwix ye tenement of John of Bolton, citizin &amp; marchant of York, on y<SUP>t</SUP> oon party, &amp; tenement of yabbot &amp; convent of Cristall, on yat other party, in Mikelgate in York is holy &amp; fully ye wall of ye said John of Bolton, and yat al ye ease yat ye said Abbot has of ye said wall is thurgh sufferanse &amp; paciens of ye same John of Bolton. And ye same day and ye same yere Alice Semer, neuly awner &amp; possessor of said tenement of John of Bolton, swore &amp; opinly affermed for treweth yat John Lofthouse, &amp; other of ye deputȝ of ye said Abbot &amp; convent w<SUP>t</SUP>drewe ye said wall unknawinge to ye said Alice.</P>
<P>And ye same day, we, ye said serchours, were and serched a tenement of ye said John of Bolton in Petergate, in ye tenur of John Wetelay, &amp; we fynd yat ye same place has taken mikel herm for defaut of a gutter, ye whilk shuld be betwix ye said place &amp; tenement of Thomas Holme, ye whilk gutter ye same Thomas Holme shuld make &amp; reparell, to save &amp; isshewe ye wattere fro ye said place of John of Bolton.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">Enrolment Book Civ. Ebor.</HI> B. Y. 87.]</P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>M<SUP>d</SUP>, that we, Thomas Gaytclyff, John Gaycok, serchours of <NOTE PLACE="marg">March 9, 1468.</NOTE> masounes within yis citee of York, John Forster, &amp; John Meidlay alias Williamson, serchours of wryghtes w<SUP>t</SUP>in ye saide citee, have bene &amp; takyn of a grounde yat stode in variaunce bitwix thabbot &amp; Convent of Rivaux, on that oon partie, &amp; the Dene &amp; Chapiter of ye cath' kyrke of Seint Peter in York, on that other partie, lying buttyng opon ye water in Laierthorp, in subarbes of the saide citee, buttyng opon ye water of Fosse at the weest ende, and on a lane y<SUP>t</SUP> leedes from ye hie strete of Laierthorp unto ij closeȝ belangyng som tyme to ye personage of Seint Marye kyrke in Layrethorp, and, accordyng to ye custume of ye same citee, ye ix day of Marce, ye viij yere of ye reigne of Kyng Edwarde ye iiij, by ye comaundement of William Snawesill, yan beyng Mare of the same citee, and, after
<PB N="19" REF="20"/>
ye examinacion, good advise, &amp; grete deliberacion by us hadde, as wele by substanciall wrytyng undre sealeȝ, as by ye instruc∣cion &amp; recorde of honest personnes, havyng perfite notice &amp; knawlynge of ye saide grounde, we have demed yat ye tennauntes of ye said Abbotes &amp; Convent have wrangwisly halden &amp; occupies xviij poules feet of ye grounde of ye saide Deaneȝ &amp; Chapiter, the whiche xviij fote of ground we have demed &amp; awarded shalbe departed from ye grounde of ye saide Abbot &amp; Convent, and delivered &amp; laide unto ye grounde of ye saide Deane &amp; Chapiter, to have &amp; to halde to yayme &amp; to yare successours for evermore, etc.—</P><TAILNOTE><P><HI REND="italic">Id.</HI> 331<HI REND="italic">a.</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>Memorandum, that yis is ye awarde and juygement of William Hyndeley, John Sutton, John Haxby, ande Richard Bisshop, serchiours of ye masons and wrightes in the cite of Yorke, assigned ande lymytt by William Lambe, Maire of ye city of Yorke, with the full assente and consente of William Snawsell Aldreman of ye saide cite, for his partye, and S<SUP>r</SUP> William Watson, vicare of Saynte Georg churche in Fisshergate, ruler ande gouvernor of a chaunterie belongyng to the saide churche, on y<SUP>t</SUP> othir partie, to serche ande deme a gutter apon a tenement in Walmegate in Yorke, perteynyng to the saide chaunterie, and a pales perteynyng to a tenement of the saide William Snawsell, nowe in ye halding of one Robert Yereslay, at the este ende of Fosse brigge in Walmegate; firste, the saide iiij serchiours awardes ande demes betuyx the saide partieȝ, for thair bother ease, yat ye forsaide William Snawsell shall abide w<SUP>t</SUP> the voydance of y<SUP>e</SUP> waterfall of ye forsaide gutter, and, in like forme, the saide vicare, as by right ande duete belongyng to ye saide chaunterie, shall bere the charge of ye uphaldinge ande makyng of ye forsaide pales at alle dayes, at his owen propre costes ande expenseȝ.—</P><TAILNOTE><P><HI REND="italic">Id.</HI> 331<HI REND="italic">a.</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>The xxiij<SUP>ti</SUP> day of the moneth of Octobr, in the xv<SUP>th</SUP> yere of <NOTE PLACE="marg">Oct. 23, 1479.</NOTE> Kinge Edward the iiij<SUP>t</SUP>, William Hyndeley, John Shupton, masons, John Hirste ande Christofr More, carpentours, iiij serchiours
<PB N="20" REF="21"/>
w<SUP>t</SUP>in the saide cite, cam in thair propre personnes in the counsail chambre, afore the Maire aboun saide, ande there and thanne made thaire bodelye otheȝ uppon the holy Evangelist truely forto serche the meteȝ ande boundeȝ of a certayn grounde of John Gillyot of Yorke, Aldreman and merchaunt, adjonyng upon ane oyere grounde of William Rakett th'elder, and Thomas Aslacby. Where apon and incontinent after, the said daye and yere, the forsaide serchiours, accordinge to the custume of the same cite, ande by th'assentes ande desiers aswele of the forsaid John Gillyott, as also of S<SUP>r</SUP> Thomas Hambald, attorney of the forsaideȝ William Rakett and Thomas Aslacby, yanne yere also presente in the saide counsaill chambre, yode unto the grounde of the saide John Gillyottes, lyynge at the baksyde of the saide John Gillyotte's tenement wherein he than dwelled, in Copper∣gate towardes the kinge's water of Fosse, in the parrishe of Alle Halowes upon the Pavement w<SUP>t</SUP>in the saide cite, betuyx a tene∣ment in the haldyng of Henre Williamson on y<SUP>t</SUP> one side, and a tenement of the saides William Rakett and Thomas Aslacby, late in the haldyng of Robert Amyas, on y<SUP>t</SUP> oyere syde. Ande the same grounde y' and yan the same serchiours diligently serched and mesured by gode deliberacon; and incontinent, the same daye and yere, the saide serchiours, after thair serche so made, cam in the saide counsail chambre afore the saide Mayre, and y'e and thanne saide, in vertu of thair othe, that the saide grounde conteyneth in lengthe at the ovirsyde in breede, frome the tenement of the saide Henre Williamson unto the grounde of the saideȝ William Rakett and Thomas Aslacby, vj yerdes ane ynche lakk, ande at the ney'e syde v yerdes, halfe yerde and halfe quarter, and more by ane halfe ynche as to thair estimacon, etc.</P>
<P>Memorandum, that ye saideȝ day, yere, presence ande place, the forsaide John Gillyott promised for his partie that if the saideȝ William Rakett ande Thomas Aslacby will at any tyme hereafter have a newe serche of the saide grounde, that yan he will beere his due parte of alle suche costes, as shall be requisite in that behalfe, <NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot">A few thorn letters are used in this document.</NOTE> etc.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">Enrolment Book, Civ. Ebor.,</HI> B. Y. 145.]</P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>Aug. 20, 16 Edw. IV. (1476).—John Burgh, William Stane∣house,
<PB N="21" REF="22"/>
William Cole &amp; Richerd Blakelok, seircheours of ye <NOTE PLACE="marg">Aug. 20, 1476.</NOTE> wrightes and tilers w<SUP>t</SUP>in ye citie of Yorke, ye same day above written, come to fore Thomas Wrangwish Maire &amp; ye chamber∣leyns, in ye counsell chaumbre uppon Owse brigg, and award &amp; jugement gaffe of a variaunce of a ground be twix John Gilyot Alderman of ye on partie, and Ambrose Preston of London chandeler of ye other partie. First yai deme a gutter yat liggeȝ in lengh frome ye streit of Petirgate, be fore doun thrugh a tenement of ye said John Gilyot Alderman to ye Kynge's dyke be hynd of ye on partie, and a tenement of ye said Ambrose Preston of ye other partie, ye which said gutter and ye leid yer of, we ye said seirchours fyndes be our discrecions pertenyth evenly to ye forsaid John Gilyott &amp; the said Ambrose, never ye lesse we consider ye greit cost and expences yat ye forsaid John Gilyot maid and done, we y'fore giffes and awardes yat ye said John Gilyott shall have ye said gutter all hole to hym selff, so yat he giffe to ye forsaid Ambrose, or to his depute, for cause of eassement in watter fallyng owt of ye forsaid gutter uppon ye ground of ye said Ambrose, iij s. iiij d. now furthwith, and never after yis to giff more to ye said Ambrose for ye said gutter, and els ye said John Gilyott to bere charge of ye watter commyng of ye said gutter.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">House Book, Civ. Ebor.</HI> i. 21.]</P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>M<SUP>d</SUP>, that the xv<SUP>th</SUP> day of Decembre, the yere of r.r. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Dec. 15, 1501.</NOTE> Henre vij<SUP>th</SUP> after ye conquest ye xvij<SUP>th</SUP>, by assent and consent of William White Alderman, on yat oon partie, and Ric' Thorn∣ton Alderman, on yt other partie, John Sclater and John Stevenson, sersours of the carpenters, Ric' Blakeloke and William Ellot sersours of the teilers, tofore ye right wurship∣full Sir, John Stokdale Maier of the citie of York, wer sworne upon the Holy Evangelistes treuly to viewe &amp; serche two tenementeȝ, newly &amp; of late maid &amp; reparared by ye said Ric' Thornton on North strete &amp; Mekilgate negh Ousebrygge end, adjoyng unto the tenementeȝ of ye said William on ye said stretes; whiche sersours went unto ye same two tenementeȝ &amp; viewd theym, and after theyr otheȝ by assent &amp; consent of the said partieȝ ordered in maner &amp; forme ensuyg. That is to say,
<PB N="22" REF="23"/>
ather of theym shall have theyr esyng drop upon other at theyr tenementeȝ in North stret, yat is to wit y<SUP>e</SUP> said Ric' Thornton for his kid helme upon ye tenement or ground of ye said William Whyte, and the said William for his long house opon ye tenement or ground of ye said Ric' Thornton. And William White grauntes yat a grece &amp; a gutter, whiche y<SUP>e</SUP> said (Ric' Thornton) hath laid &amp; festened unto a tenement of ye same William at Ouse brigge end, to stand &amp; abid still as it nowe doth unto y<SUP>e</SUP> tyme y<SUP>t</SUP> the said William or his eyreȝ of newe bild or repayre his said tenement ther. And ye said Ric' Thornton grauntes yat the sparreȝ &amp; tymbre of ye said William, which is shot &amp; hyngeth over ye ground of y<SUP>e</SUP> same Ric' ther by viij<SUP>th</SUP> yncheȝ &amp; more anenst y<SUP>e</SUP> pan of his house, shall hyng &amp; abid still as it doth unto tyme yat ye said William or his eyres of new bild or repayr os his above∣said; and then he to bild up right from his soile tre upward. And this ordour and award by assent &amp; consent of y<SUP>e</SUP> said partieȝ was giffen by the same serchors tofore the Maier, Michell White, George Kyrk, William Neleson, Aldermen, the Chamberleyns, and other, diverse other honest persons beyng present w<SUP>t</SUP> the said Maier in ye Counseill Chambre opon Ouse brigge, the day &amp; yere abovesaid.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">House Book Civ. Ebor.</HI> viii. 121.]</P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="collection of court documents">
<HEAD>III. PRESENTMENTS OF THE JURIES AT THE COURTS OF THE ABBOT OF SELBY.</HEAD>
<HEADNOTE><P>[From the Originals at Londesbrough.]</P></HEADNOTE>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>12 Edw. IV. 1472.—Jhesus. Thes er y<SUP>e</SUP> grefis y<SUP>t</SUP> xij men fendes defectyffe. In y<SUP>e</SUP> fyrste we say y<SUP>t</SUP> John Bellynghom maid afray of Jo . . . . . &amp; grefesly hurt hem of parell of his dethe, y<SUP>e</SUP> bludwyt vj s. viij d., &amp; ton halfe to y<SUP>e</SUP> kyrke warke, &amp; y<SUP>e</SUP> toy . . . . ye lord. Item John Dawson maid afray of John Belyngham, y<SUP>e</SUP> mercyment iij s iiij d, the ton half to the k . . . . &amp; y<SUP>e</SUP> toyere to y<SUP>e</SUP> lord. Item Ryc' Emson maid afray of John Broun &amp; drue blod on hym, y<SUP>e</SUP> bludwyt vj s. viij d., y<SUP>e</SUP> ton halfe to y<SUP>e</SUP> kyrke, y<SUP>e</SUP> tother to y<SUP>e</SUP> lord. Item ye said Ryc' maid afray of a man of Fenton, ye fray iij s. iiij d., the ton
<PB N="23" REF="24"/>
halfe to y<SUP>e</SUP> kyrke and oyere to y<SUP>e</SUP> lord. Item Ryc' Cornner maid afray of Herse Thorppe, y<SUP>e</SUP> fray, ether of tham, xij d. Item Roger, y<SUP>e</SUP> Merciallse man, maid asalt of strangher, &amp; fraid y<SUP>e</SUP> neghboures, y<SUP>e</SUP> salt xx d. Item Ryc' Emson maid asalt of William Broune at his dore, &amp; afrayd his neyghburs of Palmsondai, y<SUP>e</SUP> salt xx d. Item William Wallas maid asalt of John Balme at his dore, y<SUP>e</SUP> salt xx d. Item gyf yer be anny mane y<SUP>t</SUP> has anny swyne, y<SUP>t</SUP> will not set tham befor the hyrd, y<SUP>a</SUP> sall forfyt for evere swyne iiij d. W Pallmms pro Domino, Johannes Eleson, Robertus Walker, Barnerde Lignkolne.</P>
<P>Also xij men has ordan &amp; chosyn ij men of ather gatt for to gedyr y<SUP>e</SUP> swyn hyrd hyreȝ w<SUP>t</SUP> the constabylle William Baker &amp; Robert Stylyngton, . . Gower, John Rowghte, &amp; Robert Wrthe, for Mekylgate.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>M<SUP>d</SUP> y<SUP>t</SUP> yes er y<SUP>e</SUP> Artecles y<SUP>t</SUP> . . . . y<SUP>e</SUP> whest fendes yam greweid. In y<SUP>e</SUP> fyrste we say y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>e</SUP> bruher y<SUP>t</SUP> bruhis to sell, sall sell w<SUP>t</SUP> in his hus j galon all for ij d., &amp; j quart for j halpeny, be a mesur seald, &amp; j . . j d. ob. forthe at dore; &amp; also in casse be y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>a</SUP> sall not deny no por man nor woman penyworthe ner halpeny∣worthe, galon nor halfe galon, when y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>a</SUP> com tharfor for yar monny, &amp; it may be prowyd, &amp; schoy have abown xij galons w<SUP>t</SUP> in hyss hows, opan of forfetynge iij s. iiij d. as oft as shoy his fone defectyffe. Item we desyer a remedy of owr buschers for sellynge of thar flech, for we thynke y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>a</SUP> sell un to pepyll der fleche y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>e</SUP> pore pepyll gruchis gretly thar wyt, whar for we desyer, be awyse of my Lord &amp; the Stuerd, for to have a serche wekly of the buschers, &amp; se y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>a</SUP> sell a resonabyll pennyworth after he byes so. Item, for owr fechers, elykwys, y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>a</SUP> sell noy feche w<SUP>t</SUP> owt y<SUP>t</SUP> it be abyld be fyche offesers as sall be asegnid be Lord &amp; Stuerd, &amp; at y<SUP>e</SUP> fecher be sworne what y<SUP>t</SUP> it coste at see, &amp; he for to have a com∣petent wennynge; &amp; y<SUP>t</SUP> no man cute hys feche bot y<SUP>t</SUP> at be serched be y<SUP>e</SUP> debetes y<SUP>t</SUP> ar ordane for sersynge. Item we say y<SUP>t</SUP> yer have boght of late in y<SUP>e</SUP> markyge unsesanabyll wetyl, y<SUP>t</SUP> is to say, feche &amp; herrynge, bothe Thom Smythe &amp; John Clyffe; we amersy the ather of tham xij d.; &amp;, yf thay brynge anny more fyche chafer, y<SUP>a</SUP> for to forfyte thar feche. Item we d(es)yer y<SUP>t</SUP> no bakster y<SUP>t</SUP> has to by to sell, by no corne in ye markythe
<PB N="24" REF="25"/>
to a xj be strekenge to y<SUP>e</SUP> comyne pepyll be servid, opane of vj s. viij d., y<SUP>t</SUP> to be forfyt, y<SUP>e</SUP> ton halfe to y<SUP>e</SUP> Lord, y<SUP>e</SUP> toher half to ye kyrkwarke. Item gyffe anny man that comhis to y<SUP>e</SUP> markythe w<SUP>t</SUP> anny corne sall not set it up fro markyth day to markyde day, bot yf it cane be prewyd y<SUP>t</SUP> he his bed no selver tharfor, bot y<SUP>t</SUP> he sell it as markythe gos, &amp; that y<SUP>e</SUP> markythe of corne be endyd be xij of da, opan of forfetyng of his corne. Item we say that Rychard Atkynson maid afray of the constabyll, y<SUP>e</SUP> mercyment iiij d. Item we say that John Kokher (mercyment xij d.) maid afray of John Barton.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>June, 14<SUP>th</SUP> Edw. IV. 1472.—First the constables present that William Couper (iiij d.) made affray uppon Thomas Kirkhous and hym stroke w<SUP>t</SUP> a staff, anno xiij. Item Patryk (xx d.) &amp; James Glover, glover, (xx d.) made affray the same, and outhir drewe blode of othir, and rescued the constables. . . . Item Thomas (ij d.), servaunt of John Eleson, made affray uppon Stryngersen, when he made the kynge's wach. Item John Shepherd (ij d.) made affray uppon Th. Michell (ij d.) &amp; stroke hym with his bowe in the felde. Item Gerard Melton (xij d.) made affray, &amp; stroke a straunger w<SUP>t</SUP> a wodknyfe &amp; drewe blode. Item John Kyng (vj d.) made affray uppon the goldsmyth (vj d.) of Selby.</P>
<P>xxj men sworn for the lord and tenantȝ say uppon thair othe that Thomas Dransfeld is a theef and has knowelach felony, and now liffeȝ as a vacabond. Item that one Patryk, dwellyng in Midelthorp, is a vacabound, and hath no craft used then lyvelode to lyff uppon, agayns the forme of lawe liffyng, and called avowtrer w<SUP>t</SUP> othir men wyfeȝ. Item that John Bek is a vacabound and gos about w<SUP>t</SUP> a lettre testimoniall, beggyng to beseke you to see his writtyng, and that he may be warned to be of gode governance. Item Laurence of Lawe is a vacabound, and uses no craft to lyf by, bot lyffeȝ sus∣peciouslye agayns lawe of this land. Item that Stephen Taillour, dwellyng in Midelthorp, is a vacabond, y<SUP>r</SUP> fore by caus he hath dwellyng bot of short tyme in the towne, it is necessary to charge hym to be of gode reule. Item that William, ser∣vaunt of Herry Couper, is a ryotter on nyghtes, sittyng up at
<PB N="25" REF="26"/>
uncovable tyme, and that he drawes to his felyship Thomas Folyfote, John Arott thelder, &amp; John Arott yonger, which be not well disposed. Item that John Hode is a vacabound, and usith to go w<SUP>t</SUP> the Marchalsy, and in a place that he come to he cutt asmych bacon out of a flyk as was worth iij d., unlawefully. Item that William Broun of the Marchalsye uses unlawefull playes by nyghteȝ, and syttes up at uncovable tyme. Item that John More, tenaunt to Robert Mascald in Midelthorp, is a receptour of suspect persones, commyng by nyght and goyng by nyght, and liffes as a vacabound. Item that Robert Coureenay receptes mysgoverned persones and suspect of felony, by nyghtes, if he do so from hensforward, to forfet a payne of xl s. Item that Robert Broun of the Cowe layne receptes Scottes and othir suspect peple, we payne to lefe that reule in payne of xl d. Item that Roger of the Mar∣chalsye, servaunt to William Broun, is a suspect persone, and we desire to have hym out of the towne. Item we desire that ye will commaund John Donkan to be well rewlyd. Item that John Coke fyssher suffers me(n) to play in his hous at the tableȝ for mony by nyghteȝ. Item that oone panyermaker houses &amp; harbers suspect persones in his hous, and liffes as a vacabond. Item Hobson of Goldall &amp; Heryson of the same er forstallers of samen comyng toward the markett in Selby; we will that thay lefe; and, if thay be founden gilty herafter, outhir of thame to lese vj s. viij d. Item that no man bot officers bers unlawefull wepyn to the kirk then in the market in payne of xij d. Item we ordeyn that all vacabondes, bifore writen, kepe gode reule in tyme to come, and, if any of thayme be founden gilty, to voide the toune of Selby by Michaelmes day next for to come in payne of xl s.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>Oct., 12 Edw. IV. (1472).—Jhesus. Thes er ye fawtes y<SUP>t</SUP> xij men fendes defectyve. In y<SUP>e</SUP> fyrste xij men says y<SUP>t</SUP> the crosse in the markythe his defectyff &amp; lyke to fall, &amp; sas the Lord sall reperell be Passe day, in payn of the jeberde y<SUP>t</SUP> may fall thar off. Item the Melne brige his defectyffe, &amp; be longes to the Lord to reperall, &amp; it be maid be y<SUP>e</SUP> forsaid day in pan of perell y<SUP>t</SUP> may fall. Item the Cokreke bryge his defectyffe,
<PB N="26" REF="27"/>
&amp; be longes to the Lord to reperell, &amp; it be maid be the said day. Item we fend y<SUP>t</SUP> Ryc' Derreke his lepere, &amp; his not abyll to felychep emange the pepell, wharfor we desyer y<SUP>t</SUP> he be wodyd be Myrtynmes next comyng, opan of xl s. Item we say that thar sall no man geder non akcornes in the comone wod in pane of xvj d. as of as thay be prewed gederynge. Item we say that John Wryght of Faxflet has broken y<SUP>s</SUP>, he was of Selby, be diveres tymes, for the whylke we amercy him x s. Item we say y<SUP>t</SUP> John Scheperd selld unseuynabyll flech, for the welke we amecy him ij d. Item we say y<SUP>t</SUP> William Broun of Merschalse met women at y<SUP>e</SUP> toun end wyt thar gess, &amp; boght tham or thay com at the merketh, whar for we amercy hym iiij d. Item we say y<SUP>t</SUP> John Byrd maid afray of Remeng∣hyngton weffe &amp; drwe blod on hym, &amp; Remyngton drwe blud on hym, we amercy ather of tham xij d. Item we saie y<SUP>t</SUP> William Walas &amp; Ric' Thomson maid afray at kyrk dore &amp; frayd paryschens, we amercy ather of tham iiij d. Item we say y<SUP>t</SUP> Asschomae y<SUP>t</SUP> dwelles next Schepman wyffe maid afray of John Wesmerland, we ameecy hym xij d. Item we say y<SUP>t</SUP> John Rowthe maid afray of Robert Scheperd &amp; John his son, we amercy hym iiij d., and Robert Scheperd iiij d. Item we say y<SUP>t</SUP> Milles Wytton &amp; Robert Sumerschals, smythe, maid afray, we amercy ather of tham vj d. Item we say y<SUP>t</SUP> John Corner maid afray of William Bacon, we amercy hym xiiij d. Item we say y<SUP>t</SUP> John Yonge &amp; the correher maid afray, we amercy (a)ther of tham ij d. Item we say y<SUP>t</SUP> John Chaine &amp; fader maid afrae and druwe blud of ather of tham, iiij d. Item we say y<SUP>t</SUP> John Dawson maid afray of William Resen, we amercy hym iiij d. Item we say y<SUP>t</SUP> Roger Whallay &amp; Ryc' of Back∣howes maid afray, we amercy yam ij d. Item we say y<SUP>t</SUP> Thomas Smythe maid afray of Cransfeld and drwe blud on hym, we mercy hym vj d.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>Thys er ye defawtes y<SUP>t</SUP> xij men fendes deffectyffe at the gret cowrtes at Mykelmes, y<SUP>e</SUP> yer of r. of kynge Edward iiij<SUP>ti</SUP> xv. (1475).</P>
<P>In the fyrste we say that the Mylne bryge is defectyffe, &amp;
<PB N="27" REF="28"/>
lyke, bot it be amend son, y<SUP>t</SUP> it wyll be gret hurt to the ton, whar for, bot it mendyd be Martynmes, we amarce it xl s. Item we say that Skokryke bryge is defectyffe, &amp; lyke to be gret hurt to the kynge's pepyll, w<SUP>t</SUP> out it be amendid, whar for, bot it be amendid be the said day, we amercy it xx s. Item we say that the fotman's cawse be for William Chawe dore is defectyffe, wharfor, bot it mendyd be the said day, we amercy it xij d. Item we say that the said William has incrossid afor his dor of the hy way, bot yff he lay it agane, we amercy hym xij d. Item we say that the hows y<SUP>t</SUP> John Zonge dwells in of the busser rent, and the hows of Robert Raynald next by stoppes the watyr sew that the water may not hawe it reght corsse, whar for, bot it be mendid be Mertynmes, we amercy ather of tham iij s. iiij d. Item we ordeyne that the new sewes in Gouththorp eu' in defaut of Rauf Babthorp squyer, is defectyve, yerfore payne is that it be mendyd by Martynmes next in payne xij d.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>Oct., 17th Edw. IV. (1477).—Item that Richard Fereby etc has barked ledyr unlawefully &amp; sold it to the kynge's people wher by the lawe it is noght half barked.</P>
<P>We say y<SUP>t</SUP> John Studherd (viij d.) maid afray of Wylliam Underwod (iiij d.) wryght, &amp; John Studherd had his hed brokynge. Item William Panter (vj d.) maid afray of ij stranghis (ader of tham xij d.), &amp; the panter had his hed brokyn. Item we say y<SUP>t</SUP> Rychard Dyschforth &amp; Robert Smythe, fecher, toke &amp; selld j stranges man heirreng for iiij a penny, agans ordonans of the ton. Item we say y<SUP>t</SUP> Ryc' Dychforthe (xl d.) &amp; John Hodd made afray of one Barchand of Rekall, bocher, for brynghyng in of wetell for the welfare of comhons. Item if any man take to sell any oyer man fyssh in the merkett, and any man do the contrary, he to forfett vj s. viij d. Item that the purpressures come in this day xiiij day, to gyf thair presentment bilongyng to their office, in payne of vj s. viij d. Item that Thomas Berbour, after he was sworn, departed frome the Jury. Item William Bacon holdes ij dogges unlawefull, it is charged to kepe that one in band,
<PB N="28" REF="29"/>
and put away the tother, in payne of xx s. Item that Richard Dysshford had in his shop fyssh by xiiij daes, to it stanke in so mykell it was caried to Ouse, yerfore, if he do any more, for to forfett vj s. viij d.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>Thys is the wardytte of xxij men &amp; the constabylls, the xix day of Aprill, the xix yer of r. of K. E. iiij<SUP>ti</SUP> (1479).</P>
<P>In the fyrst, we fynd a gret defawt in the crosse in the merkythe place, that it is in pounte to fall, &amp; lyke to doy gret hurt bot it be amendid. Item we fynd y<SUP>t</SUP> Stewn Harlynge (ij s.) maid afray of Kyrlowe. Item we fynd y<SUP>t</SUP> W. Harwod (xij d.) maid afraye of Robert Raner in the merkythe. Item we fynd y<SUP>t</SUP> William Hadfeld (xl d.) maid afray of Robert Lyndsay &amp; drewe blod of the same Lyndsay. Item we fynd y<SUP>t</SUP> William Paynter maid afray of John Emson of Thorp, xx d., &amp; blod drawn of the payntor, xx d. Item Robyn Belfeld (ij s.) maid afray of Bakon man, and of hym drewe blod.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="document">
<P>1483.—Jhesus. Item we fend y<SUP>t</SUP> Pereson has a servand y<SUP>t</SUP> is yll disspossid of hyr handes, whar for we wyll y<SUP>t</SUP> schoy be woydyd the ton be twix this &amp; Sant George day, opon pane xx s. Item we fend y<SUP>t</SUP> one Wrodyngton, a waykabound, is avell dyssposid man y<SUP>t</SUP> dwelle her amang us, and has yl∣dyssposid folkis comynge to hym, whar for we well y<SUP>t</SUP> he be woydyd the ton be the said day, opan in prisonment. Item we fend y<SUP>t</SUP> on Breyerton, talzer, has an ewell dyspossid woman to his wyff of hyr handes, and cutes corn in harwyste, &amp; oyere thynges tak in the fyld, as eghes; we woll y<SUP>t</SUP> schoy be woydyd ton be said day, opan of prisonment. Item we fend y<SUP>t</SUP> Herre Warter has ylldysspossid cheldyr, &amp; of brekynge of mens heghis, &amp; takyng of kydes &amp; oyer stuffe, whar for we amercy hym for y<SUP>e</SUP> defawt y<SUP>t</SUP> his maid iiij d.; and yf it may be fonden doynge hurt agane, then we wyll y<SUP>t</SUP> he forfit iij s. iiij d. Item we fend y<SUP>t</SUP> John Herrot has avell dyssposid chylld of brekynge of heghis, war for we amercy hym for y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>t</SUP> is don iiij d., &amp;, yf y<SUP>a</SUP> be fonden anny more in defawt, we amercy tham thar efter iij s. iiij d. Item we
<PB N="29" REF="30"/>
fend y<SUP>t</SUP> William Whalley has yll dispossid cheldyr of brekynge of heghis, wharfor we amercy hym for y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>t</SUP> is done, iiij d., &amp;, yf y<SUP>a</SUP> be fonden anny mor in defawt, we amercy hym iij s. iiij d. . . . Item we fend y<SUP>t</SUP> the crosse in the merkyth place is lyke to fall, and lyke, bott grace be, to myschef sume man, whar for we dysyer y<SUP>t</SUP> it may be mendid or anny hurt fall. Item we fend y<SUP>t</SUP> melners is not deligent to serve the Lorde's tennandes be for owte men, whar for we dyseyer the Lorde's offecer gyff warnynge to tham y<SUP>t</SUP> it be mendid, and also y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>a</SUP> take mesurabyll multure of men's corne, for ther is diverse men y<SUP>t</SUP> complens of tham, wharfor we amercy tham nowe at this tym for defawt y<SUP>t</SUP> is maid ij s., ande eftyr, &amp; thay ar fonden defectyffe, to forfyt xx s. Item we well y<SUP>t</SUP> yff it may be fonden be the offecer or be anny oyere man y<SUP>t</SUP> anny bocher y<SUP>t</SUP> slays flech kep anny ower Thorsday y<SUP>t</SUP> was sclayn of Setterday afor, bot yf it be powderd, from May day to Makylmes day, to forfyt the flech, &amp; xx<SUP>ti</SUP>d. to the Lord. Item we desyer y<SUP>t</SUP> the offecers, y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>a</SUP> make a dew serche wekly of the syss of bred &amp; all, for pur pepell y<SUP>t</SUP> lyffhis of the penny complens tham grettly y<SUP>t</SUP> the sys is not kepid. Item we well y<SUP>t</SUP> our butes in the Owt wod be maid be the tonchype of Selby, be maid be Wetsonday next comynge, opan of vj s. viij d. Item we fend a gret defawt y<SUP>t</SUP> in Owsgat the ground gos away, and lyke in prosisse of tym, w<SUP>t</SUP> owt y<SUP>t</SUP> it be amendyd, is lyke to mescheffe all the gates of Owsgate, &amp; all the howynge y<SUP>t</SUP> bondys of the watter; whar for we desyer y<SUP>t</SUP> my Lord &amp; his breyer lye ther hedes togeder, y<SUP>t</SUP> ther may be fonden a remdy ther fore, ar it be wars. Item we desyer y<SUP>t</SUP> my Lord and his breyer wald gyff us tymber, y<SUP>t</SUP> we may mayke a comyne seghe, y<SUP>t</SUP> the pepyll may be eassid, for the comyns gretly grughis ther wythe y<SUP>t</SUP> ther is non as ther was wont to be. Item y<SUP>t</SUP> evere mane clens his gutters againe the payment for uschuynge of the water for drownnynge of payment be Whetsonday, yen evere pec iiij d.</P>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="collection of birth certificates">
<PB N="35" REF="31"/>
<HEAD>IV. CERTIFICATES OF THE ENGLISH PARENTAGE AND BIRTH OF CERTAIN PERSONS WHO HAVE BEEN CHARGED WITH BEING SCOTS.</HEAD>
<HEADNOTE><P>[From the York City Records.]</P></HEADNOTE>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<P>To all trewe Christen men to whome this present writyng <NOTE PLACE="marg">1476. John Ry∣chardson.</NOTE> shal com, Rycherd Salkeld sqwyer, Thomas Becham sqwyer, John Aglanby gentilman, John Whelpdale gentilman, Robert Tanyswod yoman, Edward Nycolson yoman, Roberte Graveson husbondman, and John Iveson husbondman, sendes gretyng well in oure Lorde Gode. That where as oon John Rychardson, berer of this, is noysed yat he shuld be a Scottes man and borne in Scotland, and for asmykell as it is medefull and meretory thynge to every Cristen man to bere wittnesse of the truthe, we notefie and declares to youre audience, that the forsaid John Richerdson is a trewe ligeman to the kynge of England, and getten and born in Crossby besyde Karlill, and the names of his godfaders John Warwyk gentilman and John Rycherdson of Crossby aforesaid yoman, and Elisabeth Tenyswod hys god moder. And thys wyll we recorde and bere wittenesse be thys lettre of record sealed with our seales, wyth other mo yf nede be. Made in the yere of our Lorde millesimo cccclxxvj.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">Reg. Civ. Ebor.</HI> A. Y. 343.]</P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<P>To ye most worshipfull &amp; ther especiall maister, John Tong, mair of ye cite of York.</P>
<P>Be it credebly certifide to y<SUP>or</SUP> moost wirshipfull and honor∣abyll <NOTE PLACE="marg">1477. John Colyn.</NOTE> mastership, y<SUP>t</SUP> whereas off late tym a man of ye citie of York, cald John Colyn, was notyd and diffamyd . . . iniquite, be veray malesse, y<SUP>t</SUP> he shud be a Skotte &amp; no Ynglysman, wherfor we, Maister Robert Symson deane of Darlyngton, Sir Robert Clerk preste, William Betel. Jamys Bland Richard Deman, William Zotson, W. Smart. Rob' Bay, W▪ Merchall John Robynson . . . &amp; John Symson declares hym on owr honeste &amp; trewth, y<SUP>t</SUP> ye said John was born at Cokyrton, &amp;
<PB N="36" REF="32"/>
cristynede in ye fount of y<SUP>is</SUP> Derlyngton, and is a trew Ynglys∣man born both of fader &amp; moder; y<SUP>t</SUP> will we vereffy and mak good agan all maner of men y<SUP>t</SUP> sais y<SUP>e</SUP> contrary; oblyssyng also our selve to y<SUP>ev</SUP> in c<HI REND="italic">li,</HI> yff ye contrary may be lawfully prevyd, be this owr writyng. Also we William Bettl, James Bland, Ric' Demen, William Zotson, in y<SUP>e</SUP> moost humbly wys thankes your mastership, y<SUP>t</SUP> it wald plese y<SUP>or</SUP> goodnes as to do as mych for our sakes as to shew ye sayd John y<SUP>or</SUP> favour, for ye qwych we in tym comyng sall do y<SUP>or</SUP> plesour and servyce yff it ly in owr power. And in record y<SUP>t</SUP> this premisses be trew we to ye said have sett to owr sells. Yevyn at Darlyngton ye iij Sonday of Lentyn.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">House Book, Civ. Ebor.</HI> i. 62.]</P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<P>M<SUP>d</SUP> the xij<SUP>e</SUP> day of Novembre, the xvij yere of Kyng Edward <NOTE PLACE="marg">1477. John Saunderson</NOTE> the iiij [came] into the counsel chaumbre of Ousebrig to fore John Tong maire of the cite of Yorke, Thomas Wranggwish, Robert Amyas aldermen, John Hag, William Letwyn chaumber∣leyns of the same cite, and other thare beyng present, on John Saunderson, of Yorke, fissher, and thar and then shewed howe that he of late ayanest right and gude consciens by the childern of wekydnes was wrongfully noysed, slaundered and defamed that he shold be a Scotissheman and born in Scotland; the saide John Saunnderson, willyng to subdieu and avoid the said noise and slaunder, and declare and prove hym self a trewe Englissheman, cam afore us in his propre person w<SUP>t</SUP> other ful notable and discreit personeȝ born w<SUP>t</SUP>in the counties of Northumbreland, Westmerland &amp; Cumberland, that is to say Herry Horseley gent, Robert Wivell, Sir Robert Cuttbert prest, Laurence Lelegrave yoman, William Spacy, Nicholas Hay, w<SUP>t</SUP> othere, and there &amp; then in &amp; on the premisses dieulie sworn &amp; examyned, said &amp; confessed that they verelie knewe the said John Saunder∣son for a trew Englissheman, and at he was born in Cheswyk in Northumbreland, and son to John Saunderson of the same, husbond, and Alison the wiffe of the same John, his moder, and at William Saunderson, Robert Saunderson, and Elyn Saunder∣son war god faders and god moder unto the same John Saunderson fissher, etc.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">House Book, Civ. Ebor.</HI> i. 76.]</P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<PB N="37" REF="33"/>
<P>Unto all theis untill whome this presentes shal com, we, Sir <NOTE PLACE="marg">1478. Thomas Bakhus.</NOTE> John Banarsdall ye vicar of Morland, Roland Was, Thomas Fawlo∣feld, Thomas Saxeld, Thomas Appielby, William Fawlofeld squires, William Bakus, Robert Bakus, William Cuke, Robert Cuke, John Cuke, John Wenttire, William Abdison, Arthure Bethome, Thomas Reke, of the parrish of Morland, sendes gretyng in our Lorde &amp; recommendaccin unto whome it semys. And for als mykell as it is meretorie and medfull thing anentes God in every case nedefull to witnesse treuth, and specialy where it is effectualy requirit, plese it you to wete that we er newe of late ryplie enformet by diverse credable persones, that on Thomas Bakhus, bringer of this presentes lettres, shold be wrongfully nosed and slaundered as for a Scottes man born, and also un∣rightwisly vexit &amp; turbilled hym to grete hyndrance &amp; scathe, als well in body as in gudeȝ, wherfore we afore writen make opynlie knowen, and trulie beris wittenesse before God and all the worlde, that the forsaid Thomas Bakhus is trewe lige man till our soverand lord ye kyng, and was borne of his modre &amp; gettyn w<SUP>t</SUP>in the forsaid towne of Morland, and there was Cristyned at the funte stone, and his godfaders callid Thome Smyth, the whilke is yit of live, and Jellyne Disforthe, &amp; is godmoder Annes Burbake, and therfore if eny will say or bere hym onhand the contrarie bot at he is a trewe lige Inglis man borne till our for∣said soveraynt lorde the kynge and at this forsaide recorde, at we have made in maner &amp; forme afore writen, is veray truthe &amp; suthefastnes, and that we will abide &amp; stand yare by w<SUP>t</SUP> our bodyes &amp; gudes. In wittenes hereof we have setto our sealeȝ. Gevyn at Morland aforsaid, the xxij<SUP>ti</SUP> day of the moneth of Septembre, the yere of ye regne of Kyng Edward the Fourte ye xviij<SUP>th</SUP>.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">Reg. Civ. Ebor.</HI> A. Y. 326<HI REND="italic">a.]</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<P>Record pro Roberto Elwald conerour. For asmych as <NOTE PLACE="marg">1479. Robert Elwald.</NOTE> it is right meretorie as medeful to wittenesse ye trewth, be it knawen to all maner of men to whom this present writyng commys, that Robert Elwalde, ye son of John Elwalde, is a trewe Ynglish man, gottyn of his fadre aforsaid, and born of his modre w<SUP>t</SUP>in the paryssh of Saynt
<PB N="38" REF="34"/>
John Baptist w<SUP>t</SUP>in Hexhamshire, whose godfadre was John Elwalde of the said parysh and John Robson of the Langlee, and Janet Elwalde godmodre, of Hakefurth w<SUP>t</SUP>in the said shire, and was Cristenyt in the founte of the said parich of Saynt John Baptist; Wherfore we, the Prior of Hexham, Sir Thomas Laveroke chaplan and parish prest of the said parich, &amp; William Smyth parishclerke of the same, Thomlyn of Eryngton of Falefelde, Gerarde of Eryngton of Walwykgraunge, Alex Armstrang of Croslee, Thomlyn Armstrang of Bewfrount, Robert of Eryngton of Whittyngton, Robert of Chester gentilmen, William Soureby, Robert of Sourby, Richerd Sourby, John of Whitwhame, Alan Kell, John Denyug, John of Rede, John of Spayn, William Ferlame, John of Greme, and John of Copde in, besekes you by the way of charitie to repute and halde the said Robert Elwalde as for a trewe Ynglish man, as is afore rehersed, and as for the more trewe certificat to be made to you, we the forsaid Prior, gentilmen, and yomen afore rehersed hath setto our seales. Gevyn at Hexham, the xxvij<SUP>t</SUP> day of August, the yere of the reigne of Kyng Edward the iiij<SUP>t</SUP> the xix<SUP>th</SUP>.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">Reg. Civ. Ebor.</HI> A. Y. 326<HI REND="italic">b.]</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<P>2 May 21, Edw. IV.—Item the same day, tofore all above∣said, <NOTE PLACE="marg">1481. William Broun.</NOTE> cam personalie Thomas Arcle, dwellyng in Elborth in ye paresh of Dodyngton, countie of Northumbreland, yoman, &amp; Johnes Tailfere, servaunt to Sir Henry Percy Knyght, &amp; yare shewid &amp; said yat on William Broun of Yorke, litster, was a trewe Inglissheman, born in the town of Nesbet, in the parissh of Dodyngton, ande son to William Broun of the same Nesbet, and had to his godfaders Robert Colstone of Dodyngton &amp; William Gudeneghbour of the same, &amp; Isabel Clerk, the wiffe of John Clerke of Nesbet, his godmoder, and at the said William Broun was nather of alie ne of blode to eny Scotishman, and y<SUP>t</SUP> he, w<SUP>t</SUP> many others, if nede require it, is &amp; welbe redy at all tymeȝ to testefie ye same. And, more, the same day was broght tofore the said Maire and other abovewriten, by the right wirshupful S<SUP>r</SUP> Thomas Danby, thes recordes testefying the pre∣misseȝ under diverse seales, etc.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">House Book, Civ. Ebor.</HI> ii. 25.]</P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<PB N="39" REF="35"/>
<P>For als much as it is both nedeful, medful, &amp; meritory to <NOTE PLACE="marg">1481. John Hans.</NOTE> bere trewe wittenes &amp; to recorde ye treuth of every thynge yat stondeth in doute, yerfore be it knawen to every trewe Christen man yat this present testimonial heris, seis, or redis, yat we, Sir William Eure knyght, Maister John Kelynge chaunceler of Durham, William Pollard esquire, John Stathom jentilman, William Belasys jentilman, James Tippyng forster of Aukeland parke, Cristofer Preston, William Nodder, Thomas Spence, William Blithman, Richard Morton, Richarde Cuke, Richarde Emendson, Jenkyn Batmanson, Thomas Porter, &amp; Thomas Cotis beris witnes, &amp; recordys opon our honestie, be dew examinacion &amp; trewe enformacion, yt whar as John Hans, of the cete of Yorke, glover, is grevouslie vexid &amp; trobilde, to his grete cost &amp; expens, surmysing on hym yat he shold be a Sottys man born, wharfore we aforesaid, and ich on of us, recordes &amp; beris wittenes, yat the said John Hans is an Inglischeman, &amp; was born in Bishope Aukeland, &amp; diverse honest men yat knewe both his fadir &amp; moder, &amp; had borogage in the same towne, &amp; John Catrike, yit beyng on lieff, recordeth uppon his treuth yat Kateryn his wiffe was his godmoder, &amp; Richerd Blithman, Adame Geme, &amp; Sir Robert Kyngeswod prest was his godfaders. And for the more credence to be gevyn to this our writynges, we abovesaid, and ich on of us singulerly, hathe setto our seals. Gevyn at Bisshop Awkeland, the thirtend day of May.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">Reg. Civ. Ebor.</HI> A. Y. 351<HI REND="italic">a.]</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<P>For as mykell as it is meritable to bere wittenes &amp; suthfast <NOTE PLACE="marg">1481. John Meldrem.</NOTE> record in any cause whilke myght ben trouble, losyng of goodes, or good fame to any trewe Cristen man, in defawte of sooth∣fast knowlage, therfore it is yat we, S<SUP>r</SUP> Henry Percy, lieutenaunt of th'est Merches of England affornemptes Scotland, S<SUP>r</SUP> Thomas Grey of Heton, S<SUP>r</SUP> Roger Heron of Forde, S<SUP>r</SUP> Thomas Grey of Horton, knyghtes, &amp; William of Folbery of the same, berith witnes &amp; suthfast record yat John Meldrem, dwelling in Yorke, is Englishman, gottyn by his fadir &amp; born of his modir within ye reyme of England, his fadir dwelling in Folbery apon ye wattir of Tyll, olife callit William Meldrem, ye said John
<PB N="40" REF="36"/>
Meldrem born in Northame apon Twede, &amp; Cristned within ye founte of ye proche kirke of ye same; his two god fadres, on callit John Rootherford constable of ye castell of Northame olyf at the makyng of this writyng, ane othir callit Robert Maxwell, dwelling in ye castell of Morpath, his godmodir callit Annes Jacson, ye wife of Adam Jakson dwelling in Dudo, both olyfe; wherfor we the aforsaid knyghtes &amp; swyer willith &amp; preith every goode Englishman not to presume nor sey any thing contrery yis our writing, in so mikill if eny wold presume ye contrarie this our record; and witnes of the whilkeȝ to this our writyng we have set our signettes, havyng the strength of our selys, ye ix day of Septembre, the xxj yhere of ye reyne of Kyng Edward the iiij<SUP>t</SUP>.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">Reg. Civ. Ebor.</HI> A. Y. 352.]</P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<P>Unto all trewe Xpen people to whom this present writyng <NOTE PLACE="marg">1482. John Malson.</NOTE> shall com, see, or heyre, gretyng in our Lorde God. And for as much as evill disposed people and childern of wekidnesse, thrugh malice and envy, by the temptacion of an evill sperit, falslie &amp; untrewlie hath noysed &amp; slaunderd a trewe Inglisshe∣man, cald John Malson, of Yorke, girdler, yat he shold be a Scottisman born, which John Malson was gottyn &amp; born betwix his fader &amp; his moder, Richerd Malson &amp; his wiffe, in the town of Langwathby, and Cristennyte in y<SUP>t</SUP> same kirke, and had to godfaders John Mekyll of Penryth beyng of lyffe at yis day in Penreth, &amp; John Walker of Langwathby, &amp; y<SUP>e</SUP> wiffe of Wilkyn of Carleton y<SUP>t</SUP> late discesyd was his god moder, and many ouer of the said John kyn and frendes at this day dwellyng w<SUP>t</SUP>in the cunte of Cumbreland; and therfore, be caws y<SUP>t</SUP> every trew Cristen man, by the way of charite, is bunden forto supporte &amp; maynteyn y<SUP>e</SUP> trewth of every trewe Cristenman, and forto sub∣dewe, repreve, &amp; to put down all falssett and untrewit, tharfore we all whos namys eftyr folowes, that is to say S<SUP>r</SUP> Christofer of Moresby knyght &amp; stewerd of Penryth, &amp; of all the whenys hamys, John of Crakanthorp of Holggull ryssavour of Penryth, &amp; of the whennys hamys, Richerd Musgrave of Hertley Castell esquire, Johannet Musgrave of Edynhall wedowe, William Musgrave &amp; Nicolas Musgrave esquires, Robert of Warcop of Warcop esquire,
<PB N="41" REF="37"/>
John Warcop, John Maunchell, Robert Maunchell esquires, William Hoton of Penreth, Rolland Wharton, William Bethum &amp; John Bost of Penreth gentilmen, John Watson, John Gryndon, John Symson, Richard Robynson, Henry Kirkbeke, Robert of Gyll of Penȝ &amp; John Mekyll of Penry, &amp; god faders of the same John Malson yemon, John of Carleton, Thomas Carlton, John of Wyndshalys, William Wyndshalys, Robert Walkar &amp; John Walkar of Langwathby yemon, w<SUP>t</SUP> many oder mo, will uphald, maynteyn apon our treuth &amp; worshippys at ye said John Malson is a Inglissh born man, gyttyn &amp; born as is abown said. In wittenesse of the same we have setto our sealles at Penrȝ, ye xxj day of Januar', &amp; ye xxj yer of our soveran lorde Kyng Edward the fourth.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">Reg. Civ. Ebor.</HI> A. Y. 352.]</P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<P>Too all maner of men this present writyng seyng or heryng, <NOTE PLACE="marg">1484. Alexander Ambler.</NOTE> God graunte &amp; gyff thaym joy and comforth. And for as mykel as it is meritorie, nedeful &amp; spedeful to every man to pupples and declare in ilke mater the treuth, and specially there where trewth is liklie w<SUP>t</SUP>owte recorde and wittenesse to be oppressid and set oparte froym the scewres of right, I, S<SUP>r</SUP> Thomas Flesho<SUP>r</SUP>, the vicar of Estwitton in the countie of Yorkshire, sayes and beris wittenesse of myn prestehode, also declareth opynlie for trewth yat I the sayd vicar in my kirk of Estwitton gaffe Confirmacion and Cristendom unto Alexaund' Annler w<SUP>t</SUP> all other observaunce acordyng to the constitucion of all holy kirke, wittenesse of his godfaders, yat is to say Alexaund' Blakborne, Thomas Tesedale, Ric' Darley w<SUP>t</SUP> all other neghbores, Alan Gaytterd, Will<SUP>a</SUP>m Clapeham, Richerd Clapeham, William Teysdale, Willyam Bourell, and at every gude person will labur forto restore hym into his gude name and fame like as we trewlie and dulye woll afferme of o<SUP>v</SUP> wirshippes, and all such defamers as wold distrue eny rightful man forto gar hym lese his godes w<SUP>t</SUP> thare fals reportes to get thame a thanke w<SUP>t</SUP>all, and it wer medeful to punyssh thaym in such fourme yat other fals flaterers may tak ensample w<SUP>t</SUP>all. Written at Est Witten, on the Monday next after the fest of Saynt James the Apostell.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">Reg. Civ. Ebor.</HI> A. Y. 351<HI REND="italic">a.]</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<PB N="42" REF="38"/>
<P>Memorandum, that ye ij<SUP>d</SUP> day of Novembre, the secund <NOTE PLACE="marg">1484.</NOTE> yer of ye regne of Kyng Richard ye Thrid, yer came oon Richard Davis of ye citie of Yorke, glovere, into ye councell chaumbre upon Owse brig, afore Thomas Wrangwish, yen being Mair of ye said citee; and afore all ye councell of ye said citee yen being yere and yan, and yere shewed a forget testimonyall sormysing in ye same in ye names of diverse of ye honest men of Ripon, wher ye same testimonyall was forget, that oon Alisaundre Aunbler of ye said citie, glovere, shuld be a Skottish∣man borne; the contrarie wherof was yen &amp; yere proved true in ye presence of all ye said councell by an oyere testimonyall of auctoritee &amp; credence by ye said Alisaundre labored and sued in ye tyme y<SUP>t</SUP> Mastre Amyas was Mair of yis said citee, as in ye regestre of ye said citie in ye last ende yer of, next ye 'Vynters, Ordynaunce more evidently it may apper.</P>
<P>Item on Fryday, ye iij<SUP>de</SUP> daye of Decembre, came oon Thomas Watson of yis same citie, tanner, &amp; oon George Hill into ye same councell chambre, afore ye said Mair and ye chaumbrelayns, and yen and yere shewed and declared that thay, and eythre of theym, wer present and herde when William Thomson of Rypon, Rawlyn Cundall of ye same, John Cole of ye same, mercer, &amp; John Watson of ye same, shomaker, said and swor yat thay ne noon of theim wer nevere prevey to ye sealing of ye forsaid forged and untrue testimonyall, shewed &amp; labord by ye said Richard Davis, and y<SUP>t</SUP> thay and every theym wolbe redye on thair owne cost to come hedre &amp; make it good upon a book.</P>
<P>Item Richard Thoneton of yis citie of Yorke, spicer, came ye same day &amp; tyme and place afore ye said Mair, and shewed and pl(a)ynly declared y<SUP>t</SUP> he was present &amp; herde when Robert of ye Wardrop of Ripon aforsaid said and swore y<SUP>t</SUP> he was nevere privey to ye sealing of ye forsaid forged, false testymonyall.</P>
<P>Item William Banes, baker, and Thomas Blande sayd in y<SUP>e</SUP> same place &amp; presence yat ye said Richard Davis proferd eythre of theym a pair of gloves to say yat yay sawe y<SUP>e</SUP> said forget &amp; untrue testimonyall sealed.</P>
<P>Item Thomas Wright of Thriske came into ye same place &amp; presence and offerd to swer upon a booke y<SUP>t</SUP> ye forsaid
<PB N="43" REF="39"/>
Alisaundre Aunbler is a true Inglishe man, borne in Estwitton, and y<SUP>t</SUP> he welbe at all tymes redy to prove &amp; make good eythre upon a book or els with his handes.</P>
<P>The x day of Decembre, in the yere abovesaid, before the said Mayre, in the said chambre, where and when personally appered John Gatescalles, Robert Wilkynson, John Hausse, John Downe, William Pert, John Kirkby, and Richard Watson.</P>
<P>Unto whome the said Thomas Wrangwish Maire, shewing first the testimoniall approbate of the said Alisaundre in the days of Robert Amyes Maire, and the above writyn declaracion concernyng the desetyng of a fals testimoniall, purchasid by the forsaid Ric' Davys, examined and demaunded of theme severally how they wold accept the said Alisaundre after the forsaid declaracion, which answerd and said, ichone of theme, that they wold accept hyme for a true Englisman as they did hertofore surmising none othere upon hyme herefter.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">Reg.</HI> A. Y. 354<HI REND="italic">a.]</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<P>M<SUP>d</SUP> that the Tuesday next tofore the fest of the Nativitie of <NOTE PLACE="marg">1485. Andrew Lambe.</NOTE> Saint John Baptist, that is to say the xxj day of the moneth of Juyn, in the yeres of our Lord God a m<SUP>l</SUP>cccclxxxv, and the reigne of King Richard the Third secund, in the counsaill chambre upon Ouse brig w<SUP>t</SUP>in the citie of York, before the right worshipful Sir Nicholas Loncastre maire of the said citie, one Andrew Lambe of the same, baker, diffamed by certayn of his craft that he shuld be a Scot, borne in the realme of Scotland, appered personally, being present in the said chambre the moost part of his said craft, w<SUP>t</SUP> othre in grete nombre assembled ther, where and when for his perfiter declaracion that he shuld be an Inglissh man, borne w<SUP>t</SUP>in the realme of England, he shewed unto the said Mayre certayne recordes of auctoritie, as foloweth herafter; which red, serched, and duly examined by hym in the presence of all his craft, chamberleyns and othre being present, and no thing probable object ayenst the same by the said craft, ne othir ther being present, the said Maire, after sad and mature examinacion of the said recordes in the presence forsaid, decreed and finally determyned that noo man of the said craft,
<PB N="44" REF="40"/>
ne othre w<SUP>t</SUP>in ye citie of York, suburbs, or precinctes of ye same, from hensfurth name or call the said Alexandre <HI REND="italic">(sic)</HI> a Scot, or Scotteshman, under the payne of vj s. viij d., evere man so doing, and also that the said Alex geve none occasion to any of his said craft to call hyme a Scot under the payne of forfaitour of vj s. viij d. to be equally employed to the chambre and the craft of bakers.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<HEAD>Copia literae testimonialis domini Comitis Northumbriae pro Andr' Lambe.</HEAD>
<P>Henry Erle of Northumberland, lord of thonours of Cokir∣mouth and Petworth, Warden of the Est and Middel marches of England anenst Scotland, and Justice of all the Kinge's forestȝ from Trent north, to all men to whome this writing shalbe shewed, greting. For asmoch as my welbeloved Andrew Lambe, of the citie of York, baxster, by indisposed personnes onely of malice have, as I am enformed, troubled hyme, sur∣mising hyme to be a Scottes man, I for a due prove in this behalve to be had have caused serch to be maid, whereby I am veralie accertayned that the said Andrew is the kyng our soverain lorde's true ligeman and subgiet, borne w<SUP>t</SUP>in this his realme of England, in the towne of Brenklowe, of the parissh of Pont Eland in the countie of Northumberland; wherfor, on the king our souverain lorde's behalve, I, the said Warden, charge you, and on myne desire, that noo maner of persone, of what degre or condicion he be, vex, trouble, or annoy the said Androw Lambe in persone ne in goodes, by reason of the said surmise, but quietely and peasably to have and rejose his fre libertie according onto our said souverain lorde's lawes, as ye woll eschewe the punycion than may ensue unto you, or any of you, for the contrary doing and os ye woll that I doo for you if thing require. Yeven undre my signet and my signe manuel, in my castell of Alnewik, the xviij<SUP>th</SUP> day of Juyn, in the twenty yere of the reign of our souverain lord King Edward the Fourt.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>J. Newton.</SIGNED> <SIGNED>HENRY NORTHUMBERLAND.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<PB N="45" REF="41"/>
<HEAD>Copia literae testimonialis Abbatis de Alnewek et aliorum pro eodem Andrea.</HEAD>
<P>Unto all good Christen people to whos knowlage thies presentȝ writing shalcome, Thomas Abbot of the monasterie of our Ladie of Alnewyk, John Herbotill recevour unto my Lord of Northum∣berland w<SUP>t</SUP>in the same cuntre, John Heron of Bokkenfeld gentilman, William Dokson, Th. Hedle, Thomas Stedeman of Morpath, Robert Dobson of Thriston, Edward Dobson of Felton, John Dobson, Robert Gibson of Acton, Thomas Hall, and John Bradelee of Anewik forsaid yoman sendes greting in our Lord everlasting. For asmoch as it is meritorie and medefull to witnesse and certifie the truthe in evere mater, and, in especiall, ther as it is meritorie and medefull may gender or cause prejudice, hurt, or hinderance unto the innocent, we, therfor, the forsaid Abbot, gentilmen, and yomen testifie, record, and bereth witnesse that Andrew Lambe of York, baxter, wonnyng in Ousegate, is an Inglish man, borne in the parish of Pont Eland in the towne of Brenklaw, where his moder decesed in child bed of the same Andrew, having too oone of his godfaders John of Kalom, to whome his fader was servaunt in the same Brenk∣law, and oone othre, William Haton of Shetryn, and to his god∣moder Eden of Peyth; wherfor we, as affore, exorte, pray, and require all good lordes, masters, and frendes not for to molest, vex, ne trouble the said Andrew in that behalve, bot to accept and admit, repute, and hold hyme as a good true Inglish man borne, at our record and testificacion. In witnesse wherof we the forsaid Abbot, gentilmen, and yomen have putto our sealles to this present writyng, writtyn the xiiij day of the moneth of Juyn, the xxj yere of the reigne of our souverain lord King Edward the iiij after the conquest of England.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<HEAD>Alia record pro eodem Andrea.</HEAD>
<P>Be it knawne to all men that this present writing heres or sees, and in evere mater of truthe is meritorie and medefull to record the truthe, there as conc' Andrew Lambe is noysed in the citie of York by his neghbours, and specially by his adver∣saries,
<PB N="46" REF="42"/>
to be a Scotteshman borne; it is not soo, for the truth in the mater is serchid, understand, and fondon contrary, for the said Andrew was borne in the towne of Brenlay in Pont Eland parisshe, and Cristynd in Pont Eland kirk, as it is fon by men of age and substance in the parissh; wherfor the said Andrew, w<SUP>t</SUP> othre worshipfull men of his frendes, hath re∣quired ye vicar of Pont Eland to record ye same w<SUP>t</SUP> other diverse gentilmen and yomen, y<SUP>t</SUP> is to say Sir Thomas Harbotill vicar of ye same kirk of Pont Eland, Alex Mitfurth gent, Ric' Cocour, Will Barnewell, John Gateshened, Thomas Andreson, William Watson, John Wynship yoman; wherfor we, forsaid rehersid, in witnesse settes to our sealles. Also ther was iij men of York her xiiij days affor, and desirid to under∣stand if any sike man had any record lat tyme affor or noo, and we certified yem y<SUP>t</SUP> ther was none y<SUP>t</SUP> tyme requirid, and we certified yem at y' was required noone or now. Wharfor we forsaid vicar, gentilmen, and yomen settes to our sealles, the Sunday after ye Magdaleyne day, the yere and reigne of King Edward xx.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">Reg. Civ. Ebor.</HI> A. Y. 327<HI REND="italic">b.]</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<HEAD>To the right honorable Sirs, the Maier, Aldermen, &amp; Comon Counseil of the Citie of York.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SIGNED>Your awne Sir John Aske.</SIGNED></OPENER>
<P>Right honorable Sirs, I commaund me unto you and thank <NOTE PLACE="marg">1486. John Har∣rington.</NOTE> you for the tender favour that ye have unto my kynseman, M. John Harington, the clerc of your Couneseil. And where I am informed that he at his late being w<SUP>t</SUP> the Kinge's grace, understode, by his good lordes and maisters y', that he was reputid to be a Scot, which grew on the report of one Thomas Wharf of (your) citie, whome ye have examyned, and ferder entendith to examyne in that behalve, I desire you to have knawledge for truith that the saide M. John was borne in Estryngton besides Houeden, of his moder, a poore gentil∣(wo)man, whose fader was to my fader, whome God assoile, at the third and third degre of consanguinitie, which I wold have comen and shewid unto you in propre person, if it had semed
<PB N="47" REF="43"/>
to my saide kynseman that I shuld soo have done: and soo I wol at his pleasour hast. If this slaunderous report come to the eers of some yongmen of the blode that he is of, it woll grewe theyme, I doubt not, which I pray you desire the saide Thomas Wharfe to remembre. As for his fader, I trust he woll declare hyme unto you to be an Englishman and a poore gentilman borne, thof he never weir taken heir bot for a yoman, which he haith been right wele at ease before this, and yit may lif to his honestie, blissid be God, the better, if my saide kynseman his sone fare wel, to whome I pray you, for my sake, to be more singler good lord and maisters, if ye can soe be in eny wise. And our Lord God preserve you to His pleasour. From Aughton the xxiij day of Septembre.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">House Book, Civ. Ebor.</HI> vi. 41.]</P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<HEAD>To the right worshipfull Sirs, the Maier, aldermen, and common counesell of the citie of York.</HEAD>
<P>Right worshipfull Sirs, I commaund me unto you. And for so much as I understand that M. John Harington hath been lately inquietid by untrue report maide of hyme above in the court, and emonges you also by one of his neghbours, which haith been called afore you and dar not avowe the same, bot that which he saide he denyed ayene, in the which behalve and oderwise ye have shewid your self luffing and kynd unto the saide M. John, as I am enfourmed, I hertly thank you, latting you wite that the saide M. John is my kynseman, and soo I have taken hyme and yit doith, as he can and woll more largely show unto you by petiegrew. This I pray you to report, if the case require, and for my sake and othre unto whome he is of kyn, and I shalbe glad to doo what I can for you by Gode's grace, Who preserve you. Frome Cartemell, iij<SUP>d</SUP> day of Novembre.</P>
<P>And hertly I pray you, and everych of you, to remembre the premisseȝ, as my speciall trust is in you. And if y' be eny maliciouse person that wrongfully wuld vex or trouble my saide kynseman, I pray you to be his good maisters according to right. And who so ever it be that soo doith I shall put me in
<PB N="48" REF="44"/>
devour to remembre hym in my power w<SUP>t</SUP> Gode's grace.—W<SUP>t</SUP> the handes of your good lover, Sir Robert Harington, knight.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">House Book, Civ. Ebor.</HI> vi. 48.]</P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<HEAD>To my right worshipfull sirs, the maier, aldermen, sheriffes and common counsell of the citie of York.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SIGNED>Your loveing freynd Jhon Conyers, Knight.</SIGNED></OPENER>
<P>Right worshipfull Sirs, I commaund me unto you. And where I am enfourmed that my trusty and right hertly wel∣beloved M. John Harington haith be put to grete trouble and noted a fals Scott, in the which behalve, as I understand, he haith not onely declared hyme self before you one English man, bot aswele a gentilman borne in the parishing of Estring∣ton, w<SUP>t</SUP>in xiiij miles of the citie of York, and also a graduate of the Universitie of Cambridge, w<SUP>t</SUP> record under the seal of the same Universitie testifying his demenaunce there; and for somuch as the saide M. John, after his commyng frome the saide Universitie, come into this counetre to my service, I certifie you that he was in my service by divers yeres my clerc and secretarie in the rowme of a gentilman, and soo taken unto the tyme of his commyng to York to offic for demeaning hyme to me that I had hyme in my singler favour, and for his trueth, wisedome, and lernyng accept hyme to be of my fee and counesell as yit he is, which I desire and hertly pray you to recorde as the case shall require. And if y' be thing that I may doo for your pleas', I shalbe more glad for his sake to accomplish the same by Gode's grace, Who preserve you. Frome Horneby, the xxiiij day of Octobr'.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">House Book, Civ. Ebor.</HI> vi. 49.]</P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<P>To all trewe Cristen people to whom y<SUP>is</SUP> present writtyng <NOTE PLACE="marg">1496. Robert Elwald.</NOTE> shall come or be shewed, Roland Prior of Hexham, Gilbert Eryngton, John Ridlee, squyers, Robert Eryngton of Whittyng∣ton, Nicholas Eryngton, Symon Armestrang, Charles Eryngton, gentilmen, Sir Robert Whitqwam chaplayn &amp; parysch prest of Saynt John ec, &amp; William Smyth, parysche clerk of the
<PB N="49" REF="45"/>
same, Thomas Sourby, John Denyng, John Spane, Robert Lee, Thomas Grene, John Copden, yomen, sendes gretyng in our Lord God everlastyng, &amp;, to whome it belongeth, dieu recomen∣dacion. And for so mekyll as it is meritory, medefull, and a speciall dede of charite to certiffie and witnes the trewth in every rightwise mater, therfor we make it knawen to your universite that Robert Elwalde, the son of John Elwald, is a trewe Ynglischeman, getten of his fader beforsayd and born of his moder, w<SUP>t</SUP>in ye parysche of Saynt John Baptist within Hexham shire, &amp; his godfadyrs callyd John Elwald of the said parische, &amp; John Robson of ye Langelee, and his godmoder callid Janet Elwald of Hakefurth within ye said shire of Hexham, &amp; Cristened in ye fount of ye said parische of Saynt John Baptist. Wherfor we pray &amp; charitably exhorte all our good loufers, welwillers, and frendes that ye walde help &amp; supporte the said Robert Elwald in his right, as ye wald we did to frendes and neghbours of yours, if the case require. In witnes herof we above said hase setto our seales. Gyffen at Hexham, the xxviij<SUP>th</SUP> day of Octobre, in the xij<SUP>th</SUP> yere of the regne of our soveraigne lord Kyng Henre the vij<SUP>th</SUP>.</P>
<P><HI REND="italic">Litera testimonialis pro Roberto Elwald de Eboraco conyour.—</HI></P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">York House Book,</HI> viii. 12.]</P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<P>Be it knowen to all Cristen pepill to whome this present <NOTE PLACE="marg">1496. William Robinson.</NOTE> writtyng shall here or see, that where it is meritorie to every Cristen creature to certifye a mater of trewth, we, Thomas Darnwater of Lepington, gentilman, Sir William Darnwater, his broder, chantry prest of Saynt Mary kirk in Castellgate, John Bell of York yoman, Janet Bell wiff unto William Wright of York, and Issabell Materson wiff to Robert Abell of York fyscher, certifieth &amp; recordeth that William Robynson of York, wever, is a trewe Ynglisch man borne, &amp; was borne in a towne called Boulton in Westmerland, &amp; Cristined within All Halowe kyrk within the said town. His fader name was William Robynson, &amp; his moder name Katerine; his godfader's name Adame Wolfe, &amp; his other godfader's name was Adam Kedy, &amp; his godmoder was John Dernwater wiff of Boulton gentilman, moder unto Thomas of Darnwater &amp; S<SUP>r</SUP> William Darnwater
<PB N="50" REF="46"/>
above written; and John Percevall of Ousby godfader unto ye said William Robynson under ye bischop hand, and Janet Bell above written god suster unto ye said William Robynson, John Bell, &amp; Issabell Materson above wrytten, borne in ye said town wher the said William Robynson was borne. And for more declaracion of treuth in the premiseȝ, we the abovesaid Thomas Darnwater, &amp; oyer tofore named, ar &amp; shalbe redy to record &amp; testifie thees premyses at every tyme when we yerto shalbe reasonably requyred. In witnes &amp; record herof the partieȝ above∣said hath setto theyr sealeȝ, the xxiij<SUP>th</SUP> day of moneth of Decembre, the xij<SUP>th</SUP> yere of ye regne of Kyng Henry the vij<SUP>th</SUP>.—</P><TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">York House Book,</HI> viii. 14<HI REND="italic">a.]</HI></P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="certificate">
<P>Unto all Cristen men to qwome this present writtynge shall <NOTE PLACE="marg">1497. John, Thos., and Ralph Nelson.</NOTE> come, we, Sir James Strangways Knyght, Thomas Prior of Montgrace, S<SUP>r</SUP> John Pekett vicar of ye parysche kyrke of Osmonderley, Thomas Loraunce, James Balderston, John Baxster, Henr' Thomson, George Thomson, William Lowraunce, Robert Balderston, John Hudson, Thomas Dixson, William Noddyng, Thomas Hudson, Robert Laken, John Balderston, John Seneer, Robert Seneer, William Prud, Thomas Lokwod, John Cruke, Robert Appilby, John Laken &amp; Thomas Laynge yomen. In asmyche as it is medfull &amp; meritory to every trewe Cristen man for to certifie the trouth in every mater, therfor we certifie to yowe for trewth &amp; recordie yat John Nelson, Thomas Nelson, &amp; Raufe Nelson ar Ynglyschmen, &amp; born in town of Osmonderley, &amp; Cristient at ye same kyrk. In witnes wherof we have setto our seales. Geven at Osmonderley, the viij<SUP>th</SUP> day of ye moneth of Septembre, ye yere of our Lord m<SUP>l</SUP>cccc iiij<SUP>xx</SUP>.xvij.</P>
<P><TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL ROWS="3">John Nelson</CELL>
<CELL>James Clerk, godfader.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>William Evynwood, god∣fader.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>Agnes Darley, godmoder.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL ROWS="3">Raufe Nelson</CELL>
<CELL>Sir Rauffe Surtes, godfader.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>Robert Makynson, god∣fader.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>Agnes Yngilby, godmoder.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL ROWS="3">Th. Nelson</CELL>
<CELL>Thomas Corte, godfader.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>James Balderston, godfader.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>Issabell Wellerby, god∣moder.</CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE></P>
<TAILNOTE><P>[<HI REND="italic">York House Book,</HI> viii. 27.]</P></TAILNOTE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="treatise">
<PB N="58" REF="47"/>
<HEAD>VI. CUSTOMS AND LIBERTIES OF THE BURGESSES OF NEW MALTON. SAEC. XV.]</HEAD>
<HEADNOTE><P>[From the Original Roll.]</P></HEADNOTE>
<P>Thies er the custumes and libertes, the qwhyche was concest and graunted to the Burgese of New Mallton at the fyrst fun∣dacyon of the sayd Malton be the Lorde of y<SUP>e</SUP> same, and in all tymys hydyrward hath ben usyd.</P>
<P>Fyrst it was graunted to the for sayd Burgeses a wast of ather syde of the town of New Malton, y<SUP>t</SUP> the Burgeses and thare successors schall in the sayd wastys gett stone, and fro thens stone and erd take and cary to the edyficacion and beyldyng w<SUP>t</SUP>in y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd town, when som ever y<SUP>ai</SUP> wyll, and als ofte as thay wyll, w<SUP>t</SUP> owtyn impedyment of any man. And thay schall haffe iiij portes, that is to say iiij ȝattes, and y<SUP>e</SUP> walles of ye sayd Burgage undyr . . . awn kepyng w<SUP>t</SUP> fre entre and goyng oute w<SUP>t</SUP>in the sayd walles of y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgage, w<SUP>t</SUP> all y<SUP>e</SUP> proffettes of y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd walles, to the mendyng of y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd walles, and also of y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd ȝattes. And the sayd Burgese ever more hathe usyd for to pastur' and to fede y<SUP>r</SUP> bestes in y<SUP>e</SUP> fore sayd wastes.</P>
<P>Also it was grauntyd y<SUP>e</SUP> fore sayd Burgese common pastur' to all y<SUP>r</SUP> bestes in y<SUP>e</SUP> feyldes and in y<SUP>e</SUP> more, fer and ner, and in all othyr places, excepptt severall of y<SUP>e</SUP> lorde, w<SUP>t</SUP> fre entre and goyng owte to y<SUP>e</SUP> mor' by a large way, the qwhyche is called y<SUP>e</SUP> owtegang, w<SUP>t</SUP>owtyn any styntyng; and y<SUP>e</SUP> pastur' and y<SUP>e</SUP> owtegang war graunted and gyffen to y<SUP>e</SUP> fore sayd Burgese of y<SUP>e</SUP> lordi's lande of y<SUP>e</SUP> fore sayd Burgage.</P>
<P>Also it was graunted and usyd y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgese afore sayd schulde haffe y<SUP>r</SUP> fre cowrtt for to be haldyn w<SUP>t</SUP> in y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgage a fore sayd; and thay schall haffe two Ballyffes and two undyr Ballyffes, j Burgese clerke resydentt and bydyng w<SUP>t</SUP> in y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgage, for to hold the fore sayd cowrtt of ther own fre will . . . be xij sworne Burgese be thar fayth y<SUP>t</SUP> thay made to the lorde and to y<SUP>e</SUP> commonte of y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgage. And y<SUP>t</SUP> noo othyr Balyffe schal make no tachement nor somond w<SUP>t</SUP> in y<SUP>e</SUP> fore sayd
<PB N="59" REF="48"/>
Burgage w<SUP>t</SUP> owte y<SUP>e</SUP> Balyffe of y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgage y<SUP>t</SUP> is sworne. And y<SUP>t</SUP> no distreyn y<SUP>t</SUP> is made w<SUP>t</SUP> in y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgage schall be remevyd w<SUP>t</SUP> owten y<SUP>e</SUP> libertye of y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgage.</P>
<P>Also [it] is grauntyd and usyd y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>e</SUP> fore sayd Burgese schall make bott ij suttes by y<SUP>e</SUP> ȝer' to y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd cowrtt, that is to say, at y<SUP>e</SUP> grett cowrtt next eftyr y<SUP>e</SUP> fest of Sayntt Myghell, and at y<SUP>e</SUP> grett cowrtt next eftyr Sayntt Hyllare day, exceppyd thay haffe prisoners for to delyver, or jugement of any playntt for to be gyffen. And yai schall haffe y' viij days of somondes; and at all y<SUP>e</SUP> fore sayd cowrtes may y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgese assoyn yame ons or twyse, and iffe yai make a defawte and apper efter ye seconde assoyn yai schall be amersyd iiij d., and no more.</P>
<P>Also it is usyd y<SUP>t</SUP> noo man y<SUP>t</SUP> haldes of thame schall haffe noo cowrte bot alonly y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgese cowrte, and also y' schal noo cowrtt be halden w<SUP>t</SUP> in y<SUP>e</SUP> liberte of y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgage bot y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd cowrte of ye Burgage.</P>
<P>Also it is grauntyd and usyd y<SUP>t</SUP> no Burgese, nor noo odyr man that dwellys w<SUP>t</SUP> in y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgage, schall sew one a nodyr bot alonely in y<SUP>e</SUP> cowrtte of y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgage; and iffe any Burgese of y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgage be sewed be any man of y<SUP>e</SUP> contre, or any neghbur of y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgage, the sayd Burgese schall haffe hys viij days respett; and iffe so be y<SUP>t</SUP> and he come in to y<SUP>e</SUP> cowrte y<SUP>e</SUP> fyrst day after he be atachyd, and aske viij days fro y<SUP>t</SUP> day and also he schall haffe hys delays, that is to say twa assoynys after every apperyng; and that als well y<SUP>e</SUP> playntyffe as y<SUP>e</SUP> defender in all maner of playnttes als well of dett as of trespas, and also in pley of lande and als wele wagyd os be fore.</P>
<P>And iffe so be y<SUP>t</SUP> and a Burgese of y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgage sew hys neghbur of y<SUP>e</SUP> same town, no Burgese or any man of y<SUP>e</SUP> contr . . . e schall haffe cowrte fro day to day w<SUP>t</SUP> hys delays, y<SUP>t</SUP> is to say two assoynis, als wele ye playnttyffe as the defender.</P>
<P>And iffe so be y<SUP>t</SUP> he apper not after y<SUP>e</SUP> seconde assoyn, than schall y<SUP>e</SUP> foresayd soyn be turned in to defawte, and he schall be amercyd be y<SUP>e</SUP> aferyng of xij men.</P>
<P>Also it is usyd y<SUP>t</SUP> yffe any man that dwellys w<SUP>t</SUP> in y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgage, als wele a foraner as Burges, be sommonyd or atachyd to any cowrte w<SUP>t</SUP> owte ye Burgage, or to the wapyn∣tak, the Balyffes or Subbalyffes of y<SUP>e</SUP> said Burgage, or any
<PB N="60" REF="49"/>
mynister of ye Lorde's haffyng lett' patant of the lorde, come to thame y<SUP>t</SUP> hold y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd cowrtt or wapyntake the fyrst day of somondes or atachement, and aske y<SUP>e</SUP> prevalege of y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgage, he y<SUP>t</SUP> holdes y<SUP>e</SUP> cowrte or wapyntake schall graunte it, so y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>e</SUP> ryght jugement be done to every man.</P>
<P>Also it is graunted and usyd that y<SUP>e</SUP> jugement of all maner of playnttes and consideraconys in ye sayd Burgag cowrte schall be gyffen and jugyd be y<SUP>e</SUP> sutterys of y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd cowrte, and all mercyamentes fered, exceppyd alonely the amercya∣mentes of y<SUP>e</SUP> comon backster and assyse of brede, and of alle odyr transgrescyons y<SUP>t</SUP> towchys the lorde's persons.</P>
<P>Also it is grauntyd y<SUP>t</SUP> alle Burgese of y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgage schall be fre of all maner of toll of y<SUP>e</SUP> lord in all maner of merchauntyse, bot iffe yai be assocyat w<SUP>t</SUP> any foroner or stranger, and than the foroner and the stranger schall gyffe toll als wele for ye Burgese as for hym selfe, exceppyd common bucherys, the qwyche gyffes toll dayly of old custom, and exceppyd Burgese y<SUP>t</SUP> sellys heryng in Lentyn, y<SUP>e</SUP> qwhyche schall gyffe for sellyng of m<SUP>l</SUP> heryng j d., or ellys for sellyng of ye same thay schall gyffe to y<SUP>e</SUP> skattegyld iiij d.</P>
<P>Also it is grauntyd to thame a fre prison for all maner of evyll doers that er takyn w<SUP>t</SUP> in y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgage, that in y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd cowrte, by y<SUP>e</SUP> commonte of the sutterys, thay may juge the sayd prisoners or mysdoers and delyver thame. And y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgese schall w<SUP>t</SUP> in y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgage ordan a pelory and a thew, lawfull and strang.</P>
<P>Also it is usyd y<SUP>at</SUP> y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgese of y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgage schall answere be fore the justyse of pease in all sessyons and inqwyres w<SUP>t</SUP> xij chosyn of the same; and also before the scheryffe in hys Turne holdyn w<SUP>t</SUP> in y<SUP>e</SUP> liberte of y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgag, and in no nodyr place; and that y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgese schall make y<SUP>r</SUP> a panyll of y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd xij, and y<SUP>t</SUP> panyll schall be presentyd and delyvered be fore y<SUP>e</SUP> Justicie or y<SUP>e</SUP> Scheryffe by y<SUP>e</SUP> Balyffe, or Subballyffe of y<SUP>e</SUP> same Burgag.</P>
<P>Also it is grauntyd to y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgese a liberte for to grynde y<SUP>r</SUP> corne and y<SUP>r</SUP> maltt at the mylne of y<SUP>e</SUP> lord, that is to say, when j qwharter wheytt is sald for iiij s., than schall y<SUP>r</SUP> corne be multyrd at y<SUP>e</SUP> xvj vessell; and qwhen j qwharter
<PB N="61" REF="50"/>
qwheytt is sold for iiij s. vj d. and mor to it come to vj s., yan y<SUP>r</SUP> corn schall be multeryd at y<SUP>e</SUP> xx vessell; and qwhen j qwharter qwheytt is sold for vj s., than y<SUP>r</SUP> corn schall be multeryd at y<SUP>e</SUP> xxiiij vesell.</P>
<P>And yai schall haffe in y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd mylnes two mylners and j page chosyn by y<SUP>e</SUP> assent of ye commonte of ye Burgage, the qwhyche mylners schall be sworn in y<SUP>e</SUP> cowrtt at two tymes in y<SUP>e</SUP> yere, that is to say, at y<SUP>e</SUP> two hede cowrttes to y<SUP>e</SUP> commonte off the Burgage, and non of the mylners schall take no maner of thyng of thame y<SUP>t</SUP> grynd y<SUP>r</SUP> corn for y<SUP>r</SUP> labor, bott alonly of hym y<SUP>t</SUP> is y<SUP>e</SUP> chefe mylner.</P>
<P>Also y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgese schall grynd iiij qwhartars maltt for j d., and it be broght to the mylne all to gedyr and at o tyme; and ȝhe haffe bott j quarter at o tyme, thay schall gyffe for y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd quarter gryndyng a farthyng.</P>
<P>Also it is used that all maner of mesurys of y<SUP>e</SUP> mylne that yai take multyr w<SUP>t</SUP> schall (be) proved in y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd cowrte of the Burgage by y<SUP>e</SUP> Balyffes two tymes in y<SUP>e</SUP> ȝhere, and y<SUP>r</SUP> schal no mylner be remevyd fro y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd mylnes w<SUP>t</SUP> owtyn y<SUP>e</SUP> assent of y<SUP>e</SUP> commonte of y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgage, nor y<SUP>r</SUP> schall no mylner be putt into y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd mylne w<SUP>t</SUP> outyn ye assent of y<SUP>e</SUP> commonte, nor mynyst' in y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd mylnes be fore y<SUP>t</SUP> he be sworn to be trew to y<SUP>e</SUP> commonte.</P>
<P>Also it was grauntyd and usyd y<SUP>t</SUP> all ye Burgese of y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgage, and all y<SUP>t</SUP> dwels w<SUP>t</SUP> in it, may grynde y<SUP>r</SUP> corn and y<SUP>r</SUP> maltt y<SUP>t</SUP> yay by in y<SUP>e</SUP> contre, or in y<SUP>e</SUP> markytt, qwher some ever yay wyll, w<SUP>t</SUP> owtyn any impediment so y<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>e</SUP> corne or maltt com never w<SUP>t</SUP>in y<SUP>r</SUP> howses.</P>
<P>Also the sayd Burgese schall haffe y<SUP>e</SUP> standard, that is to say the buschell, halff a buschell and j qwartir of j buschell, and j galon, j potell and j qwarte, j ȝerde wande, and weghttes w<SUP>t</SUP> j pare of balanys, the qwhyche mesures schuld agre w<SUP>t</SUP> the kynge's standard, and be merkyd w<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>e</SUP> merke that is ordande y<SUP>r</SUP> fore; and all maner of mesurys y<SUP>t</SUP> er fondon w<SUP>t</SUP>in y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgage, als wele in y<SUP>e</SUP> mylne as in any odyr place, schall be schewed and prevyd be fore y<SUP>e</SUP> Balyffes and y<SUP>e</SUP> commonte of y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgage, and be merkyd w<SUP>t</SUP> ye merke afore sayd; and y<SUP>e</SUP> standard be fore sayd schall be selled w<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>e</SUP> common seall, and y<SUP>e</SUP>
<PB N="62" REF="51"/>
merke schall be kepyd undyr y<SUP>e</SUP> seallys off iiij Burgese chosyn for the same iṅtent.</P>
<P>Also it is grauntyd that al maner of bakars and buchers schall be sworn two tymes in ye yere to y<SUP>e</SUP> commonte of y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgage, that is to say at y<SUP>e</SUP> two grete cowrttes, y<SUP>t</SUP> yay haffe done trewly in y<SUP>r</SUP> ocupacyon and schall do trewly; and if so be the buchers wyll not doo so, thay schall be amersyd at y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd cowrtt; and the bakars schall be amersyd als ofte as yai fayll; and also ye sayd bakars schall haffe holle brede aftyr y<SUP>e</SUP> ordenance of y<SUP>e</SUP> Ballyffes; and also y<SUP>t</SUP> no bakar y<SUP>t</SUP> bakys qwhytte brede schall bake brown brede for to sell, nor he y<SUP>t</SUP> bakys brown brede schall bake no qwhyte brede.</P>
<P>Also it is usyd and grauntyd that every Burgese of ye sayd Burgage may lawfully sell y<SUP>r</SUP> maltt and y<SUP>r</SUP> ale y<SUP>t</SUP> commys owte of y<SUP>r</SUP> garnes w<SUP>t</SUP> owtyn any interrupcyon of ye Lord or of y<SUP>e</SUP> Ballyffes, and yai may sell y<SUP>r</SUP> ale w<SUP>t</SUP> in y<SUP>r</SUP> awn howses of qwhat pryce som ever thay wyll, and yat, als wele of ye malt y<SUP>t</SUP> thay by, as of y<SUP>t</SUP> that yay hafe in y<SUP>r</SUP> garnes, every tyme in ye ȝere.</P>
<P>Also it is grauntyd and usyd y<SUP>t</SUP> all men y<SUP>t</SUP> dwellys w<SUP>t</SUP>in yis sayd Burgage may sell bred and ale of all maner of pryce y<SUP>t</SUP> yay wyll in the fest of Sanct Myghell and in y<SUP>e</SUP> feste of y<SUP>e</SUP> Byrthe of oure Lorde, un to the next cowrtte aftyr y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd fest, w<SUP>t</SUP> owtyn any interupcion of ye lord or of the Ballyfes.</P>
<P>Also it is grauntyd and usyd that every common brewer y<SUP>t</SUP> wyll sell ale w<SUP>t</SUP> owtyn y<SUP>r</SUP> howses, y<SUP>t</SUP> thay schall mak y<SUP>r</SUP> fyne j tyme in y<SUP>e</SUP> ȝere w<SUP>t</SUP> y<SUP>e</SUP> Ballyffes of y<SUP>e</SUP> Burgage, that is to say at y<SUP>e</SUP> fest of y<SUP>e</SUP> Puryfycacyon of oure Lady, for all y<SUP>e</SUP> ȝere: and thay schall pay halfe y<SUP>r</SUP> fyne att y<SUP>e</SUP> fest of Saynt Petyr callyd y<SUP>e</SUP> Ad Vincula; and y<SUP>e</SUP> todyr halfe at ye fest of y<SUP>e</SUP> Puryfycacyon of owr Lady in y<SUP>e</SUP> ȝere next folowyng, excepyd the brewers y<SUP>t</SUP> holdys of y<SUP>e</SUP> knyghty's fee: and y<SUP>e</SUP> brewers y<SUP>t</SUP> holdes of y<SUP>e</SUP> Prior of Malton, the qwhyche makes noo fyne nor gyffes no thyng to y<SUP>e</SUP> Lorde.</P>
<P>Also it is usyd y<SUP>t</SUP> the sayd Burgese schall chese in y<SUP>r</SUP> cowrte two ale tastars, y<SUP>e</SUP> qwhyche two tastars w<SUP>t</SUP> j subballyffe schall taste the ale of all common brewers every weke; and yai fynde any ale not sufficiant for j peny a galon, than y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd tasturs schall sett it at iij farthynges j galon; and iff so be y<SUP>e</SUP> brewers wyll sell it abown y<SUP>t</SUP> price, thay schall be amersyd, and y<SUP>e</SUP> ale schall be forfett: and y<SUP>t</SUP> sall be als wele of y<SUP>e</SUP>
<PB N="63" REF="52"/>
brewers that hold of y<SUP>e</SUP> Prior of Malton, and of y<SUP>e</SUP> Knyghte's fee, as of othyr brewers of y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgage.</P>
<P>Also it is usyd and graunted y<SUP>t</SUP> every Burgese schall gyff to y<SUP>e</SUP> Lord one tyme in y<SUP>e</SUP> ȝere a farme for hys tenement, the qwhyche is called the gaffelege, that is to say, for every tenement y<SUP>t</SUP> hath j dore j d. And yf so be it be lattyne in farme to y<SUP>e</SUP> cowrte of y<SUP>e</SUP> burgage aftyr y<SUP>e</SUP> fest of Seyntt Myghell: and for every howse y<SUP>t</SUP> is lattyn to farme that hathe two doores ij d. in ye ȝere to y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd cowrte; and for every tofte y<SUP>t</SUP> is nott beldyd j d. by y<SUP>e</SUP> ȝere, exceppyd yay be tenementes of y<SUP>e</SUP> Knyghte's fee, or of y<SUP>e</SUP> Prior of Malton, y<SUP>e</SUP> qwhyche gyffes no thyng to ye Lorde. And if so be a Burgese appropyr many tenementes lyyng all to gedyr, and hold yam to hys propyr use, he schall gyffe butt j gaffelege to y<SUP>e</SUP> Lorde, as it war for j tenement.</P>
<P>Also yffe so be y<SUP>t</SUP> any Burgese haffe dyverse tenementes to hys awn use in dyverse places, or yf he make of j tenement dyverse tenementes w<SUP>t</SUP> dyverse tenandes dwellyng in thame, he schall gyffe hale gaffelege, and it is lefull to every Burgese to sell hys tenementes, or to gyffe yame, or to wyll yame in hys testament w<SUP>t</SUP> owtyn impedyment of the Lorde or of y<SUP>e</SUP> Balyffes, and the Lorde of y<SUP>e</SUP> fee schall not haffe, nor never hade, y<SUP>e</SUP> warde of y<SUP>e</SUP> herytage of any Burgese of y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgage, nor he schall never clame no thyng of y<SUP>e</SUP> herydance, bott alonly hys faythe for hys tenementes or hys lande aftyr y<SUP>e</SUP> decesse of hys pre∣decessors.</P>
<P>Also it is ordanyd y<SUP>t</SUP> no groser of fysche awe to cutt hys awn fysche be hym selffe, nor be a nodyr man, bott yffe y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd fysche be boght w<SUP>t</SUP> odyr men; and yff he doo he schall be amersyd and the fysche sall be forfett.</P>
<P>Also it is ordanyd that no schomakar that makes schone schall nott ocupy nor use the tannar<SUP>s</SUP> crafte, nor a tannar schall not use nor ocupy schomaker crafte.</P>
<P>Al thyes lyberteis and customes [above] wrytyn, w<SUP>t</SUP> many othyr moo liberteis, the qwyche un to the lib . . . Burgage pertenys, the fore sayd Burgeses claymes for to hafe . . . and y<SUP>r</SUP> antecessors liberally hafe usyd be fore tyme, [the qwhyche ty]me is w<SUP>t</SUP> owtyn man's membraunce or mynde, the qwhyche . . . in y<SUP>e</SUP> clayme of y<SUP>e</SUP> sayd Burgeses and also in tyme . . . to be claymed.</P>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>
