<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE><DATE>8-23-16</DATE><RESPSTMT><NAME>lattaj</NAME><RESP>MURP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Added TEMPHEAD, checked ID, and added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Proofed title page. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure; removed DIV2; changed HEAD to HEADNOTE P. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected [dollar]s. Checked for &amp;cs with incorrect spacing. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs and endqs, abq's, oes, qs, Ae's, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections. Checked italic I / J and U / V. Checked for missing page GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTS. Checked CLOSERs, OPENERs, SIGNEDs, SALUTEs, TRAILERs, BYLINEs. Checked decorated initials. Checked FIGUREs. Sample: 2 minutes. Proofing: 0 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 50 minutes. DONE.</ITEM></CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="CME00053">
<STC T="M">53</STC>
<BIBNO T="mec">CME00053</BIBNO>
<VID>CME00053</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="enm">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="4" MS="y"/>
<P>THE ENGLISH CHARLEMAGNE ROMANCES.</P>
<P>PART V.</P>
<P><HI REND="italic">The Romaunce of The Sowdone of Babylone and of ferumbras his Sone who conquerede Rome.</HI></P>
<P>RE-EDITED FROM THE UNIQUE MS. OF THE LATE SIR THOMAS PHILLIPPS, <HI REND="italic">with Introduction, Notes, and Glossary,</HI> BY EMIL HAUSKNECHT, PH. D.</P>
<P>LONDON: PUBLISHED FOR THE EARLY ENGLISH TEXT SOCIETY, BY N. TRÜBNER &amp; CO., 57 &amp; 59, LUDGATE HILL.</P>
<P>MDCCCLXXXI.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="poem">
<PB N="1" REF="72"/>
<HEAD>The Romaunce of the Sowdone of Babylone and of Ferumbras his Sone who Conquerede Rome:</HEAD>
<HEADNOTE><P>From the unique MS. of the late Sir Thos. Phillipps.</P></HEADNOTE>
<LG>
<L>GOd in glorye of myghteste <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> myghtes</NOTE> moost, <MILESTONE N="1"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">God has ordained all things wisely.</NOTE></L>
<L>That al thinge made in sapience</L>
<L>By vertue of woorde and holy goost,</L>
<L>Gyvinge to man grete excellence, <MILESTONE N="4"/></L>
<L>And alle, þat is in erthe, wroght <NOTE PLACE="marg">He has subjected the earth to man, and man to God.</NOTE></L>
<L>Subiecte to man and man̄ to the,</L>
<L>That he shoulde witħ herte and thought</L>
<L>To loue and serve, and noon̄ but the: <MILESTONE N="8"/></L>
<L>For ȝyfe man̄ kepte thy co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>maundemente <NOTE PLACE="marg">The man who keeps His com∣mandments and loves Him well,</NOTE></L>
<L>In al thinge and loued the welle</L>
<L>And hadde synnede in his entente,</L>
<L>Than̄ shulde he fully thy grace fele; <MILESTONE N="12"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">will feel His grace.</NOTE></L>
<L>But for the offences to God I-doo<HI REND="italic">n</HI> <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">MS.</HI> dōō</NOTE> <NOTE PLACE="marg">But many who offended Him have felt His vengeance.</NOTE></L>
<L>Many vengeaunces haue be-falle.</L>
<L>Where-of I wole yoū telle of oon̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">I will tell you of one; it would take too long to tell of all.</NOTE></L>
<L>It were to mocħ to telle of alle. <MILESTONE N="16"/></L>
<L>While þat Rome was in excellence</L>
<L>Of alle Realmes in dignite, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Listen to me, and ye shall hear how Rome, the former mistress of all nations, came to fall by its sins,</NOTE></L>
<L>And howe it felle for his offence,</L>
<L>Listinythe a while and ye shal see, <MILESTONE N="20"/></L>
<L>Howe it was wonen̄ and brente</L>
<L>Of a Sowdon̄, that heathen̄ was, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and was destroyed by a heathen Soudan.</NOTE></L>
<L>And for synne howe it was shente;</L>
<L>As Kinge Lowes witnessith þat cas, <MILESTONE N="24"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">King Lewis has borne witness to</NOTE></L>
<L><PB N="2" REF="73"/>
As it is wryten in Romaunce <NOTE PLACE="marg">that story, which, written in Ro∣mance and found in very old chro∣nicles at St Denys in France, relates</NOTE></L>
<L>And founden in bokes of Antiquyte</L>
<L>At Seinte Denyse Abbey in Fraunce[e], <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">leaf worn.</NOTE></L>
<L>There as Cronycles remembrede be, <MILESTONE N="28"/></L>
<L>Howe Laban, the kinge of hie degre, <NOTE PLACE="marg">how Laban, the king of Babylon, who was born at Ascalon, con∣quered a great part of Christen∣dom.</NOTE></L>
<L>And sy<ABBR>r</ABBR> and Sowdon̄ of hie Babilon̄,</L>
<L>Conquerede grete parte of Christiante,</L>
<L>That was born in Askalon̄. <MILESTONE N="32"/></L>
<L>And in the Cite of Agremare <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> <NOTE PLACE="marg">He was holding his court in the city of Agremore, on the river Flagot,</NOTE></L>
<L>Vppon̄ the Rivere of Flagote</L>
<L>At þat tyme he soiorned the<ABBR>r</ABBR> <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE></L>
<L>Fulle roially, wel I wote, <MILESTONE N="36"/></L>
<L>With kinges xij and Admyralles xiiij, <NOTE PLACE="marg">with 12 kings and 14 amirals, and many worthy barons and knights,</NOTE></L>
<L>With many a Baron̄ &amp; Kniȝtis ful boold,</L>
<L>That roialle were and semly to sene;</L>
<L>Here worþynesse al may not be told. <MILESTONE N="40"/></L>
<L>Hit bifelle by-twyxte March and Maye, <MILESTONE N="1, bk" UNIT="lf"/></L>
<L>Whan kynde corage begynneth to pryke, <NOTE PLACE="marg">when, in the time between March and May,</NOTE></L>
<L>Whan̄ ffritħ and felde wexen gaye,</L>
<L>And every wight desirith his like, <MILESTONE N="44"/></L>
<L>Whan̄ lovers slepen̄ withe opyn̄ yȝe,</L>
<L>As Nightyngalis on grene tre,</L>
<L>And sore desire þat thai cowde flye,</L>
<L>That thay myghte withe here lou<HI REND="italic">er</HI>e be: <MILESTONE N="48"/></L>
<L>This worthy Sowdon̄ in this seson̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">he went to the chase</NOTE></L>
<L>Shope him to grene woode to goon̄,</L>
<L>To chase the Bore or the Veneson̄,</L>
<L>The Wolfe, the Bere and the Bawson. <MILESTONE N="52"/></L>
<L>He roode tho vppon̄ a fforeste stronde <NOTE PLACE="marg">in a wood near the sea.</NOTE></L>
<L>With grete rowte and roialte,</L>
<L>The fairest, þat was in alle þat londe,</L>
<L>With Alauntes, Ly<HI REND="italic">m</HI>meris and Racches free. <MILESTONE N="56"/></L>
<L>His huntes to chace he co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>maunde,</L>
<L>Here Bugles boldely for to blowe,</L>
<L>To fere the beestis in þat launde.</L>
<L><PB N="3" REF="74"/>
The Sowdon̄ woxe wery I-nowe; <MILESTONE N="60"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Being weary with hunting, he sat down under a holm tree, and,</NOTE></L>
<L>He rested him vndere an holme tre</L>
<L>Sittynge vppon̄ a grene sete</L>
<L>Seynge a Dromonde com sailyng in þ<SUP>e</SUP> see <NOTE PLACE="marg">seeing a dromond sailing on the sea, he charged one to enquire for news concerning the ship.</NOTE></L>
<L>Anone he charged to bekyn̄ him w<HI REND="italic">i</HI>t<HI REND="italic">h</HI> honde <MILESTONE N="64"/></L>
<L>To here of him tidinges newe.</L>
<L>The maist<HI REND="italic">er</HI> sende a man to londe, <NOTE PLACE="marg">The interpreter of the vessel being sent ashore, in∣formed the soudan, that this dromond, freighted at Babylon,</NOTE></L>
<L>Of diuers langages was gode and trewe,</L>
<L>And saide "lorde, this Dromonde <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> <MILESTONE N="68"/></L>
<L>Fro Babyloyne comen̄ is,</L>
<L>That was worþe thousande poundis,</L>
<L>As <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">or</HI> Ar</NOTE> it mete with shrewes I-wis,</L>
<L>Charged with perle and p<HI REND="italic">re</HI>cious stones <MILESTONE N="72"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">with a cargo of rich furs, spices, oil, brass and pearls, intended as a present to the soudan, had been driven by stress of weather to Rome, where they had been robbed by the Romans.</NOTE></L>
<L>And riche pelure and spicerye,</L>
<L>With oyle and bras qweynte for the nones</L>
<L>To presente yow, my lorde worthy.</L>
<L>A drift of wedi<ABBR>r</ABBR> vs droffe to Rome, <MILESTONE N="76"/></L>
<L>The Romaynes robbed vs anone;</L>
<L>Of vs thai slowgh ful many one.</L>
<L>With sorwe and care we be bygone.</L>
<L>Whereof, lorde, remedye <MILESTONE N="80"/> <MILESTONE N="3" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Ye ordeyne by youre Barons boolde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Therefore he solicited that the soudan would take revenge on those who had done such villainy to him.</NOTE></L>
<L>To wreke the of this vilane;</L>
<L>Or certes oure blis is coolde."</L>
<L>The Soudon hirynge this tyþinge, <MILESTONE N="84"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">The soudan, hearing these tidings, made a vow to Mahound and to Apolyn, that they should dearly pay for it.</NOTE></L>
<L>With egre chere he made a vowe</L>
<L>To Mahounde and to Appolyne,</L>
<L>That thai shulde by it dere I-nowe,</L>
<L>Er that he wente fro theyme. <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> <MILESTONE N="88"/></L>
<L>"Where be ye, my kinges boolde,</L>
<L>My Barons and my Admyral?</L>
<L>Thes tidinges make myn herte coolde</L>
<L>But I be venged, dyen I shalle. <MILESTONE N="92"/></L>
<L>Sire Ferumbras, my sone so dere, <NOTE PLACE="marg">'Ferumbras, my son,' he said, 'and my daughter Floripas, ye must</NOTE></L>
<L>Ye muste me comforte in this case;</L>
<L><PB N="4" REF="75"/>
My ioye is alle in the nowe here <NOTE PLACE="marg">be my comfort in this case.</NOTE></L>
<L>And in my Doghter Dame Florypas. <MILESTONE N="96"/></L>
<L>Sortybraunce, my Counselere, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Order Sorti∣brance, my counsellor, to be called for, and my chancellor Oliborn,</NOTE></L>
<L>Lete clepe him forthe to counsaile me,</L>
<L>And Oliborne, my Chauncelere</L>
<L>And noble Clerke of hie degre, <MILESTONE N="100"/></L>
<L>And Espiarde, my messangere, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and Espiard my messenger, that he may go to Africa and to Asia and to all the princes, who owe me allegiance, and command them hastily to assemble with shield and lance at Agremore."</NOTE></L>
<L>To goon to Assye and to Aufrike,</L>
<L>To kinges, princes fer<ABBR>r</ABBR> and ne<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>Barons, Admyralls and Dukes frike, <MILESTONE N="104"/></L>
<L>Comaundinge hem vppon̄ her legeaunce</L>
<L>To come in al hast vnto me,</L>
<L>Wel Armed with shelde and launse,</L>
<L>To Egremoure þon̄ riche Cite." <MILESTONE N="108"/></L>
<L>In shorte tyme this message was wroghte <NOTE PLACE="marg">In a short time 100,000 men had assembled.</NOTE></L>
<L>An hundred thouusande on a rowte</L>
<L>That robbery was righte dere boght,</L>
<L>Was never none derrer withoute<HI REND="italic">n</HI> douȝte. <MILESTONE N="112"/></L>
<L>The kinge of Baldas, sir Lukafe<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">On the advice of Lukafer, king of Baldas,</NOTE></L>
<L>Of Aufryke lorde and governoure,</L>
<L>Spake to the Sowdon̄, that me<HI REND="italic">n</HI> myghte here,</L>
<L>And saide "sir, for thyn honou<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <MILESTONE N="116"/></L>
<L>Do sende for shippes both fe<ABBR>r</ABBR> and nere."</L>
<L>Carrikes, Galeis and shippes shene, <NOTE PLACE="marg">the soudan also brought together 700 sail and a</NOTE></L>
<L>vij hundred were gadered al in fere</L>
<L>And a Dromonde for the Sowden̄ kene. <MILESTONE N="120"/> <MILESTONE N="4" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Sir Ferumbras of Alisaundre <NOTE PLACE="marg">dromond for himself, for Fe∣rumbras of Alex∣andrie, for the</NOTE></L>
<L>In the Dromonde with him was,</L>
<L>Of Assy the kinge of Chaunde<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Asiatic king of Chaunder and for Floripas.</NOTE></L>
<L>And his faire dogħter Floripas. <MILESTONE N="124"/></L>
<L>Two maistres were in the Dromounde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">There were two masters in that vessel, and two idols placed on the main top, with round maces, therewith to menace the Christians. The sails of red sendal-silk were</NOTE></L>
<L>Two goddes on hye seten̄ thore</L>
<L>In the maister toppe, withe macis rounde,</L>
<L>To manace with the Cristen̄ lore. <MILESTONE N="128"/></L>
<L>The sailes were of rede Sendelle,</L>
<L>Embrowdred witħ riche araye,</L>
<L><PB N="5" REF="76"/>
With beestes and breddes every dele, <NOTE PLACE="marg">richly em∣broidered with figures of animals and birds.</NOTE></L>
<L>That was right curious and gaye; <MILESTONE N="132"/></L>
<L>The Armes displaied of Laban</L>
<L>Of Asure and foure lions of goolde. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Four golden lions, the arms of the soudan of Babylon, were also displayed thereon.</NOTE></L>
<L>Of Babiloyne the riche Sowdon̄,</L>
<L>Moost myghty man he was of moolde, <MILESTONE N="136"/></L>
<L>He made a vowe to Termagaunte, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Laban made a vow to Terma∣gant, to destroy Rome, and after that Charle∣magne.</NOTE></L>
<L>Whan Rome were distroied &amp; hade myschau<HI REND="italic">n</HI>ce,</L>
<L>He woolde turne ayen erraunte</L>
<L>And distroye Charles the kinge of Fraunce. <MILESTONE N="140"/></L>
<L>Fortħ thai sailed on the flode,</L>
<L>Tille thai come to the haven of Rome: <NOTE PLACE="marg">Having disem∣barked in the haven of Rome,</NOTE></L>
<L>The wynde hem served, it was ful goode.</L>
<L>Ther londed many a grymlye gome. <MILESTONE N="144"/></L>
<L>Thai brente and slowen, þat Cristen were, <NOTE PLACE="marg">they slew all Christians, and burned towns, abbeys and churches.</NOTE></L>
<L>Town̄, Abbey and holy chirche.</L>
<L>The hethen hade such power there,</L>
<L>That moche woo gan thai there wircħ. <MILESTONE N="148"/></L>
<L>Tidinggis came to Rome anone <NOTE PLACE="marg">The Pope of Rome, hearing of the heathens laying waste the whole country,</NOTE></L>
<L>Unto the Pope, that þ<SUP>t</SUP> tyme was,</L>
<L>That the heþen came to bren and slone.</L>
<L>This was to hem a sory cas. <MILESTONE N="152"/></L>
<L>He lete cal his counsaile to-geder <NOTE PLACE="marg">assembled his council.</NOTE></L>
<L>To wete, what was beste to don̄.</L>
<L>Anone as thai were come þede<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>He asked of hem al ful sone: <MILESTONE N="156"/></L>
<L>"Lordinges, it is vnknowne <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> to you,</L>
<L>That this cursed hathen Sowdon̄</L>
<L>Bre<HI REND="italic">n</HI>nyth and stroyeth oure pepul nowe,</L>
<L>Alive he leveth vnneth not one. <MILESTONE N="160"/></L>
<L>Seint Petir be oure governoure <MILESTONE N="5" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>And save this worthi Cite of Rome,</L>
<L>And Seinte Poule be oure gydoure</L>
<L>From this cursed hethen̄ houne <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">looks like</HI> hound.</NOTE>!" <MILESTONE N="164"/></L>
<L>Ifreȝ he bispake him than̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Jeffrez, a senator</NOTE></L>
<L><PB N="6" REF="77"/>
Of Rome he was a Senatoure, <NOTE PLACE="marg">of Rome, advised that worthy men should be sent to Charles of Douce France to implore his assistance.</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "senditħ some worthy man</L>
<L>To Charles kinge of hye honoure. <MILESTONE N="168"/></L>
<L>He wolde you helpe with al his mygħte,</L>
<L>That noble kinge of Dowse Fraunce."</L>
<L>"Certes" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Savaris "þat weren no rigħte, <NOTE PLACE="marg">But Duke Savariz, thinking this to be a wretched piece of timidity,</NOTE></L>
<L>It were right a foule myschaunce, <MILESTONE N="172"/></L>
<L>To sende to þat worthy kinge.</L>
<L>We have oure hedes yet al hole, <NOTE PLACE="marg">as they had not tried anything for themselves,</NOTE></L>
<L>Oure sheldes be not broke no-thinge,</L>
<L>Hawberke, spere, ner poleyne, ner pole. <MILESTONE N="176"/></L>
<L>Where-of shul we playn̄ to him,</L>
<L>That no thinge yet have assaide?</L>
<L>Mecħ uylanye we myght wynne,</L>
<L>That for noght were so sone afrayed. <MILESTONE N="180"/></L>
<L>Ten thousande men delyu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>e me tyte <NOTE PLACE="marg">asked for 10,000 men to be put under his command.</NOTE></L>
<L>Tomorue next in-to the feelde,</L>
<L>And I shall prove with al my myghte</L>
<L>To breke there bothe spere and shelde." <MILESTONE N="184"/></L>
<L>Vnto the Senatours it semed welle,</L>
<L>His counsaile goode and honourable.</L>
<L>This worthi Duke was armed in stele</L>
<L>In armes goode and profitable; <MILESTONE N="188"/></L>
<L>He bare a Chek of goulis clere,</L>
<L>An Egle of goolde abrode displayed.</L>
<L>With him many a bolde Bachelere</L>
<L>Tho spake Savaryȝ witħ wordes on hye <MILESTONE N="192"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">The next morning the duke ad∣dressed his men,</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "my felowes alle,</L>
<L>This daie prove you men̄ worthy,</L>
<L>And faire you al shal befalle.</L>
<L>Thenke yat Criste is more myghty <MILESTONE N="196"/></L>
<L>Than here fals goddis alle;</L>
<L>And he shal geve vs the victorie,</L>
<L>And foule shal hem this day bifalle."</L>
<L>Fortħ than rode þat faire Ooste <MILESTONE N="200"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">and directed them to the soudan's</NOTE></L>
<L>With right goode chere and randon̄,</L>
<L><PB N="7" REF="78"/>
Tille than come ful nyȝe the cooste. <NOTE PLACE="marg">pavilion near the shore.</NOTE></L>
<L>Of the Sowdons Pavylon̄ <MILESTONE N="6" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Ferumbras was of hem ware <MILESTONE N="204"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras, that doughty warrior, becoming aware of them, led</NOTE></L>
<L>And sprange out as a sparkil of glede;</L>
<L>Of Armes bright a sheelde he bare,</L>
<L>A Doughty man̄ he was of dede.</L>
<L>xv thousande came oute there <MILESTONE N="208"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">15,000 men against the Romans.</NOTE></L>
<L>With him at þat same tyde,</L>
<L>Ayen the Romaynes for to were,</L>
<L>Witħ bobaunce, booste and grete pride.</L>
<L>The stoure was stronge, enduryn<ABBR>g</ABBR> longe: <MILESTONE N="212"/></L>
<L>The Romaynes hade there the feelde;</L>
<L>The Sarysyns thai slougħ amonge,</L>
<L>Ten thousand and mo with spere and sheelde. <NOTE PLACE="marg">10,000 and more of the Saracens were slain, and the Romans, though victorious, were led back to Rome by the cautious Savaris.</NOTE></L>
<L>Sauariz was wise and ware <MILESTONE N="216"/></L>
<L>And drowe towards þat Citee.</L>
<L>His baner displaied witħ him he bare</L>
<L>To releve with his meyne.</L>
<L>The Pope with his Senatours <MILESTONE N="220"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">The Pope thanked God for the victory.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thanked god þat tyme of glorie,</L>
<L>That gafe hem þat day grete honours,</L>
<L>Of hethen that dai to have the victorie.</L>
<L>Lukafere, kinge of Baldas, <MILESTONE N="224"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Lukafer of Baldas having scoured the country,</NOTE></L>
<L>The countrey hade serchid and sought,</L>
<L>Ten thousande maidyns faire of face <NOTE PLACE="marg">brought 10,000 maidens to the soudan, who</NOTE></L>
<L>Vnto the Sowdan hath he broghte.</L>
<L>The Sowdon̄ co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>manded hem anone, <MILESTONE N="228"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">ordered them to be slain,</NOTE></L>
<L>That thai shulde al be slayn̄.</L>
<L>Martires thai were eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ychon̄,</L>
<L>And therof were thai al ful fayne.</L>
<L>He saide "my peple nowe ne shalle <MILESTONE N="232"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">saying, he would not have his people polluted by them, and he would destroy every Christian seed.</NOTE></L>
<L>With hem noughte defouled be,</L>
<L>But I wole distroie ou<HI REND="italic">er</HI> all</L>
<L>The sede over alle Cristiante."</L>
<L>Tho spake lukefere the kinge, <MILESTONE N="236"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Lukafer said to the soudan:</NOTE></L>
<L>That hethen̄ hounde Baldas,</L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="79"/>
And saide "Sir Sowdan̄, g<HI REND="italic">ra</HI>unte me one thinge, <NOTE PLACE="marg">"Grant me thy daughter and I will bring thee Charlemagne and all his twelve peers."</NOTE></L>
<L>Thi doghter Dame Floripas.</L>
<L>The kinge of Fraunce I shal the bringe <MILESTONE N="240"/></L>
<L>And the xij dosipers alle in fere."</L>
<L>The Sowdan saide in þat tokenyn<ABBR>g</ABBR>,</L>
<L>"I g<HI REND="italic">ra</HI>unte the here, that is so dere." <NOTE PLACE="marg">Laban assented; but Floripas said, she would only consent to be his darling,</NOTE></L>
<L>Tho sayde Floripe "sire, noon̄ haste, <MILESTONE N="244"/></L>
<L>He hath note done as he hath saide.</L>
<L>I trowe, he speketh these wordes in waste, <MILESTONE N="7" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>He wole make bute an easy brayde.</L>
<L>Whan he bryngith home Charles the kinge <MILESTONE N="248"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">when he had taken Charles and the douzepeers.</NOTE></L>
<L>And the xij dosipers alle,</L>
<L>I g<HI REND="italic">ra</HI>unte to be his derlynge</L>
<L>What so evere therof by-falle.</L>
<L>Than on the morowe the Sowdan̄ <MILESTONE N="252"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">The next morning the soudan ordered Lukafer to assault the City with 30,000 men.</NOTE></L>
<L>Callid to him Lukafe<ABBR>r</ABBR> of Baldas,</L>
<L>To assaile the Cite anone:</L>
<L>"And loke thou tary not in this cas!</L>
<L>Thritty thousande of my menie, <MILESTONE N="256"/></L>
<L>Of Gallopes, Ethiopes and Aufricanes,</L>
<L>Take hem to the walles witħ the.</L>
<L>Betitħ down̄ wallis, towris and stones."</L>
<L>Lukafe<ABBR>r</ABBR> blewe his clarion̄ <MILESTONE N="260"/></L>
<L>To Assemble the Sarasyns þat tide,</L>
<L>Where-of thai knewe right welle the soune,</L>
<L>Thai made hem redy for to ride,</L>
<L>But whan thai come to the yate, <MILESTONE N="264"/></L>
<L>The Dikes were so develye depe, <NOTE PLACE="marg">The Saracens, finding the ditches too deep, cannot pass, and are</NOTE></L>
<L>Thai helde hem selfe Chek-mate;</L>
<L>Ouer cowde thai nothir goo nor crepe.</L>
<L>Lukafe<ABBR>r</ABBR> in al the haste <MILESTONE N="268"/></L>
<L>Turned to the Sowdan agayn̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">obliged to return.</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "sir, it is alle in waste,</L>
<L>We laboure nowe alle in vayne.</L>
<L>To depe and brode the Dikes bene, <MILESTONE N="272"/></L>
<L>The Towres so stronge be witħ alle,</L>
<L><PB N="9" REF="80"/>
That by Mahounde I can note seen̄,</L>
<L>How that we shulde wyne ther to the walle."</L>
<L>Who was woode but the Sowdon̄? <MILESTONE N="276"/></L>
<L>He reneyed his goddis alle.</L>
<L>He clepede his Engyno<HI REND="italic">ur</HI> sir mavone, <NOTE PLACE="marg">The soudan calls for his engineer Mavon,</NOTE></L>
<L>To counsaile he did him faste calle.</L>
<L>He tolde him the case of þat myschefe, <MILESTONE N="280"/></L>
<L>How it stode at that ilke tyde.</L>
<L>Mavon Gafe him counsel in breefe <NOTE PLACE="marg">who advised him to fill the ditch</NOTE></L>
<L>To fille the Dikes þat were depe. <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read</HI> 'wide'</NOTE></L>
<L>Every man to woode shal goon̄, <MILESTONE N="284"/></L>
<L>Fagotis to hewe and faste bynde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">with fagots.</NOTE></L>
<L>And fille the Dikes faste anoon̄</L>
<L>With alle, that we may ther fynde.</L>
<L>"Gramercy, Mavon̄," q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Laban than̄, <MILESTONE N="288"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Laban thanks his wise engineer.</NOTE></L>
<L>"Mahoundis benysone thou shalt haue,</L>
<L>Of alle myn Ooste the wiseste man, <MILESTONE N="8" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>With counsaile men for to saue.</L>
<L>Alle this was done the seconde daye, <MILESTONE N="292"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">The following day, the ditch being filled with fagots, the city</NOTE></L>
<L>Men myght go even to the walle;</L>
<L>On every party the ooste laye,</L>
<L>Thai made assaite <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">sic.?</HI> assaute.</NOTE> then generalle. <NOTE PLACE="marg">was assaulted from all quarters. The Romans ran to the towers, and</NOTE></L>
<L>The Romaynes ronnen̄ to the toures, <MILESTONE N="296"/></L>
<L>Thai were in ful grete dowte;</L>
<L>Thai hade many sharpe shoures, <NOTE PLACE="marg">a sharp conflict ensued.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thai were assailed sore a-bowte.</L>
<L>Wifis and maidyns stones thai bare <MILESTONE N="300"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Women and maidens carried stones which the</NOTE></L>
<L>To the walles than ful faste,</L>
<L>Thai were in grete drede and care;</L>
<L>The men over the wallis did caste. <NOTE PLACE="marg">men threw over the walls.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thai slowen many a Sarasyn̄, <MILESTONE N="304"/></L>
<L>x <HI REND="italic">thousande</HI> <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">MS.</HI> M<SUP>l</SUP></NOTE> pepul of hem̄ and moo. <NOTE PLACE="marg">10,000 Saracens were slain and</NOTE></L>
<L>The daie passed to the fyne,</L>
<L>The hethen withdrowe hem tho. <NOTE PLACE="marg">the heathens obliged to withdraw.</NOTE></L>
<L>Whan these tidinges came to laban, <MILESTONE N="308"/></L>
<L><PB N="10" REF="81"/>
His goddes he gan chide. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Laban chides his gods and nearly grows mad with vexation.</NOTE></L>
<L>He waxe both blake, pale and wan,</L>
<L>He was nyȝe woode þat same tyde.</L>
<L>Tho Lukafer comfortede him welle <MILESTONE N="312"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">But Lukafer told him that, having espied that</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "sir, be not dismayed,</L>
<L>For I have aspied everydele,</L>
<L>Howe thai shalle alle be betrayede.</L>
<L>Sauariz wole to morowe witħ us fighte, <MILESTONE N="316"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Savaris would, the following day, come out again to fight with them, he would have a banner made exactly like his, which when Savaris was much engaged in the battle, he would unfold and enter Rome.</NOTE></L>
<L>His baner knowe I ful welle;</L>
<L>I shal have an othere, I yoū plighte,</L>
<L>Like to this every dele.</L>
<L>Whan he is moste besy in bataile, <MILESTONE N="320"/></L>
<L>Than wole I with banere displaiede</L>
<L>Ride in to Rome w<HI REND="italic">i</HI>t<HI REND="italic">h</HI>out faile,</L>
<L>Thus shal thai al be betrayede.</L>
<L>The Sowdan̄ was glad of this tidinge, <MILESTONE N="324"/></L>
<L>Hopinge it shulde be so;</L>
<L>And even as it was in purposynge, <NOTE PLACE="marg">And so it turned out;</NOTE></L>
<L>Right so was it aftir I-do.</L>
<L>Wenynge it hade be Sauarye, <MILESTONE N="328"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">the Romans mis∣taking him for Savaris, returning from his sally,</NOTE></L>
<L>Relevinge fro the hethen stou<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>Wenynge doth ofte harme w<HI REND="italic">i</HI>t<HI REND="italic">h</HI>oute lye,</L>
<L>He entred to the maist<HI REND="italic">er</HI> Toure. <NOTE PLACE="marg">he entered the main tower,</NOTE></L>
<L>The firste warde thus thay wo<HI REND="italic">n</HI>ne <MILESTONE N="332"/> <MILESTONE N="9" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>By this fals contrevede engyne.</L>
<L>Thus was moche sorowe bygon̄,</L>
<L>Thai slougħ all, that were ther-Inne. <NOTE PLACE="marg">and slew all therein.</NOTE></L>
<L>Whan̄ Sauariz saugħ this discomfitu<ABBR>r</ABBR> <MILESTONE N="336"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Savaris becoming aware of the arti∣fice of the enemy,</NOTE></L>
<L>Of the Romaynes in that tyme,</L>
<L>And howe harde than̄ was here aventu<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>Of sorowe þat myghte he ryme</L>
<L>Of x thousande men̄ lefte no moo <MILESTONE N="340"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">and seeing out of 10,000 Romans no more than seventy-two left,</NOTE></L>
<L>But sexty men̄ and twelfe,</L>
<L>And whan he sawe this myschief tho,</L>
<L>He turned homewarde agayn him selue. <NOTE PLACE="marg">turned back, but found the gate shut,</NOTE></L>
<L>By than̄ he founde the gate shite <MILESTONE N="344"/></L>
<L><PB N="11" REF="82"/>
With Sarisyns, that hade it wone;</L>
<L>And Estragot with him he mette</L>
<L>With bores hede, blake and donne.</L>
<L>For as a bore an hede hadde <MILESTONE N="348"/></L>
<L>And a grete mace stronge as stele.</L>
<L>He smote Sauaryz as he were madde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and was slain by Estragot, a black giant of Ethiopia.</NOTE></L>
<L>That dede to grounde he felle.</L>
<L>This Astrogot of Ethiop, <MILESTONE N="352"/></L>
<L>He was a kinge of grete strengtħ;</L>
<L>Ther was none suche in Europe</L>
<L>So stronge and so longe in lengtħ.</L>
<L>I trowe, he were a develes sone, <MILESTONE N="356"/></L>
<L>Of Belsabubbis lyne,</L>
<L>For ever he was thereto I-wone,</L>
<L>To do Cristen̄ men grete pyne.</L>
<L>Whan tidinggis came to the [P]ope, <MILESTONE N="360"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">After the death of Savaris, the Pope</NOTE></L>
<L>That Duke Sauaryz was dede slayn̄,</L>
<L>Than̄ to woo turned alle his hope;</L>
<L>He dide calle than̄ to counsaile <NOTE PLACE="marg">summoned his council again.</NOTE></L>
<L>Alle the Senatouris of Rome, <MILESTONE N="364"/></L>
<L>What þinge þat myght hem most availe,</L>
<L>And what were beste to done.</L>
<L>Tho by-spake a worthy man of counsaile,</L>
<L>An Erille of the Senatouris: <MILESTONE N="368"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">An earl of the senatours sug∣gested the neces∣sity of dispatch∣ing messengers to Charlemagne, im∣ploring him to</NOTE></L>
<L>"The best counsaile, þat I can</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Sending vnto Charles the kinge <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">This line in a much later hand.</NOTE></L>
<L>Certifiynge him by your myssangeris</L>
<L>The myschief þat ye are Inne, <MILESTONE N="372"/></L>
<L>That he come with his Dosyperys <NOTE PLACE="marg">come to their deliverance.</NOTE></L>
<L>To reskue Cristiante fro this heþen." <MILESTONE N="10" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>All thai assentede anone therto; <NOTE PLACE="marg">hey all assented.</NOTE></L>
<L>The le<HI REND="italic">tt</HI>res were made in haste. <MILESTONE N="376"/></L>
<L>Thre messageres we ordeyn̄ <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> were ordeyned</NOTE> therto, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Three messen∣gers, with letters written in haste,</NOTE></L>
<L>That went forthe at the laste.</L>
<L><PB N="12" REF="83"/>
At a posterne thai wente oute <NOTE PLACE="marg">left the city by a postern at mid∣night, and passed the enemy's camp without being noticed by any wight.</NOTE></L>
<L>Pryvely aboute mydnygħt, <MILESTONE N="380"/></L>
<L>And passed through alle the route.</L>
<L>Of hem was war no wigħt.</L>
<L>BVt let we nowe the messangeris goon̄,</L>
<L>And speke we of Laban̄, <MILESTONE N="384"/></L>
<L>Howe he dide saile the Cite anoon̄,</L>
<L>And co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>maundid, þat every man <NOTE PLACE="marg">Laban com∣manded every man to throw pikes and bills over the walls, to kill the Romans.</NOTE></L>
<L>Shulde withe Pikeys or witħ bille</L>
<L>The Wallis over throwe, <MILESTONE N="388"/></L>
<L>That he myght the Romaynes kille,</L>
<L>Playnly on a rowe,</L>
<L>By water he ordeynede the shippes goon̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">He ordered the ships to go up the water, with their boats bound to the mast, that they might fight in close combat.</NOTE></L>
<L>The bootis bownden to the maste, <MILESTONE N="392"/></L>
<L>That thai myght fight with hem anoon̄,</L>
<L>Honde of honde, þat was here caste.</L>
<L>To the Toure a bastile stode, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Near the tower there stood a bastile which formed a principal protection to the city.</NOTE></L>
<L>An engyne was I-throwe— <MILESTONE N="396"/></L>
<L>That was to the Cite ful goode—</L>
<L>And brake down̄ towres both hie and lowe. <NOTE PLACE="marg">It was laid low by stones hurled from an engine.</NOTE></L>
<L>Tho sorowede alle the Citesyns</L>
<L>And were ful hevy than̄. <MILESTONE N="400"/></L>
<L>Tho wox prowde the Sarasyns, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Laban, growing proud, summoned the Romans to surrender.</NOTE></L>
<L>And than bispake sire laban</L>
<L>And saide "yolde youe here to me,</L>
<L>Ye may not longe endure, <MILESTONE N="404"/></L>
<L>Or ellis shall ye al slayn̄ be,</L>
<L>By mahounde I you ensure."</L>
<L>A Romayne drife a darte him to <NOTE PLACE="marg">Instead of an answer, a Roman hurled a dart at his breast-plate, but his hauberk shielded him.</NOTE></L>
<L>And smote him on the breste plate, <MILESTONE N="408"/></L>
<L>Ne hadde his hawberke lasted tho,</L>
<L>Mahounde had come to late.</L>
<L>Tho was the Sowdon̄ more þan̄ wod, <NOTE PLACE="marg">The soudan, more than mad, charged Ferum∣bras to destroy them all,</NOTE></L>
<L>He cried to Ferumbras, <MILESTONE N="412"/></L>
<L>"For Mahoundes loue, þat is so good,</L>
<L>Destroye vp bothe man and place.</L>
<L><PB N="13" REF="84"/>
Spare no thinge that is alyve,</L>
<L>Hows, Toure ner Walle, <MILESTONE N="416"/> <MILESTONE N="11" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Beest, ner man, Childe nere Wife,</L>
<L>Brenne, slo and distroye alle."</L>
<L>Tho Ferumbras ordeynede anone</L>
<L>To bende the Engynes to the town̄ <MILESTONE N="420"/></L>
<L>And bete down̄ botħ Toure and stoon̄.</L>
<L>He cleped fortħ Fortibraunce and Mavon̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">and enjoined Fortibrance and Mavon to direct their engines against the walls.</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "be youre Engynes goode?</L>
<L>Shewe forth here nowe your crafte <MILESTONE N="424"/></L>
<L>For Mahoundis love, þat gevith man foode,</L>
<L>That ther be no Toure lafte."</L>
<L>Tho the grete gloton̄ Estagote <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Estragote</NOTE> <NOTE PLACE="marg">The great glutton Estragot, with his heavy mace,</NOTE></L>
<L>With his myghty mace sware <MILESTONE N="428"/></L>
<L>On the Gatis of Rome he smote <NOTE PLACE="marg">smote on the gates and brake them in pieces.</NOTE></L>
<L>And brake hem alle on thre thare.</L>
<L>In he entrid at the Gate <NOTE PLACE="marg">But as he was entering one of the gates, they let the portcullis fall, which crushed him to the ground,</NOTE></L>
<L>The Porte-Colis on him thai lete falle. <MILESTONE N="432"/></L>
<L>He wende, he hade come to late,</L>
<L>It smote him through herte, lyuer and galle.</L>
<L>He lai cryande at the grounde <NOTE PLACE="marg">where he lay crying like a devil.</NOTE></L>
<L>Like a develle of Helle; <MILESTONE N="436"/></L>
<L>Through the Cite wente the sowne,</L>
<L>So lowde than gan he yelle.</L>
<L>Gladde were al the Romaynes, <NOTE PLACE="marg">The Romans were glad, but the Saracens grieved.</NOTE></L>
<L>That he was take in the trappe, <MILESTONE N="440"/></L>
<L>And sorye were al the Sarsyns</L>
<L>Of þat myschevos happe.</L>
<L>Sory was the Soudon̄ than̄</L>
<L>And Ferumbras and Lukafe<ABBR>r</ABBR>. <MILESTONE N="444"/></L>
<L>Thai drowe hem tille her tent<HI REND="italic">es</HI> than̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">They withdrew to their tents, leav∣ing behind the corpse of Estra∣got, whose soul went up to Mahound.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thai left him ligginge there.</L>
<L>Mahounde toke his soule to him</L>
<L>And broght it to his blis. <MILESTONE N="448"/></L>
<L>He loued him wel and al his kyn,</L>
<L><PB N="14" REF="85"/>
Of þat myghte he not mys.</L>
<L>Anone the [P]ope dide somon̄ alle; <NOTE PLACE="marg">The Pope called all his people to St. Peter's,</NOTE></L>
<L>The peple of the Cite came, <MILESTONE N="452"/></L>
<L>To Seinte Petris he dide hem calle,</L>
<L>And thidere came every man.</L>
<L>He saide on hie "my Children dere, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and proposed to them</NOTE></L>
<L>Ye wote wel, howe it is; <MILESTONE N="456"/></L>
<L>Ayenst the Sarisyns, þat nowe be here,</L>
<L>We mowe not longe endure I-wis.</L>
<L>Thay brekene oure walles, oure Toures alle <MILESTONE N="12" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>With caste of his Engyne. <MILESTONE N="460"/></L>
<L>Therefore here amonge yoū alle</L>
<L>Ye shalle here counsaile myne.</L>
<L>Thai bene withdrawe to here Oost, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> reste</NOTE></L>
<L>And on-armede thay ben alle. <MILESTONE N="464"/></L>
<L>Therfore, me thenketh, is beste <NOTE PLACE="marg">to attempt a sally with 20,000 men, to attack the enemy before day∣break within their camp,</NOTE></L>
<L>To-morowe erly on hem to falle.</L>
<L>We have xxx<SUP>ti</SUP> thousande men;</L>
<L>Twenty thousande shal go witħ me, <MILESTONE N="468"/></L>
<L>And in this Cite leve ten <NOTE PLACE="marg">and to leave 10,000 for the guard of the city.</NOTE></L>
<L>To governe the comynalte."</L>
<L>The Senatouris assentede sone <NOTE PLACE="marg">The senators assented.</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide, bet<HI REND="italic">er</HI> myghte no man seyne. <MILESTONE N="472"/></L>
<L>On the morowe this was it done <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> <NOTE PLACE="marg">In the morning</NOTE></L>
<L>God bringe hem wele home agayne.</L>
<L>The Pope did display than <NOTE PLACE="marg">the Pope dis∣played the banner of Rome,</NOTE></L>
<L>The hie baner of Rome, <MILESTONE N="476"/></L>
<L>And he assoiled every man̄</L>
<L>Througħ gracious god in Dome.</L>
<L>He praide of helpe and socou<ABBR>r</ABBR> <NOTE PLACE="marg">and after a prayer for the preserva∣tion of the city,</NOTE></L>
<L>Seinte Petir and Poule also <MILESTONE N="480"/></L>
<L>And oure lady, þat swete floure,</L>
<L>To saue the Cite of Rome from woo.</L>
<L>Forth thai riden̄ towarde the Oost. <NOTE PLACE="marg">they marched out.</NOTE></L>
<L>Ferumbras romede a-boute; <MILESTONE N="484"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">But Ferumbras. going his rounds,</NOTE></L>
<L><PB N="15" REF="86"/>
He saw the Romaynes comen̄ by the Cost, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">MS.</HI> Oost <HI REND="italic">corrected to</HI> Cost.</NOTE> <NOTE PLACE="marg">discovered their coming,</NOTE></L>
<L>Thereof he hade grete dowte.</L>
<L>He blewe an horne, of bras it was; <NOTE PLACE="marg">sounded the alarm,</NOTE></L>
<L>The Sarsyns be-gon̄ to wake. <MILESTONE N="488"/></L>
<L>"Arise vp" he saide in aras, <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> a ras.</NOTE></L>
<L>"We bene elles alle I-take,</L>
<L>And Armes anone, every wight,</L>
<L>To horse with spere and shelde! <MILESTONE N="492"/></L>
<L>Ye may se here a ferefułł sighte</L>
<L>Of oure enemyes in the felde.</L>
<L>Astopars, <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> goo ye biforne vs, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and drew up his troops.</NOTE></L>
<L>For ye be men of myghte; <MILESTONE N="496"/></L>
<L>Ethiopes, Assayneȝ and Askalous,</L>
<L>Go nexte afore my sighte.</L>
<L>My Fadir and I with Babyloynes,</L>
<L>Ho <NOTE N="4" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> We</NOTE> shal kepe the rerewarde. <MILESTONE N="500"/></L>
<L>King Lukafe<ABBR>r</ABBR> with Baldeseynes,</L>
<L>To venge alle, shalle have the Fowarde." <MILESTONE N="13" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>The Romaynes aspied, þat thai were ware</L>
<L>Of here comynge than̄, <MILESTONE N="504"/></L>
<L>And therfore hade thay moche care.</L>
<L>Natheles on he<HI REND="italic">m</HI> thai gon̄—</L>
<L>Seinte Petir be here socoure!—</L>
<L>And laiden on side, bake and bon̄. <MILESTONE N="508"/></L>
<L>There bigan a sturdy shoure <NOTE PLACE="marg">There began a hard struggle.</NOTE></L>
<L>Sire <NOTE N="5" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">MS.</HI> Berumbras.</NOTE> Ferumbras of Alisaundre oon̄, <NOTE N="6" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE></L>
<L>That bolde man was in dede,</L>
<L>Vppon a steede Cassaundre gaye, <MILESTONE N="512"/></L>
<L>He roode in riche Weede.</L>
<L>Sire Bryer of Poyle a Romayne to fraye <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras slew Sir Bryer of Apulia</NOTE></L>
<L>He bare through witħ a spere,</L>
<L>Dede to the grounde ther he lan̄ <MILESTONE N="516"/></L>
<L>Might he no more hem dere!</L>
<L><PB N="16" REF="87"/>
That sawe Huberte, a worthy man,</L>
<L>Howe Briere was I-slayn̄,</L>
<L>Ferumbras to qwite than̄ <MILESTONE N="520"/></L>
<L>To him he rode ful even̄.</L>
<L>With a spere vppone his shelde þan̄</L>
<L>Stifly ganne he strike;</L>
<L>The shelde he brake I-myddis the feelde; <MILESTONE N="524"/></L>
<L>His Hawberke wolde not breke.</L>
<L>Many goode strokes were delte.</L>
<L>Ferumbras was a-greved tho,</L>
<L>He smote with mayne and mygħte <MILESTONE N="528"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">and the worthy Hubert.</NOTE></L>
<L>The nekke asonder, the ventayle also,</L>
<L>That dede he sate vprighte.</L>
<L>There was bataile harde and stronge;</L>
<L>Many a steede wente ther a-straye, <MILESTONE N="532"/></L>
<L>And leyen at the grounde I-stonge,</L>
<L>That resyn never aftyr that day,</L>
<L>IX thousand of the payens pride <NOTE PLACE="marg">9000 pagans were killed,</NOTE></L>
<L>That day were slayn̄, <MILESTONE N="536"/></L>
<L>And viij thousande of the Romaynes side, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and 8000 Romans.</NOTE></L>
<L>That in the feelde dede lay<HI REND="italic">n</HI>e.</L>
<L>Lukafere, þat paynym proude, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Lukafer destroyed eighteen Romans,</NOTE></L>
<L>Slough Romaynes eyȝtene, <MILESTONE N="540"/></L>
<L>Of wer<ABBR>r</ABBR> moche sorowe he coude,</L>
<L>His strokes were over alle sene.</L>
<L>Gyndarde, a Senatoure of Rome, <NOTE PLACE="marg">he also slew Gyndard, a senator of Rome,</NOTE></L>
<L>Had slayne Sarsenys ten̄, <MILESTONE N="544"/> <MILESTONE N="14" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Tille he met with the cursed gome, <NOTE PLACE="marg">who had slain ten Saracens.</NOTE></L>
<L>Lukifere slough him than.</L>
<L>Tho come the Pope with grete aray, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Then came the Pope with a great guard and his banner before him.</NOTE></L>
<L>His baner to-fore him wente. <MILESTONE N="548"/></L>
<L>Ferumbras than gan̄ to assaye,</L>
<L>If he myght that praye entente,</L>
<L>Supposynge in this though[t]e, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras, sup∣posing him to be the sovereign,</NOTE></L>
<L>Ther was the souerayne; <MILESTONE N="552"/></L>
<L>He spared him therfore rigħt nogħt,</L>
<L><PB N="17" REF="88"/>
But bare him down̄ ther in þ<SUP>e</SUP> playn̄. <NOTE PLACE="marg">burst open the thick crowd and threw him down to the ground.</NOTE></L>
<L>Anoon̄ he sterte on him all ane</L>
<L>His Ventayle for to onlace, <MILESTONE N="556"/></L>
<L>And saugh his crown̄ newe shafe, <NOTE PLACE="marg">But seeing his tonsure, he was ashamed.</NOTE></L>
<L>A-shamed thanne he was.</L>
<L>"Fye, preest, god gyfe the sorowe! <NOTE PLACE="marg">"Fie, priest," he said, "what doest thou in the battle-field?</NOTE></L>
<L>What doist thou armede in the feelde, <MILESTONE N="560"/></L>
<L>That sholdest saie thi matyns on morwe,</L>
<L>What doist thoū witħ spere and shelde?</L>
<L>I hoped, thoū hadiste ben̄ an Emp<HI REND="italic">er</HI>oure,</L>
<L>Or a Cheftayne of this Ooste here, <MILESTONE N="564"/></L>
<L>Or some worthy conqueroure.</L>
<L>Go home and kepe thy Qwe<ABBR>r</ABBR>!</L>
<L>Shame it were to me certayne <NOTE PLACE="marg">It would be a shame for me to slay thee.</NOTE></L>
<L>To sle the in this bataile, <MILESTONE N="568"/></L>
<L>Therfore turne the home agayn̄!" <NOTE PLACE="marg">Go home and think of thy choir∣service!"</NOTE></L>
<L>The Pope was gladde þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI>-of certayne, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'without faile.'</NOTE></L>
<L>He wente home to Rome that nyght <NOTE PLACE="marg">The Pope retired with 5000 men,</NOTE></L>
<L>Witħ Five thousande and no more, <MILESTONE N="572"/></L>
<L>XV thousande lefte in the feelde aplight, <NOTE PLACE="marg">15,000 being killed.</NOTE></L>
<L>Full grete sorowe was therfore.</L>
<L>NOwe telle we of the messange<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>That wente to Charlemayne, <MILESTONE N="576"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charlemagne, having learned from the mes∣senger the great disaster which had befallen the Romans,</NOTE></L>
<L>Certyfyinge him by lettres dere,</L>
<L>Howe the Romaynes were slayne,</L>
<L>And howe the Contrey brente was</L>
<L>Vnto the Gate of Rome, <MILESTONE N="580"/></L>
<L>And howe the people song 'alas,'</L>
<L>Tille socoure from him come.</L>
<L>"Who" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Charles, that worthy kinge,</L>
<L>"The Sowdon̄ and Ferumbras? <MILESTONE N="584"/></L>
<L>I nyl lette for no thinge, <MILESTONE N="15" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Till I him oute of Cristendome chace. <NOTE PLACE="marg">said, he would not desist until he had chased the soudan and Ferumbras out of Christendom.</NOTE></L>
<L>Therefore Gy of Burgoyn̄,</L>
<L>Mynne owen nevewe so trewe, <MILESTONE N="588"/></L>
<L><PB N="18" REF="89"/>
Take a thausande pounde of Frankis fyne, <NOTE PLACE="marg">He gave 1000 pounds of francs to his nephew Guy of Burgundy,</NOTE></L>
<L>To wage wytħ the pepul newe.</L>
<L>Take this with the nowe at this tyme,</L>
<L>And more I wole sende the, <MILESTONE N="592"/></L>
<L>Loke that thou spare no hors ne shelde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and sent him off with orders to advance against the soudan by forced marches.</NOTE></L>
<L>But þat he dede be;</L>
<L>And faste hye the thyderwarde,</L>
<L>For I drede thay haue grete nede, <MILESTONE N="596"/></L>
<L>And I shalle come aftirwarde <NOTE PLACE="marg">Himself would follow as soon as possible.</NOTE></L>
<L>As faste, as I may me spede."</L>
<L>SPeke we of Sir Laban̄</L>
<L>And let Charles and Gy be, <MILESTONE N="600"/></L>
<L>Howe he ordeyned for hem than̄</L>
<L>To Distroye Rome Citee.</L>
<L>"Sir Lukafe<ABBR>r</ABBR>, thou madiste thi boost <NOTE PLACE="marg">Laban reminded Lukafer of his vaunting promise to bring him Charlemagne and his douzepeers,</NOTE></L>
<L>To conque<ABBR>r</ABBR> the Romaynes <MILESTONE N="604"/></L>
<L>And to bringe me the Ooste</L>
<L>Of the xij peris and Charlemayne.</L>
<L>Vppon̄ a condicion̄ I graunte the <NOTE PLACE="marg">in return for his daughter Floripas.</NOTE></L>
<L>My doghter, dere Dame Floripas. <MILESTONE N="608"/></L>
<L>Wherefore, I aske nowe of the</L>
<L>To holde coven<HI REND="italic">au</HI>nte in this cas."</L>
<L>"That I saide" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Lucafere, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Lukafer said, he would do all he had promised.</NOTE></L>
<L>"To Mahounde I make a vowe <MILESTONE N="612"/></L>
<L>To done al þat I hight the the<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>Ye and more th<HI REND="italic">a</HI>n <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> for Florip love."</L>
<L>He ordeyned assaute anone in haste <NOTE PLACE="marg">With 10,000 men he attacked the city on one side,</NOTE></L>
<L>With x thousande men and moo; <MILESTONE N="616"/></L>
<L>And Ferumbras at that oþ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> side faste <NOTE PLACE="marg">the other being assaulted by Ferumbras.</NOTE></L>
<L>Assailed hem with grete woo.</L>
<L>The saute endured al þ<HI REND="italic">a</HI>t daye <NOTE PLACE="marg">The combat con∣tinues as long as daylight lasts.</NOTE></L>
<L>From morowe, tille it was nyght, <MILESTONE N="620"/></L>
<L>To throwe and shete by eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>y waye,</L>
<L>While that hem endured the light.</L>
<L>Tho wente thai home to thai<ABBR>r</ABBR> tentys, <NOTE PLACE="marg">At night they retired to their tents.</NOTE></L>
<L><PB N="19" REF="90"/>
Tille it were on the morowe. <MILESTONE N="624"/></L>
<L>Isres in his fals ententes <NOTE PLACE="marg">Isres, who pos∣sessed by inherit∣ance the guard of the principal gate,</NOTE></L>
<L>Purposed treson̄ and sorowe.</L>
<L>He was chief Porter of the Town̄, <MILESTONE N="16" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>By heritage and fee so he shulde be. <MILESTONE N="628"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">planned treason.</NOTE></L>
<L>He wente to the Sowdan̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">He repaired to the soudan and offered to betray the city on condi∣tion that his life and property should be spared.</NOTE></L>
<L>For the riche Cite betraye woolde he,</L>
<L>And saide "lorde, gife me grace</L>
<L>For my goodes and for me, <MILESTONE N="632"/></L>
<L>And I wole del<HI REND="italic">yu</HI>er the this place</L>
<L>To haue and holde for ever in fee.</L>
<L>The keyes of this riche Cite</L>
<L>I haue in my bandon." <MILESTONE N="636"/></L>
<L>"That gr<HI REND="italic">a</HI>unte I" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Laban "the <NOTE PLACE="marg">The soudan pro∣mised it.</NOTE></L>
<L>To be free withoute raunson̄."</L>
<L>Ferumbras made him yare, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras with 20,000 men went with Isres.</NOTE></L>
<L>With xx<SUP>ti</SUP> thousand men̄ and moo, <MILESTONE N="640"/></L>
<L>With this Isres for to fare,</L>
<L>And to wynne the Cite soo.</L>
<L>As sone as he entred was <NOTE PLACE="marg">On entering the gate,</NOTE></L>
<L>The chief Gate of alle, <MILESTONE N="644"/></L>
<L>And alle his men in aras, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'a ras.'</NOTE></L>
<L>He lete the Portcolys falle. <NOTE PLACE="marg">he caused the traitor's head to be struck off by the portcullis, and</NOTE></L>
<L>He smote of the traitourus hede</L>
<L>And saide "god gife him care! <MILESTONE N="648"/></L>
<L>Shal he never more ete brede,</L>
<L>All traito<HI REND="italic">ur</HI>s evel mot <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">MS.</HI> met.</NOTE> thai fare!</L>
<L>If he myght leve and reigne here,</L>
<L>He wolde betraye me; <MILESTONE N="652"/></L>
<L>For go he west, soutħ or Nortħ,</L>
<L>Traito<HI REND="italic">ur</HI> shalle he never be."</L>
<L>He dide lete bere his hede on a spere <NOTE PLACE="marg">to be carried on the point of a spear through the city.</NOTE></L>
<L>Througħ-oute this faire Citee. <MILESTONE N="656"/></L>
<L>'Treson, treson̄' thai cried there, <NOTE PLACE="marg">"Treason," cried the people within,</NOTE></L>
<L>Pite it was to here and see.</L>
<L><PB N="20" REF="91"/>
The people fled by every waye,</L>
<L>Thai durst no-where a-bide. <MILESTONE N="660"/></L>
<L>The hye wey ful of dede men laye, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and all streets were soon covered with dead men.</NOTE></L>
<L>And eke by every lanys side.</L>
<L>Ferumbras to Seinte Petris wente, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras went to St. Peter's, seized the relies, the cross, the crown and the nails,</NOTE></L>
<L>And alle the Relekes he seased anoon̄, <MILESTONE N="664"/></L>
<L>The Crosse, the Crown̄, the Nailes bente;</L>
<L>He toke hem with him everychone.</L>
<L>He dide dispoile al the Cite</L>
<L>Both of tresoure and of goolde, <MILESTONE N="668"/></L>
<L>And after that brente he <MILESTONE N="17" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Alle þat ever myght be toolde. <NOTE PLACE="marg">burned the whole city,</NOTE></L>
<L>And alle the tresoure witħ hem þai bare <NOTE PLACE="marg">and carried away all the treasures and the gold to Agremore,</NOTE></L>
<L>To the Cite of Egremou<ABBR>r</ABBR>. <MILESTONE N="672"/></L>
<L>Laban the Sowdon̄ soiourned there <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> <NOTE PLACE="marg">where the soudan went to stay.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thre monþes and thre dayes more <NOTE PLACE="marg">Three months and three days they spent there in great festivities, making offerings to their gods,</NOTE></L>
<L>In myrtħ and Ioye and grete solas.</L>
<L>And to his goddes offrynge he made, <MILESTONE N="676"/></L>
<L>He and his sone Sir Ferumbras</L>
<L>Here goddis of golde dide fade,</L>
<L>Thai brente Franken̄sense, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and burning frankincense in their honour.</NOTE></L>
<L>That smoked vp so stronge, <MILESTONE N="680"/></L>
<L>The Fume in her presence,</L>
<L>It lasted alle alonge.</L>
<L>Thai blewe hornes of bras,</L>
<L>Thai dronke beestes bloode. <MILESTONE N="684"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">They drank the blood of beasts and milk, and ate honey</NOTE></L>
<L>Milke and hony ther was,</L>
<L>That was roial and goode.</L>
<L>Serpentes in Oyle were fryed <NOTE PLACE="marg">and snakes fried in oil.</NOTE></L>
<L>To serve þ<SUP>e</SUP> Sowdon̄ with alle, <MILESTONE N="688"/></L>
<L>"Antrarian Antrarian" thai lowde cryed</L>
<L>That signyfied 'Ioye generalle.'</L>
<L>Thus thai lived in Ioye and blis</L>
<L>Two monþes or thre. <MILESTONE N="692"/></L>
<L>Lete we now be alle this,</L>
<L><PB N="21" REF="92"/>
And of Gye nowe speke we.</L>
<L>NOw speke we of Sir Gȳe</L>
<L>That toward Rome hied witħ his Oost. <MILESTONE N="696"/></L>
<L>Whan̄ he approched there-to so nyȝe, <NOTE PLACE="marg">When Sir Guy drew near Rome, finding the whole city in flames,</NOTE></L>
<L>That he myght se the cooste,</L>
<L>Alle on a flame þat Cite was,</L>
<L>That thre myle al abowte, <MILESTONE N="700"/></L>
<L>Ther durst no man̄, þat ther was,</L>
<L>Come nyȝe the Cite for grete dowte.</L>
<L>That was a sory Cite than,</L>
<L>Sir Gye was in grete care, <MILESTONE N="704"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">he grieved much</NOTE></L>
<L>Ther was nowhere a soryer man̄,</L>
<L>For sorowe he sighed ful sare,</L>
<L>And saide "welallas" <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">MS. is rubbed, but it looks more like</HI> welawai.</NOTE> the while</L>
<L>"For we come ar to late, <MILESTONE N="708"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">that he had arrived too late.</NOTE></L>
<L>For by some treson or some gyle</L>
<L>Thai entred in at some Gate.</L>
<L>There is no more but for to abyde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">He resolved there to wait for Charlemagne</NOTE></L>
<L>Tille Charles come, the kinge, <MILESTONE N="712"/></L>
<L>In this mede Vnder grene wode side, <MILESTONE N="18" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>To telle him of this tithinge, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and then to tell him, how Laban had burnt the city, and had sent the relies to Agremore,</NOTE></L>
<L>Howe Laban hath the Cite brente</L>
<L>And bore the Religes <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'reliqes.'</NOTE> a-waye, <MILESTONE N="716"/></L>
<L>And howe he hath hem to Spayne sente</L>
<L>With Shippes of grete aray,</L>
<L>To Egremou<ABBR>r</ABBR> his chief Cite, <NOTE PLACE="marg">his principal town in Spain.</NOTE></L>
<L>Ther to live and ende; <MILESTONE N="720"/></L>
<L>And manassitħ Charles and his baronye.</L>
<L>God gife hem evelle ende!"</L>
<L>Kinge Charles he forgate nought <NOTE PLACE="marg">King Charles advanced to rescue Rome with his douzepeers</NOTE></L>
<L>To come to reskowe Rome, <MILESTONE N="724"/></L>
<L>Alle his Doȝypers were I-sought,</L>
<L>Fulle sone to him thay come.</L>
<L>Thre hundred thousande of Sowdeoures <NOTE PLACE="marg">and 300,000 soldiers.</NOTE></L>
<L><PB N="22" REF="93"/>
Kinge Charles with him dide lede, <MILESTONE N="728"/></L>
<L>They were doughty in all stourys</L>
<L>And worthy men of dede.</L>
<L>Sir Roulande þat worthy knighte, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Roland led the vanguard,</NOTE></L>
<L>He ladde the Fowarde, <MILESTONE N="732"/></L>
<L>And Sir Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR>, that was so wighte, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Oliver the rear,</NOTE></L>
<L>Gouerned the Rerewarde.</L>
<L>The Kinge himselfe and his Baronye, <NOTE PLACE="marg">the king was</NOTE></L>
<L>With Dukes And Erilles roialle, <MILESTONE N="736"/></L>
<L>Gouerned alle the medil partye. <NOTE PLACE="marg">with the main body.</NOTE></L>
<L>By co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>maundemente generall</L>
<L>He ordeynede grete plente <NOTE PLACE="marg">The provisions</NOTE></L>
<L>Of Flessh and Fissh, brede and wyne, <MILESTONE N="740"/></L>
<L>In shippes to saile by the see, <NOTE PLACE="marg">were conveyed by sea.</NOTE></L>
<L>To serven him ful wel and fyne.</L>
<L>Sir Gye aspied his comynge, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Guy seeing them come, went to</NOTE></L>
<L>He knewe the baner of Fraunce, <MILESTONE N="744"/></L>
<L>He wente anoon̄ ayen the kinge <NOTE PLACE="marg">meet the king, and told him the mischief done by the soudan,</NOTE></L>
<L>And tolde him of þat myschaunce,</L>
<L>Howe that the cursed Sowdan̄</L>
<L>Hath brent Rome and bore the Relekis awaye, <MILESTONE N="748"/></L>
<L>And how he hath slayn̄ alle and some,</L>
<L>That he hatħ founde of Cristen̄ faye.</L>
<L>And more-over he made his a-vowe, <NOTE PLACE="marg">who moreover had made a vow to seek Charles in France in order to afflict him with grief.</NOTE></L>
<L>To seke kinge Charles in Fraunce <MILESTONE N="752"/></L>
<L>And do him wo ther I-nowe.</L>
<L>"God gif him moch myschaunce!"—</L>
<L>"A" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI><ABBR>d</ABBR> Charles "þat neditħ noght, <MILESTONE N="19" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>He shal fynde me nere. <MILESTONE N="756"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">"He will find me near," said Charles, "and</NOTE></L>
<L>By god, þat dere me bogħt,</L>
<L>He shal by it ful dere. <NOTE PLACE="marg">shall dearly pay for it.</NOTE></L>
<L>I shalle him never leve I-wis</L>
<L>Withinne walle ner witħoute, <MILESTONE N="760"/></L>
<L>I swere by god and seinte Denys,</L>
<L>Tille I have sought him oute; <NOTE PLACE="marg">Unless he consents to be baptized,</NOTE></L>
<L>And but if he will Baptised be</L>
<L><PB N="23" REF="94"/>
And lefe his fals laye, <MILESTONE N="764"/></L>
<L>Babyloyne shal he never see <NOTE PLACE="marg">he never shall see Babylon again."</NOTE></L>
<L>For alle his grete aray.</L>
<L>Anoon to shippe every man̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">They all took ship without delay.</NOTE></L>
<L>With vitaile and with store, <MILESTONE N="768"/></L>
<L>Euen towarde the proud Sawdan̄</L>
<L>With-outen̄ any more.</L>
<L>Wynde him blewe ful fayre and goode</L>
<L>Into the Ryver of Gaȝe, <MILESTONE N="772"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Propitious winds drove them into the river Gase, where they</NOTE></L>
<L>Even over the salte flode</L>
<L>And ouer the profounde rase.</L>
<L>XXX legeeȝ from Egremou<ABBR>r</ABBR> <NOTE PLACE="marg">landed, 30 miles from Agremore,</NOTE></L>
<L>By londe for south it is, <MILESTONE N="776"/></L>
<L>And ther withoute any more</L>
<L>To londe thai wente I-wis,</L>
<L>And brente and sloughen̄ al þ<HI REND="italic">a</HI>t thai fonde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and laid waste the country.</NOTE></L>
<L>And stroyed both Toure and town̄. <MILESTONE N="780"/></L>
<L>Thai lefte no thinge on grounde,</L>
<L>That thai ne bete it down̄.</L>
<L>Tithinggis were tolde to Laban, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Laban, hearing this news,</NOTE></L>
<L>Howe Charles was I-come <MILESTONE N="784"/></L>
<L>And slough bouth childe, wyfe, man</L>
<L>And brente and stroyed alle and some</L>
<L>With thre hundred thousand of Bacheleris,</L>
<L>That were both stoute and gaye, <MILESTONE N="788"/></L>
<L>And with him al his Dosyperis,</L>
<L>Pepul of grete araye.</L>
<L>"And but ye ordeyne remedy,</L>
<L>He wole you brenne and sloon̄, <MILESTONE N="792"/></L>
<L>Youe and youre riche Baronye,</L>
<L>He wole leve a-life neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>e oon̄."</L>
<L>Whan Laban herde these tidyngys,</L>
<L>His herte woxe alle coolde <MILESTONE N="796"/></L>
<L>And saide "this is a wonder thinge! <MILESTONE N="20" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Howe durste he be so boolde? <NOTE PLACE="marg">was astonished at Charles's presumption.</NOTE></L>
<L>Litill ke<HI REND="italic">n</HI>nyth he what I may doo,</L>
<L><PB N="24" REF="95"/>
He dredith me litil nowe. <MILESTONE N="800"/></L>
<L>But certes he shalle, e<ABBR>r</ABBR> he goo,</L>
<L>To Mahounde I make a vowe.</L>
<L>Sir Lucafe<ABBR>r</ABBR> and Ferumbras <NOTE PLACE="marg">He assembled all his barons,</NOTE></L>
<L>To him dide he calle <MILESTONE N="804"/></L>
<L>And Mavon̄ and Sortebras</L>
<L>And his Barons alle.</L>
<L>I charge you vppon̄ youre legeaunce, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and charged them to bring him alive that glutton that called himself king of France,</NOTE></L>
<L>That ye bringe me that gloton, <MILESTONE N="808"/></L>
<L>That clepeth himselfe kinge of Fraunce,</L>
<L>Hidere to my Pavilon̄.</L>
<L>Kepe him a-live, the remenaunte sle <NOTE PLACE="marg">and to slay the remnant.</NOTE></L>
<L>The xij Peris ychoon̄! <MILESTONE N="812"/></L>
<L>I shalle tech him curtesye,</L>
<L>I swere by god Mahounde."</L>
<L>Ferumbras anoon̄ than <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras went forth with many Saracens.</NOTE></L>
<L>Arrayed him for to ride <MILESTONE N="816"/></L>
<L>With proude Sarasyns many a man,</L>
<L>That boldely durst a-bide.</L>
<L>Rowlande met with Ferumbras <NOTE PLACE="marg">He meets with Roland.</NOTE></L>
<L>And gafe him such a stroke <MILESTONE N="820"/></L>
<L>That al astonyed þerof he was,</L>
<L>It made him lowe to stoupe.</L>
<L>Ferombras smote him agayne <NOTE PLACE="marg">They deal each other heavy strokes.</NOTE></L>
<L>With myghte and may<HI REND="italic">n,</HI> with ire <MILESTONE N="824"/></L>
<L>That he stenyed alle his brayne,</L>
<L>Him thought, his eyen̄ were alle on fyre.</L>
<L>With Lucafe<ABBR>r</ABBR> Olive<ABBR>r</ABBR> mette, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Oliver cuts off a quarter of Lukafer's shield.</NOTE></L>
<L>And hit him on the sheelde <MILESTONE N="828"/></L>
<L>A stroke, that was right wel sette;</L>
<L>A quarter flye in the feelde.</L>
<L>Thus thai hurteled to-gedere <NOTE PLACE="marg">The combat lasted the whole day.</NOTE></L>
<L>Alle the lefe longe daye, <MILESTONE N="832"/></L>
<L>Nowe hider and nowe theder;</L>
<L>Mony an hors wente ther astraye.</L>
<L>The Dosyperis thay foughten wele, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Well fought the twelve peers.</NOTE></L>
<L><PB N="25" REF="96"/>
Duke Neymys and Oge<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <MILESTONE N="836"/></L>
<L>With goode swerdes of fyne stele</L>
<L>And so dide Gye and Syr Brye<ABBR>r</ABBR>.</L>
<L>Ferumbras was euer a-bowte <MILESTONE N="21" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>To fyghte witħ Olyvere, <MILESTONE N="840"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras charges Oliver.</NOTE></L>
<L>And Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR> with-oute dowte</L>
<L>Leyde on with goode chere.</L>
<L>Kinge Charles saugh Ferumbras, <NOTE PLACE="marg">King Charles, seeing this, rides on to Ferumbras,</NOTE></L>
<L>To him fast he rode <MILESTONE N="844"/></L>
<L>And it on the helme witħ his mace, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and strikes his helm with his heavy mace.</NOTE></L>
<L>That stroke sadlye abode.</L>
<L>Ferumbras was woode for woo, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras cannot approach him on account of the crowd.</NOTE></L>
<L>He myght for prees come him to <MILESTONE N="848"/></L>
<L>For no worldis thinge, that myght be tho.</L>
<L>Kinge Charles anoon <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">A modern hand has written in the margin</HI> "Mount."</NOTE> Ioye oute-drowe, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charlemagne with his sword Mounjoy slew 30 Saracens.</NOTE></L>
<L>And with his owen honde</L>
<L>XXX<SUP>ti</SUP> Sarseynys ther he slowe, <MILESTONE N="852"/></L>
<L>That laie dede vppone the sonde;</L>
<L>Many of hem therfore made joy Inowe.</L>
<L>Sir Lucafere of Baldas, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Lukafer of Baldas, encountering Charles,</NOTE></L>
<L>He presed to Charles sone, <MILESTONE N="856"/></L>
<L>And saide "Sir, with harde grace,</L>
<L>What hastowe here to done?</L>
<L>I behight Laban to bringe the to him <NOTE PLACE="marg">told him that he had promised the soudan to bring him Charles and the douzepeers.</NOTE></L>
<L>And the xij peris alle; <MILESTONE N="860"/></L>
<L>Now shaltowe come from al thy kyn</L>
<L>Into the Sowdans halle.</L>
<L>Yelde the to me" he saide,</L>
<L>"Thy life shalle I safe." <MILESTONE N="864"/></L>
<L>A stroke on him than Charles layde; <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles strikes him on his helmet,</NOTE></L>
<L>He made the Paynym to rafe.</L>
<L>He smote him on the helme</L>
<L>With mown-Ioye, his gode bronde. <MILESTONE N="868"/></L>
<L>Ne hadde he be reskued than,</L>
<L>He hade slayn him with his honde.</L>
<L><PB N="26" REF="97"/>
Than came Baldeȝynȝ with thronge <NOTE PLACE="marg">but Lukafer is rescued by a great throng.</NOTE></L>
<L>To reskue there here lorde, <MILESTONE N="872"/></L>
<L>And nubens with hem amonge</L>
<L>And Turkes by one accorde.</L>
<L>Tho Roulande Durnedale oute-drowe <NOTE PLACE="marg">Roland, drawing Durendale, cleared a space around him and</NOTE></L>
<L>And made Ro<HI REND="italic">m</HI>me <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> abowte. <MILESTONE N="876"/></L>
<L>XL of hem ther he slowe,</L>
<L>Tho were thai in grete dowte.</L>
<L>Roulande as fiers as a lion̄</L>
<L>With Durnedale <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Insert:</HI> 'gan.'</NOTE> tho dinge <MILESTONE N="880"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">hammered the heads of the Saracens.</NOTE></L>
<L>Vppon the Sarsyns crowne,</L>
<L>As harde as he myght flynge. <MILESTONE N="22" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Duke Neymys and Sir Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">So do the other peers,</NOTE></L>
<L>Gy and Alloreynes of Loreyne, <MILESTONE N="884"/></L>
<L>And alle the noble xij Peris,</L>
<L>Oge<ABBR>r</ABBR> and Brye<ABBR>r</ABBR> of Brytayne,</L>
<L>Thai foughten as feythfully in þat fight,</L>
<L>The feelde ful of dede men laye. <MILESTONE N="888"/></L>
<L>XXX<SUP>ti</SUP> thousande, I you plight, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and 30,000 Saracens were slain.</NOTE></L>
<L>Of Sarsenys ther were slayn̄.</L>
<L>Al thinge moste haue an̄ ende,</L>
<L>The nyghte come on ful sone, <MILESTONE N="892"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">At night the Pagans quit the field.</NOTE></L>
<L>Every wighte retourned to wende;</L>
<L>Ferumbras to his men gan gone</L>
<L>And saide "oure hornes blowe we,</L>
<L>This day haue we a ful ille afraye, <MILESTONE N="896"/></L>
<L>To saie the south and not to lye,</L>
<L>Oure goddis holpe vs not to daye,</L>
<L>What devel þat ever hem̄ eilith.</L>
<L>This bataile was so sharpe in faye, <MILESTONE N="900"/></L>
<L>That many a man it wailyth.</L>
<L>Shalle I never in herte be glade to daye, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras vows, never to desist</NOTE></L>
<L>Till I may preve my myghte</L>
<L>With Roulande, that proude ladde, <MILESTONE N="904"/></L>
<L>Or with Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR>, that is so lighte,</L>
<L><PB N="27" REF="98"/>
That evel hath vs ladde;</L>
<L>And in Paris be crowned kinge <NOTE PLACE="marg">unless he be crowned king at Paris.</NOTE></L>
<L>In despite of hem alle, <MILESTONE N="908"/></L>
<L>I wole leve for no thinge</L>
<L>What so evere byfalle.</L>
<L>Kinge Charles with grete honou<ABBR>r</ABBR> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles went to his pavilion and</NOTE></L>
<L>Wente to his Pavilon̄; <MILESTONE N="912"/></L>
<L>Of the treyumple he bare the flou<ABBR>r</ABBR></L>
<L>In dispite of Mahounde.</L>
<L>Almyghty God and Seynte Denyse <NOTE PLACE="marg">thanked God</NOTE></L>
<L>He thanked ful ofte sithe <MILESTONE N="916"/></L>
<L>And oure lady Marie of Paris, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and St. Mary of France.</NOTE></L>
<L>That made hem gladde and blitħ.</L>
<L>He recomendide the olde Knightes, <NOTE PLACE="marg">He praised the elder knights for having won the victory and exhorted the young ones</NOTE></L>
<L>That þat daye hade the victorye, <MILESTONE N="920"/></L>
<L>And charged the yonge with al her myghtes</L>
<L>To haue hem in memorye;</L>
<L>For worthynesse wole not be hadde,</L>
<L>But it be ofte sougħte, <MILESTONE N="924"/> <MILESTONE N="23" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Ner knigħthode wole not ben hadde,</L>
<L>Tille it be dere boghte.</L>
<L>"Therfore ye knightes, yonge of age,</L>
<L>Of oolde ye may now lere, <MILESTONE N="928"/></L>
<L>Howe ye shalle both hurle and rage</L>
<L>In felde with sheelde and spere.</L>
<L>And take ensample of the xij Peris, <NOTE PLACE="marg">to take an example by them.</NOTE></L>
<L>Howe thai have proved her myght, <MILESTONE N="932"/></L>
<L>And howe thai were both wight and fiers</L>
<L>To wy<HI REND="italic">n</HI>nen honourys in righte.</L>
<L>These hethen houndes we shal a-tame</L>
<L>By God in magiste, <MILESTONE N="936"/></L>
<L>Let us make myrtħ in goddis name <NOTE PLACE="marg">They make merry and go to supper.</NOTE></L>
<L>And to souper nowe goo we."</L>
<L>O Thow, rede Marȝ Armypotente, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Prayer addressed to the red Mars Armipotent,</NOTE></L>
<L>That in the trende baye hase made þy trone, <MILESTONE N="940"/></L>
<L>That god arte of bataile and regent</L>
<L><PB N="28" REF="99"/>
And rulist alle that alone,</L>
<L>To whom I profre precious present,</L>
<L>To the makande my moone <MILESTONE N="944"/></L>
<L>Witħ herte, body and alle myn entente,</L>
<L>A crown̄ of precious stoones,</L>
<L>And howe to the I gyfe</L>
<L>Withouten fraude or engyne, <MILESTONE N="948"/></L>
<L>Vppon̄ thy day to make offerynge,</L>
<L>And so shal I ever, while þat I live,</L>
<L>By righte þat longith to my laye,</L>
<L>In worshipe of thy reverence <MILESTONE N="952"/></L>
<L>On thyn owen Tewesdaye</L>
<L>With myr<ABBR>r</ABBR>, aloes and Frankensense,</L>
<L>Vppon̄ condicion̄ that thou me gr<HI REND="italic">a</HI>unte, <NOTE PLACE="marg">to grant the Mahometans the victory over the Christians.</NOTE></L>
<L>The victorye of Crystyn̄ Dogges, <MILESTONE N="956"/></L>
<L>And that I may some <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'sone.'</NOTE> hem adaunte</L>
<L>And sle hem down̄ as hogges,</L>
<L>That have done me distruccion̄</L>
<L>And grete disherytaunce <MILESTONE N="960"/></L>
<L>And eke slayn my men w<HI REND="italic">i</HI>t<HI REND="italic">h</HI> wronge.</L>
<L>Mahounde gyfe hem myschaunce!"</L>
<L>IN the semely seson of the yere, <NOTE PLACE="marg">In the spring of the year</NOTE></L>
<L>Of softenesse of the sonne, <MILESTONE N="964"/></L>
<L>In the prymsauns of grene vere,</L>
<L>Whan floures spryngyn̄ and bygy<HI REND="italic">n</HI>ne, <MILESTONE N="24" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>And alle the floures in the fritħ</L>
<L>Freshly shews here kynde, <MILESTONE N="968"/></L>
<L>Than it is semely therwytħ, <NOTE PLACE="marg">man ought to show his manhood</NOTE></L>
<L>That manhode be in mynde;</L>
<L>For corage wole a man to kitħ,</L>
<L>If he of menske haue mynde, <MILESTONE N="972"/></L>
<L>And of loue to lystyn̄ and lithe, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and to think of love.</NOTE></L>
<L>And to seke honu<ABBR>r</ABBR> for þat ende.</L>
<L>For he was neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>e gode werryou<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">For none can be a good warrior, unless he knows how to love.</NOTE></L>
<L>That cowde not loue a-ryght; <MILESTONE N="976"/></L>
<L><PB N="29" REF="100"/>
For loue hath made many a conquerou<ABBR>r</ABBR></L>
<L>And many a worthy knighte.</L>
<L>This worthy Sowdan, though he heþen we<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">The soudan was a great conqueror;</NOTE></L>
<L>He was a worthy conquerou<ABBR>r</ABBR>; <MILESTONE N="980"/></L>
<L>Many a contrey with shelde and spere</L>
<L>He conquerede wyth grete honoure.</L>
<L>And his worthy sone Ferumbras, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras and</NOTE></L>
<L>That kinge was of Alisaund<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <MILESTONE N="984"/></L>
<L>And Lucafe<ABBR>r</ABBR> of Baldas, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Lukafer wrought</NOTE></L>
<L>That cruel kinge of Cassaund<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>That wroughten wonders w<HI REND="italic">i</HI>t<HI REND="italic">h</HI> here honde <NOTE PLACE="marg">wonders with their hands.</NOTE></L>
<L>With myghte and mayne for to fyghte, <MILESTONE N="988"/></L>
<L>And over-ride mony a manly londe,</L>
<L>As men of Armes hardy and wighte.</L>
<L>The Sowdan seyinge this myschief,</L>
<L>How Charles hade him a-greved, <MILESTONE N="992"/></L>
<L>That grevaunce was him no thinge lese, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'lefe.'</NOTE></L>
<L>He was ful sore ameved.</L>
<L>He sente oute his bassatoures <NOTE PLACE="marg">The soudan sent for his vassals,</NOTE></L>
<L>To Realmes, provynces fer<ABBR>r</ABBR> and ne<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <MILESTONE N="996"/></L>
<L>To Townes, Citeis, Castels and Tours,</L>
<L>To come to him the<ABBR>r</ABBR> he were,</L>
<L>To Inde Maior and to Assye,</L>
<L>To Ascoloyne, Venys, Frige and Ethiope, <MILESTONE N="1000"/></L>
<L>To Nubye, Turkye and Barbarye,</L>
<L>To Macedoine, Bulga<ABBR>r</ABBR> and to Europe.</L>
<L>Alle these people was gadred to Agremore, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and assembled more than 300,000 Saracens at Agremore.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thre hundred thousand of Sarsyns felle, <MILESTONE N="1004"/></L>
<L>Some bloo, some yolowe, some blake as more,</L>
<L>Some horible and stronge as devel of helle.</L>
<L>He made hem drinke Wilde beestes bloode, <MILESTONE N="25" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Of Tigre, Antilope and of Camalyon̄, <MILESTONE N="1008"/></L>
<L>As is here vse to egre here mode,</L>
<L>Whan þai in werre to battayle goon.</L>
<L>He saide to hem "my frendes de<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">He addressed them in order</NOTE></L>
<L>As my trust is alle in you, <MILESTONE N="1012"/></L>
<L><PB N="30" REF="101"/>
On these Frenche dogges, that bene here, <NOTE PLACE="marg">to increase their ardour,</NOTE></L>
<L>Ye moste avenge me nowe.</L>
<L>Thai have done me vilanye,</L>
<L>Mikille of my people have thay slayn̄. <MILESTONE N="1016"/></L>
<L>And yet more-over thay manace me</L>
<L>And drive me to my contrey agayn;</L>
<L>Wherefore I wole at the bygynnynge <NOTE PLACE="marg">ordered a solemn sacrifice to his gods,</NOTE></L>
<L>To Mahounde and to my goddis alle <MILESTONE N="1020"/></L>
<L>Make a solempne offerynge;</L>
<L>The better shall it vs byfalle.</L>
<L>The laste tyme thai were wrothe,</L>
<L>We hade not done oure dute. <MILESTONE N="1024"/></L>
<L>Therefore to saye the southe" ....</L>
<L>There were many hornys blowe,</L>
<L>The presstes senden̄ thikke I-nowe</L>
<L>Goolde, and silver thikke thai throwe, <MILESTONE N="1028"/></L>
<L>With noyse and crye thai beestes slowe,</L>
<L>And thought to spede wel I-nowe;</L>
<L>And every man his vowe he made</L>
<L>To venge the Sowdan̄ of his tene. <MILESTONE N="1032"/></L>
<L>Here goddis of golde thai wex alle fade,</L>
<L>The smoke so grete was hem bitwene.</L>
<L>Whan alle was done, the Sowdan than</L>
<L>Charged Ferumbras redy to be <MILESTONE N="1036"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">and charged Ferumbras</NOTE></L>
<L>On the morowe, ere day began,</L>
<L>To ride oute of þat Cite</L>
<L>With xxx<SUP>ti</SUP> thousande of Assiens, <NOTE PLACE="marg">to march with 30,000 of his people</NOTE></L>
<L>Frigys, Paens and Ascoloynes, <MILESTONE N="1040"/></L>
<L>Turkis, Indeis and Venysyens,</L>
<L>Barbarens, Ethiopes and Macidoynes,</L>
<L>"Bringe him to me, that proude kinge; <NOTE PLACE="marg">against the Christian King, whom he wished to teach courtesy,</NOTE></L>
<L>I shal him teche curtesye, <MILESTONE N="1044"/></L>
<L>Loke that thou leve for nothinge</L>
<L>To sle alle his other mayne, <MILESTONE N="26" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Safe Rouland and Olyuere, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and to slay all his men except Roland and Oliver,</NOTE></L>
<L>That bene of grete renowne, <MILESTONE N="1048"/></L>
<L><PB N="31" REF="102"/>
If thai wole reneye he<ABBR>r</ABBR> goddis the<ABBR>r</ABBR> <NOTE PLACE="marg">if they would renounce their gods.</NOTE></L>
<L>And leven on myghty Mahounde."</L>
<L>FErumbras with grete araye <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras led out his troops;</NOTE></L>
<L>Rode forthe, Mahounde him spede, <MILESTONE N="1052"/></L>
<L>Tille he came nyȝe the<ABBR>r</ABBR> Charles lay <NOTE PLACE="marg">until arriving near Charles's camp, he ordered</NOTE></L>
<L>By syde in a grene mede.</L>
<L>In a woode he buskede his men <NOTE PLACE="marg">them to halt in a wood,</NOTE></L>
<L>Prively that same tyde, <MILESTONE N="1056"/></L>
<L>And with his felowes noon but ten <NOTE PLACE="marg">and advanced with only ten of his men to the camp of Charlemagne,</NOTE></L>
<L>To kinge Charles he gan ride</L>
<L>And said "si<ABBR>r</ABBR> kinge, that Arte so kene,</L>
<L>Upon trwes I come to speke with the, <MILESTONE N="1060"/></L>
<L>If thou be curteis, as I wene,</L>
<L>Thou wolte gr<HI REND="italic">a</HI>unte a bone to me,</L>
<L>That I migħte fight vppon̄ this grene, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and offered him to fight at once against Roland, Oliver, Guy, Duke Naymes, Ogier the Dame, and Richard of Normandy.</NOTE></L>
<L>With Rouland, Olyvere and Gye, <MILESTONE N="1064"/></L>
<L>Duke Neymes and Oge<ABBR>r</ABBR> I mene,</L>
<L>Ye and Duke Richarde of Normandye,</L>
<L>With al sex attones to fight.</L>
<L>My body I prof<ABBR>r</ABBR> here to the <MILESTONE N="1068"/></L>
<L>And requyre the, kinge, thoū do me right,</L>
<L>As thou art gentille Lord and fre;</L>
<L>And if I may conquere hem in fere, <NOTE PLACE="marg">If he should conquer them, he would lead them away to his father's hall; if he should be conquered, he would be his man.</NOTE></L>
<L>To lede them home to my Faderis halle; <MILESTONE N="1072"/></L>
<L>And if thai me, I gr<HI REND="italic">a</HI>unte the here,</L>
<L>To be thy man, body and alle.</L>
<L>The kinge Answered with word<HI REND="italic">is</HI> mylde</L>
<L>And saide "felowe, þat neditħ nought, <MILESTONE N="1076"/></L>
<L>I shalle fynde of myn̄ a Childe,</L>
<L>That shal the fynde that thou hast sought."</L>
<L>The kinge lete calle Sir Roulande <NOTE PLACE="marg">The king sent for Roland and ordered him to undertake the combat.</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "thou most with this man figħt, <MILESTONE N="1080"/></L>
<L>To take this bataile here on honde,</L>
<L>Ther-to God gyfe the grace and myghte!"</L>
<L>Roulande answered with woordis boolde <NOTE PLACE="marg">Roland refuses,</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "Sir, have me excuse<ABBR>d</ABBR>!" <MILESTONE N="1084"/></L>
<L><PB N="32" REF="103"/>
He saide, certeynly he ne wolde;</L>
<L>The bataile vttirly he refused.</L>
<L>"The laste day ye preised faste <NOTE PLACE="marg">because Charles had praised the</NOTE></L>
<L>The oolde knightes of he<ABBR>r</ABBR> worthynes. <MILESTONE N="1088"/> <MILESTONE N="27" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Let hem goon fortħ, I haue no haste, <NOTE PLACE="marg">old knights.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thai may goo shewen he<ABBR>r</ABBR> prowes." <NOTE PLACE="marg">"May they show their valour now."</NOTE></L>
<L>For that worde the kinge was wrothe</L>
<L>And smote him on the mouthe on̄ hye, <MILESTONE N="1092"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles, vexed, smites Roland on the mouth,</NOTE></L>
<L>The bloode at his nose oute-goth, <NOTE PLACE="marg">so that the blood springs from his nose,</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "traito<HI REND="italic">ur,</HI> thou shalte a-bye."</L>
<L>"A-bye" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Roulande "wole I noughte, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and he calls him a traitor.</NOTE></L>
<L>And traito<HI REND="italic">ur</HI> was I never none, <MILESTONE N="1096"/></L>
<L>By þat lord, þat me dere hath bought!"</L>
<L>And braide oute Durnedale þe<ABBR>r</ABBR> anone. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Roland draws his sword,</NOTE></L>
<L>Ho wolde haue smyten̄ the kinge the<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>Ne hadde the barons ronne bytwene; <MILESTONE N="1100"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">but the other barons separate them</NOTE></L>
<L>The kinge with-drowe him for fe<ABBR>r</ABBR></L>
<L>And passed home as it myght beste bene.</L>
<L>The Barons made hem at one <NOTE PLACE="marg">and try to con∣ciliate them.</NOTE></L>
<L>With grete praye<ABBR>r</ABBR> and instaunce, <MILESTONE N="1104"/></L>
<L>As every wrath moste over-gone,</L>
<L>Of the more myschiefe to make voydaunce.</L>
<L>Olyuere herde telle of this, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Meanwhile Oliver, who, being sorley wounded, kept his bed, on hearing of this dispute, had armed him∣self and went to Charles.</NOTE></L>
<L>That in his bedde laye seke sore. <MILESTONE N="1108"/></L>
<L>He armede him ful sone I-wisse,</L>
<L>And to the kinge he wente withoute more</L>
<L>And saide "Sir Kinge, a bone graunte me</L>
<L>For alle the servyse, that I haue done, <MILESTONE N="1112"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">He reminds him of his long services, and demands the battle.</NOTE></L>
<L>To fight with þat kinge so free</L>
<L>To morue day, ere it be none."</L>
<L>Charles answered to Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR>:</L>
<L>"Thou arte seke and woundede sore, <MILESTONE N="1116"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles remon∣strates with him.</NOTE></L>
<L>And thou also my cosyn̄ dere,</L>
<L>Therfore speke thereof no more."—</L>
<L>"Sir Kinge" he saide "I am alle hoole, <NOTE PLACE="marg">But Oliver insists.</NOTE></L>
<L>I aske you this bone in goddis name." <MILESTONE N="1120"/></L>
<L><PB N="33" REF="104"/>
"Certes" he saide "I holde the a fole,</L>
<L>But I praye, god sheelde the fro shame."</L>
<L>Forth he rideth in that Forest, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Oliver rides to the forest, and finds Ferumbras alighted under a tree, to a branch of which his steed was tied.</NOTE></L>
<L>Tille he gan Ferumbras see, <MILESTONE N="1124"/></L>
<L>Where he was ligħt and toke his rest,</L>
<L>His stede renewed til a grene tre.</L>
<L>"Sir" he saide "reste thoū wele!</L>
<L>Kinge Charles sente me hidu<ABBR>r</ABBR>. <MILESTONE N="1128"/></L>
<L>If thou be curteys knighte and lele, <NOTE PLACE="marg">"Arise," he said,</NOTE> <NOTE PLACE="marg">"I am come to fight with thee."</NOTE></L>
<L>Rise vp and let vs fight to-geder." <MILESTONE N="28" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Ferumbras sate stille and lough, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras, without moving, demands his name.</NOTE></L>
<L>Him liste not to rise oute of the place. <MILESTONE N="1132"/></L>
<L>"My felowe" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d he "what arte thou?</L>
<L>Telle me thy name for goddis grace."</L>
<L>"Sir" he saide "Generyse, <NOTE PLACE="marg">"I am Generys," says Oliver, "a young knight lately dubbed."</NOTE></L>
<L>A yonge knighte late dobbet newe." <MILESTONE N="1136"/></L>
<L>"By Mahounde" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d he "thou arte not wyse,</L>
<L>For thy comyng shaltowe sore rewe.</L>
<L>I holde Charles but a foole <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras observes, "Charles is a fool to send thee.</NOTE></L>
<L>To sende the hide<ABBR>r</ABBR> to me, <MILESTONE N="1140"/></L>
<L>I shall the lerne a newe scole,</L>
<L>If thoue so hardy to fighte be.</L>
<L>I wende, he wolde haue sende Roulande,</L>
<L>Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR> and iiij mo Dosyperys, <MILESTONE N="1144"/></L>
<L>That hade bene mygħty men of honde</L>
<L>Bataile to a-bide stronge and fiers.</L>
<L>With the me liste no playe begynne,</L>
<L>Ride agayn̄ and saye him soo! <MILESTONE N="1148"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Go and tell him to send me Roland and Oliver, and such four other douzepeers.</NOTE></L>
<L>Of the may I no worshyp<HI REND="italic">e</HI> wynne,</L>
<L>Though I slougħ the and such V mo."</L>
<L>"Howe longe" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR> "wiltowe plete? <NOTE PLACE="marg">For little honour were it to me to fight with thee." "Spare thy words," says Oliver, "and take thy arms."</NOTE></L>
<L>Take thyn̄ armes and come to me, <MILESTONE N="1152"/></L>
<L>And prove þat thou saiest in dede,</L>
<L>For boost thou blowest, and þenkes <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'as thenketh.'</NOTE> me."</L>
<L>Whan Ferumbras herde him speke so wel,</L>
<L><PB N="34" REF="105"/>
He caught his helme in grete Ir<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> <MILESTONE N="1156"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras is wrath and seizes his helmet,</NOTE></L>
<L>That wroght was of goode fyne stele</L>
<L>With Perlis pight, Rubeis and Saphir<HI REND="italic">e.</HI></L>
<L>Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR> halpe him it to onlase; <NOTE PLACE="marg">which Oliver assists him to lace.</NOTE></L>
<L>Gilte it was alle abowte. <MILESTONE N="1160"/></L>
<L>Ferumbras þanked him of his grace <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras thanks him, courteously bowing to him. They mount their steeds,</NOTE></L>
<L>And curteisly to him gan lowte.</L>
<L>Thai worthed vp on̄ here stedes,</L>
<L>To Iuste thai made hem preest, <MILESTONE N="1164"/></L>
<L>Of Armes to shewe he<ABBR>r</ABBR> myghty dedis</L>
<L>Thai layden here speres in a-reeste,</L>
<L>To-geder thai ro<HI REND="italic">n</HI>nen̄ as fire of thonde<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">rush together like fire of</NOTE></L>
<L>That both here Launces to-braste. <MILESTONE N="1168"/> <MILESTONE N="29" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>That they seten̄, it was grete wonder; <NOTE PLACE="marg">thunder, and have their lances broken.</NOTE></L>
<L>So harde it was, þat thay gan threste.</L>
<L>Tho drowen̄ thai oute here swordes kene <NOTE PLACE="marg">They draw their swords.</NOTE></L>
<L>And smyten to-geder by one assente. <MILESTONE N="1172"/></L>
<L>There thai hitten̄, it was wele sene;</L>
<L>To sle eche other was here entente.</L>
<L>Syr Ferumbras smote Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras smites Oliver on his helmet</NOTE></L>
<L>Vppon̄ the helme righte on hye <MILESTONE N="1176"/></L>
<L>With his swerde of metel cle<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>That the fyre he made oute-flye. <NOTE PLACE="marg">so that the fire flies.</NOTE></L>
<L>Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR> him hitte agayn̄ vpon̄ the hede <NOTE PLACE="marg">Oliver strikes at the head of Ferumbras,</NOTE></L>
<L><NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Blank in MS. See the note.</NOTE> the hede than fulle sore, <MILESTONE N="1180"/></L>
<L>He carfe awaye with mygħt and mayne <NOTE PLACE="marg">breaks away the circle of his helmet,</NOTE></L>
<L>The cercle, that sate vppon̄ his crown̄.</L>
<L>The stroke glode down by his bak<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">and the sword glancing off down his back, he</NOTE></L>
<L>The Arson he smot ther awaye <MILESTONE N="1184"/></L>
<L>And the botelle<HI REND="italic">s</HI> of bawme withoute lak<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">cuts off two bottles of balm,</NOTE></L>
<L>That uppone the grene ther thai laye,</L>
<L>That were trussed by-hynde him faste.</L>
<L>Tho Ferumbras was fułł woo; <MILESTONE N="1188"/></L>
<L>Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR> light adown̄ in haste,</L>
<L>The botellis he seased both two,</L>
<L><PB N="35" REF="106"/>
He threwe hem into the River than <NOTE PLACE="marg">which he throws into the river.</NOTE></L>
<L>As fer<ABBR>r</ABBR> as he myghte throwe. <MILESTONE N="1192"/></L>
<L>"Alas" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Ferumbras "what doistowe, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">MS.</HI> deistowe.</NOTE> manne?</L>
<L>Thou art wode, as I trowe.</L>
<L>Thai were worth an C mł pounde <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras tells him that they were invaluable to a wounded man, and that he</NOTE></L>
<L>To a man, þat were wounded sore. <MILESTONE N="1196"/></L>
<L>Ther was no p<HI REND="italic">re</HI>cioso<HI REND="italic">ur</HI> thinge vppon̄ grounde,</L>
<L>That myghte helpe a man more.</L>
<L>Thou shalt abye by Mahounde,</L>
<L>That is a man of myght<HI REND="italic">es</HI> moost. <MILESTONE N="1200"/></L>
<L>I shall breke both bake and crown̄</L>
<L>And sle the, ther thou goist." <NOTE PLACE="marg">should atone for their loss with his life.</NOTE></L>
<L>Tho Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR> worth vp agayn̄,</L>
<L>His swerde he hade oute I-drawe. <MILESTONE N="1204"/></L>
<L>Ferumbras him smote with mayne <NOTE PLACE="marg">He strikes at Oliver, who wards off the blow with his shield, but his steed is killed under him.</NOTE></L>
<L>And mente to haue him slawe.</L>
<L>He smote as doth the dinte of þondir;</L>
<L>It glased down by his sheelde <MILESTONE N="1208"/></L>
<L>And carfe his stedes neke a-sonder, <MILESTONE N="30" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>That dede he fille in the felde.</L>
<L>Wightly Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR> vp-sterte <NOTE PLACE="marg">Oliver quickly starts up and tries to kill his adversary's horse,</NOTE></L>
<L>As Bacheler, doughti of dede, <MILESTONE N="1212"/></L>
<L>With swerde in honde him for to hirte</L>
<L>Or Ferumbras goode stede.</L>
<L>That Ferumbras aspied welle,</L>
<L>He rode a-waye than ful faste <MILESTONE N="1216"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">but Ferumbras rides off and ties it to a hazel.</NOTE></L>
<L>And tiede him to a grene hasel,</L>
<L>And come ayen to him in haste</L>
<L>And saide "nowe yelde the to me! <NOTE PLACE="marg">"Yield thyself to me," says Ferumbras;</NOTE></L>
<L>Thou maiste not longe endure; <MILESTONE N="1220"/></L>
<L>And leve on Mahounde, þat is so de<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'free.'</NOTE> <NOTE PLACE="marg">"believe on Mahound, and I</NOTE></L>
<L>And thy life I shalle the ensure. <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">MS.</HI> ensuce.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thou shalt be a Duke in my cont<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">will make thee a duke in my country and give thee my sister."</NOTE></L>
<L>And men haue at thyn̄ owen̄ wille. <MILESTONE N="1224"/></L>
<L>To my Sustir shaltowe wedded be,</L>
<L><PB N="36" REF="107"/>
It were pite the for to spille!"</L>
<L>"Better" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR> "shul we dele,</L>
<L>By God that is in magiste, <MILESTONE N="1228"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">"Ere I yield to thee," answered Oliver, "thou shalt feel my strokes."</NOTE></L>
<L>And of my strokes shaltow more fele,</L>
<L>Er I to the shalle yelde me."</L>
<L>Thai smeten togeder witħ egre mode, <NOTE PLACE="marg">They fight for a considerable time</NOTE></L>
<L>And nathir of othire dradde; <MILESTONE N="1232"/></L>
<L>Thai p<HI REND="italic">er</HI>sed he<ABBR>r</ABBR> hauberk<HI REND="italic">es,</HI> that were so goode,</L>
<L>Tille both thayr bodyes bladde. <NOTE PLACE="marg">the blood ran from both their bodies. By mutual consent they stop to take breath.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thay foughten̄ soo longe, þat by assente</L>
<L>Thai drewe hem a litil bysyde, <MILESTONE N="1236"/></L>
<L>A litil while thaym to avente,</L>
<L>And refresshed hem at þat tyde.</L>
<L>"Generis" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Ferumbras, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras asks Oliver again his name and kin.</NOTE></L>
<L>"As thou arte here gentil knighte, <MILESTONE N="1240"/></L>
<L>Telle me nowe here in this place</L>
<L>Of thy kyn̄ and what thoū hight;</L>
<L>Me thenkith by the now evermore,</L>
<L>Thou shuldist be one of the xij peris, <MILESTONE N="1244"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">"Thou must be one of the douze∣peers, as thou fightest so well."</NOTE></L>
<L>That maiste fighte with me so sore,</L>
<L>And arte so stronge, worthy and fiers."</L>
<L>Olyuere answered to hym agayn̄:</L>
<L>"For fe<ABBR>r</ABBR> I leve it not ontoolde, <MILESTONE N="1248"/></L>
<L>My name is Olyuere certayn̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">"I am Oliver, cousin to Charlemagne."</NOTE></L>
<L>Cousyn to kynge Charles the boolde, <MILESTONE N="31" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>To whome I shalle the sende</L>
<L>Qwikke or dede this same daye, <MILESTONE N="1252"/></L>
<L>By conqueste here in this feelde,</L>
<L>And make the to renye thy laye."</L>
<L>"O" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Ferumbras than̄ to Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>"Welcome thoū arte in-to this place, <MILESTONE N="1256"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">"Thou art welcome here," says Ferumbras;</NOTE></L>
<L>I have desyrede many a yere</L>
<L>To gyfe the harde grace.</L>
<L>Thou slough myn̄ uncle Sir P<HI REND="italic">er</HI>sagyne, <NOTE PLACE="marg">"thou slewest my uncle,</NOTE></L>
<L>The doughty kinge of Italye, <MILESTONE N="1260"/></L>
<L>The worthyeste kinge þat lyued of men,</L>
<L><PB N="37" REF="108"/>
By Mahounde, thou shalt abye!" <NOTE PLACE="marg">now thou shalt pay the penalty!"</NOTE></L>
<L>Tho thai dongen̄ faste to-gede<ABBR>r</ABBR></L>
<L>While the longe day endured, <MILESTONE N="1264"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">The fight continued the whole day.</NOTE></L>
<L>Nowe hithe<ABBR>r</ABBR> and nowe thide<ABBR>r</ABBR>;</L>
<L>Fro strokes wytħ sheeld<HI REND="italic">es</HI> here bodies þai couered.</L>
<L>And at the laste Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR> smote him so <NOTE PLACE="marg">At last Oliver, smiting</NOTE></L>
<L>Vppon̄ the helme, þat was of stele, <MILESTONE N="1268"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras upon the helmet, has his sword broken.</NOTE></L>
<L>That his swerde brake in two.</L>
<L>Tho wepen̄ had he nevere a dele.</L>
<L>Who was woo but Olyuere than?</L>
<L>He saugh noone other remedy. <MILESTONE N="1272"/></L>
<L>He saide "si<ABBR>r</ABBR>, as thoū arte gentile man,</L>
<L>On me nowe here haue mercy.</L>
<L>It were grete shame I-wis,</L>
<L>And honu<ABBR>r</ABBR> were it noon̄, <MILESTONE N="1276"/></L>
<L>To sle a man wepenles;</L>
<L>That shame wolde neve<ABBR>r</ABBR> goon̄."</L>
<L>"Nay traito<HI REND="italic">ur,</HI> thou getiste noon̄.</L>
<L>Hade I here an hundred and moo! <MILESTONE N="1280"/></L>
<L>Knele down̄ and yelde the here anoon̄,</L>
<L>And eles here I woole the sloo."</L>
<L>Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR> saugh, it wolde not be,</L>
<L>To truste to moch in his grace. <MILESTONE N="1284"/></L>
<L>He ranne to the stede, þ<HI REND="italic">a</HI>t stode by the tr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> <NOTE PLACE="marg">He ran to the steed at the tree and seized a sword that was hanging there;</NOTE></L>
<L>A swerde he raught in þat place,</L>
<L>That was trussed on Ferumbras stede,</L>
<L>Of fyne stele goode and stronge. <MILESTONE N="1288"/></L>
<L>He thought he quyte <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> Ferumbras his mede.</L>
<L>Almoost hadde he abyde to longe;</L>
<L>For in turnynge Ferumbras him smote, <MILESTONE N="32" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>That stroke he myghte welle fele, <MILESTONE N="1292"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">but in turning or Ferumbras he received a blow</NOTE></L>
<L>It come on hym so hevy and hoote,</L>
<L>That down it made hym to knele. <NOTE PLACE="marg">that made him kneel down.</NOTE></L>
<L>Tho was Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR> sore ashamede</L>
<L>And saide "thou cursed Sarasyne, <MILESTONE N="1296"/></L>
<L><PB N="38" REF="109"/>
Thy proude pride shall be atamed,</L>
<L>By God and by seinte Qwyntyne.</L>
<L>Thou hast stole on me that dynte,</L>
<L>I shall quyte the thyn̄ hire." <MILESTONE N="1300"/></L>
<L>A stroke than Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR> him lente, <NOTE PLACE="marg">But Oliver returns him fearful stroke.</NOTE></L>
<L>That hym thought his eyen̄ we<ABBR>r</ABBR> on fi<ABBR>r</ABBR>.</L>
<L>Kinge Charles in his pavilon̄ was <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles, seeing Oliver on his knees,</NOTE></L>
<L>And loked towarde þat fyghte <MILESTONE N="1304"/></L>
<L>And saugh, howe fiers Ferumbras</L>
<L>Made Olyuere knele down̄ right.</L>
<L>Wo was him tho in his herte;</L>
<L>To Ih<HI REND="italic">es</HI>u Criste he made his mone; <MILESTONE N="1308"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">prayed to Christ</NOTE></L>
<L>It was a sight of peynes smerte,</L>
<L>That Olyuere kneled so sone:</L>
<L>"O Lord, God in Trinite,</L>
<L>That of myghtis thoū arte moost, <MILESTONE N="1312"/></L>
<L>By vertue of thy maieste</L>
<L>That alle knoweste and woste,</L>
<L>Lete not this hethen man</L>
<L>Thy seru<HI REND="italic">au</HI>nte ouercome in fyght, <MILESTONE N="1316"/></L>
<L>That on the bileve ne kan,</L>
<L>Ih<HI REND="italic">es</HI>u, Lorde, for thy myghte!</L>
<L>But gr<HI REND="italic">a</HI>unte thy man the victorye, <NOTE PLACE="marg">that he might grant the victory over the Pagan.</NOTE></L>
<L>And the Paynym̄ skomfited to be, <MILESTONE N="1320"/></L>
<L>As thou arte Almyghty God of glorye!</L>
<L>Nowe mekely, Lorde, I pray to the."</L>
<L>To Charles anoone an Aungel came <NOTE PLACE="marg">An angel announces him,</NOTE></L>
<L>And broght him tidingges sone, <MILESTONE N="1324"/></L>
<L>That God had herde his praie<ABBR>r</ABBR> than̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">that his prayer was heard.</NOTE></L>
<L>And gr<HI REND="italic">a</HI>unte him his bone.</L>
<L>Tho Charles thanked God aboue <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles thanks God.</NOTE></L>
<L>With herte and thought, worde and dede, <MILESTONE N="1328"/></L>
<L>And saide "blessed be thoū, lorde almyghty, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE></L>
<L>That helpiste thy seru<HI REND="italic">au</HI>nte in nede."</L>
<L>These Champions to-gedir thai gone <MILESTONE N="33" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L><PB N="39" REF="110"/>
With strokes grete and eke sure, <MILESTONE N="1332"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">They begin again.</NOTE></L>
<L>Eche of hem donge othir on̄,</L>
<L>Alle the while thai myghte endu<ABBR>r</ABBR>.</L>
<L>Ferumbras brake his swerde <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras breaks his sword on Oliver's helmet.</NOTE></L>
<L>On Olyueris helme on hye. <MILESTONE N="1336"/></L>
<L>Tho wexe he ful sore a-ferde;</L>
<L>He ranne for an othir redyly <NOTE PLACE="marg">He runs for another and asks Oliver to sur∣render.</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "Olyuere, yelde the to me</L>
<L>And leve thy Cristen̄ laye, <MILESTONE N="1340"/></L>
<L>Thou shalte have alle <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Probably an error for</HI> 'half.'</NOTE> my kingdome free</L>
<L>And alle aftir my daye."</L>
<L>"Fye, Saresyne" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Olyuere than̄,</L>
<L>"Trowest thou, that I were wode, <MILESTONE N="1344"/></L>
<L>To forsake him, þat made me man̄</L>
<L>And boght me with his hert blode."</L>
<L>He raught a stroke to Ferumbras, <NOTE PLACE="marg">But Oliver aims at Ferumbras a blow which cuts his hauberk, so</NOTE></L>
<L>On his helme it gan down̄ glyde, <MILESTONE N="1348"/></L>
<L>It brast his hawberke at þat ras</L>
<L>And carfe hym throughe-oute his syde,</L>
<L>His bare guttis men mygħt see; <NOTE PLACE="marg">that his bowels are laid bare.</NOTE></L>
<L>The blode faste down̄ ranne. <MILESTONE N="1352"/></L>
<L>"Hoo, Olyvere, I yelde me to the, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Ferumbras implores his mercy, and</NOTE></L>
<L>And here I become thy man.</L>
<L>I am so hurte, I may not stonde,</L>
<L>I put me alle in thy grace. <MILESTONE N="1356"/></L>
<L>My goddis ben false by water and londe, <NOTE PLACE="marg">consents to be christened, his gods having proved false.</NOTE></L>
<L>I reneye hem alle here in this place, <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">In the margin the Scribe adds:—</HI>'The merci Ladi helpe.'</NOTE></L>
<L>Baptised nowe wole I be.</L>
<L>To Ih<HI REND="italic">es</HI>u Crist I wole me take, <MILESTONE N="1360"/></L>
<L>That Charles the kinge shal sene, <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE></L>
<L>And alle my goddes for-sake</L>
<L>Take myn hawberke and do it on the, <NOTE PLACE="marg">He requested him to take his hauberk, to</NOTE></L>
<L>Thou shalte haue fułł grete nede. <MILESTONE N="1364"/></L>
<L><PB N="40" REF="111"/>
X thousande Saresyns waiten vppon̄ me,</L>
<L>And therfore go take my stede. <NOTE PLACE="marg">fetch his horse,</NOTE></L>
<L>Lay me to-fore the, I the praye,</L>
<L>And lede me to thy tente. <MILESTONE N="1368"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">and to carry him to his own tent.</NOTE></L>
<L>Hye the faste forth in thy way, <MILESTONE N="34" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>That the Saresyns the not hente."</L>
<L>A-noon̄ it was done, as he ordeynede,</L>
<L>And faste forth thai ryden. <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'soghten.'</NOTE> <MILESTONE N="1372"/></L>
<L>The Saresyns anone assembled, <NOTE PLACE="marg">But the Saracens, who lay concealed in the wood, rush out.</NOTE></L>
<L>For to haue with hem foghten.</L>
<L>Ferumbras saugħ the feelde thore</L>
<L>Of Sarsynes fully filled; <MILESTONE N="1376"/></L>
<L>Of Olyvere dradde he ful sore, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Oliver, being surrounded, sets</NOTE></L>
<L>That Saresyns shulde him haue killed.</L>
<L>He praide, that he wolde let him down̄</L>
<L>"Vndir yonde Olyfe tree, <MILESTONE N="1380"/></L>
<L>For if ye cast me down̄ here, with hors shoon̄ <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE></L>
<L>Alle to-treden̄ shalle I be."</L>
<L>He priked forth and layde him tha<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> <NOTE PLACE="marg">down Ferumbras under an olive∣tree, and defends himself with his sword,</NOTE></L>
<L>Out of the horses trase, <MILESTONE N="1384"/></L>
<L>And with his swerde by-gan him we<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>For amonge hem alle he was.</L>
<L>A Saresyn̄ smote him witħ a spere,</L>
<L>That it brake on pecis thre; <MILESTONE N="1388"/></L>
<L>His hauberke mygħt he not de<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>So stronge and welle I-wroght was he.</L>
<L>He hit þat Saresyns with his swerde <NOTE PLACE="marg">dealing the Saracens many a hard blow.</NOTE></L>
<L>Througħ the helme in-to the brayne. <MILESTONE N="1392"/></L>
<L>He made an other as sore aferde,</L>
<L>He smote of his Arme with mayne.</L>
<L>But than̄ come Roulande witħ Durnedale <NOTE PLACE="marg">Then Roland rushed into the throng of the enemy and slew many;</NOTE></L>
<L>And made way him a-bowte. <MILESTONE N="1396"/></L>
<L>He slowe hem down̄ in the vale,</L>
<L>Of him hade thai grete dowte.</L>
<L>The prees of Saresyns was so stronge</L>
<L><PB N="41" REF="112"/>
A-boute Roulande that tyde. <MILESTONE N="1400"/></L>
<L>Thai sloughen̄ his horsys with thronge, <NOTE PLACE="marg">his horse being killed by arrows and darts,</NOTE></L>
<L>And dartis throwen̄ on every syde.</L>
<L>Whan Roulande was on his Fete, <NOTE PLACE="marg">he fights on foot,</NOTE></L>
<L>Than̄ was he woo witħ-alle. <MILESTONE N="1404"/></L>
<L>Many of hem he felte yete</L>
<L>And dede to grounde made hem falle.</L>
<L>At the last his swerde brake, <NOTE PLACE="marg">but his sword breaking,</NOTE></L>
<L>Than̄ hadde he wepyn̄ noon̄, <MILESTONE N="1408"/></L>
<L>As he smote a Saresyns bak<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <MILESTONE N="35" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>A-sundre down̄ to the Arson̄.</L>
<L>Tho was he caught, he mygħt not flee, <NOTE PLACE="marg">he is taken</NOTE></L>
<L>His hondes thai bounden̄ faste <MILESTONE N="1412"/></L>
<L>And lad him forth to here Cite, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and led away.</NOTE></L>
<L>And in depe prison̄ they hem caste.</L>
<L>Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR> sawe, howe he was ladde,</L>
<L>A sorye man̄ than̄ was he; <MILESTONE N="1416"/></L>
<L>Him hadde leuer to haue bene dede</L>
<L>Than suffren that myschief to be.</L>
<L>Smertly aftire he pursued tho, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Oliver rides to rescue him,</NOTE></L>
<L>To reskue his dere brother. <MILESTONE N="1420"/></L>
<L>The prees was so grete, he myghte not so,</L>
<L>It myghte be no othir,</L>
<L>Be he was cowþe <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'caughte.'</NOTE> by ver<ABBR>r</ABBR> force</L>
<L>With LX of Astopartes. <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">As<HI REND="italic">c</HI>opartes.</NOTE> <MILESTONE N="1424"/></L>
<L>Thai hurte him foule and slougħ his hors <NOTE PLACE="marg">but his horse being also killed,</NOTE></L>
<L>With gauylokes and wyth dartis.</L>
<L>Yet on foote, ere he were foolde,</L>
<L>He slough of hem fiftene. <MILESTONE N="1428"/></L>
<L>He was not slayn̄, as god woolde,</L>
<L>But taken and bounded <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Miswritten for</HI> 'bounde<HI REND="italic">n.</HI>'</NOTE> w<HI REND="italic">i</HI>t<HI REND="italic">h</HI> tene. <NOTE PLACE="marg">he is overpowered and bound. Both were conducted to Lukafer of Baldas.</NOTE></L>
<L>Tho were taken̄ to Lucafe<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>The proude kinge of Baldas, <MILESTONE N="1432"/></L>
<L>Both Roulande and Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR>.</L>
<L><PB N="42" REF="113"/>
Gladde was he of that cas.</L>
<L>Kinge Charles was in herte woo,</L>
<L>When he saughe his neuewes so ladde, <MILESTONE N="1436"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles sees them, and calls for a rescue.</NOTE></L>
<L>He cried to the Frenshmen̄ tho:</L>
<L>"Reskue we these knyghtes at nede."</L>
<L>The kyng<HI REND="italic">e</HI> himselfe slough many one, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Many enemies were slain,</NOTE></L>
<L>So dede the Barons bolde. <MILESTONE N="1440"/></L>
<L>It wolde not bene, thai were agon̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">but the Saracens had fled with their prisoners, and Charles is obliged to turn back.</NOTE></L>
<L>Magre who so woolde.</L>
<L>The Saresyns drewe hem to here Cite,</L>
<L>Kinge Charles turned agayne. <MILESTONE N="1444"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Under a holm tree they find Ferumbras,</NOTE></L>
<L>He saugħ under an holme tre,</L>
<L>Where a knight him semed lay slayn̄.</L>
<L>Thederward he rode witħ swerde in honde.</L>
<L>Tho he saugħ, he was alyve; <MILESTONE N="1448"/></L>
<L>He lay walowynge vppon the sonde</L>
<L>With blody woundes fyve. <MILESTONE N="36" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>"What arte thow?" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Charlemayne,</L>
<L>"Who hath the hurte so sore?" <MILESTONE N="1452"/></L>
<L>"I am Ferumbras" he saide certayn̄,</L>
<L>"That am of hethen̄ lore."</L>
<L>"O fals Saresyn̄" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d the kinge,</L>
<L>"Thou shalte have sorowe astyte; <MILESTONE N="1456"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">whom he is going to put to death.</NOTE></L>
<L>By the I haue lost my two Cosynes,</L>
<L>Thyn̄ hede shalle I of-smyte."</L>
<L>"O gentil kinge" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Ferumbrase,</L>
<L>"Olyuere my maister me hight <MILESTONE N="1460"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">But on his requesting to be baptized,</NOTE></L>
<L>To be Baptised by goddis grace,</L>
<L>And to dyen̄ a Cristen̄ knight<HI REND="italic">e.</HI></L>
<L>Honu<ABBR>r</ABBR> were it noon to the</L>
<L>A discoumfite man̄ to slo, <MILESTONE N="1464"/></L>
<L>That is conu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ted and Baptized wolde be</L>
<L>And thy man bycomen̄ also."</L>
<L>The kinge hade pite of him than̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles took pity with him,</NOTE></L>
<L>He toke him to his grace <MILESTONE N="1468"/></L>
<L>And assyned anoon̄ a man</L>
<L><PB N="43" REF="114"/>
To lede him to his place. <NOTE PLACE="marg">led him to his tent, and ordered a surgeon to attend him.</NOTE></L>
<L>He sende to him his surgyne</L>
<L>To hele his woundes wyde. <MILESTONE N="1472"/></L>
<L>He ordeyned to him such medycyn̄,</L>
<L>That sone myght he go and ryde. <NOTE PLACE="marg">He soon recovered,</NOTE></L>
<L>The kinge commaunded bishop<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Turpyn̄</L>
<L>To make a fonte redye, <MILESTONE N="1476"/></L>
<L>To Baptise Ferumbras þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI>in</L>
<L>In the name of god Almygħtye.</L>
<L>He was Cristened in þat welle, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and bishop Turpin baptised him, by the name of Floreyn.</NOTE></L>
<L>Floreyne the kinge alle him calle, <MILESTONE N="1480"/></L>
<L>He forsoke the foule feende of helle</L>
<L>And his fals goddis alle.</L>
<L>Nought for than̄ Ferumbras <NOTE PLACE="marg">But he continued to be called Ferumbras all his life.</NOTE></L>
<L>Alle his life cleped was he, <MILESTONE N="1484"/></L>
<L>And aftirwarde in so<HI REND="italic">m</HI>me place, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Afterwards he was known as Floreyn of Rome</NOTE></L>
<L>Floreyne of Rome Cite.</L>
<L>God for him many myracles shewe<ABBR>d,</ABBR></L>
<L>So holy a man he by-came, <MILESTONE N="1488"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">on account of his holiness.</NOTE></L>
<L>That witnessitħ both lerned and lewde,</L>
<L>The fame of him so ranne.</L>
<L>NOwe for to telle of Roulande <NOTE PLACE="marg">Roland and Oliver being brought to the Soudan, Laban enquires their names.</NOTE></L>
<L>And of Olyuere, that worthy wos, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">'was.'</NOTE> <MILESTONE N="1492"/></L>
<L>Howe thai were brougħt to þ<SUP>e</SUP> Sowdan̄</L>
<L>By the kinge of Boldas.</L>
<L>The Sowdan̄ hem sore affrayned,</L>
<L>What þat here names were. <MILESTONE N="1496"/></L>
<L>Rouland saide and noght alayned:</L>
<L>"Syr Roulande and sire Olyuere, <NOTE PLACE="marg">They confess their names.</NOTE></L>
<L>Nevewes to Kinge Charles of Fraunce,</L>
<L>That worthy kinge and Emp<HI REND="italic">er</HI>oure, <MILESTONE N="1500"/></L>
<L>That nowe are takyn by myschaunce</L>
<L>To be prisoneres here in thy toure."</L>
<L>"A, Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR>, arte thou here?</L>
<L>That haste my sone distroyede, <MILESTONE N="1504"/></L>
<L><PB N="44" REF="115"/>
And Rouland that arte his fere,</L>
<L>That so ofte me hatħ anoyed.</L>
<L>To Mahounde I make a vowe here, <NOTE PLACE="marg">The Soudan swears they shall both be executed the next morning before his dinner.</NOTE></L>
<L>That to morue, ere I do ete, <MILESTONE N="1508"/></L>
<L>Ye shulle be slayn̄ botħ qwik in fere,</L>
<L>And lives shalle ye bothe lete."</L>
<L>Tho saide maide Florepas:</L>
<L>"My fader so derewortħ and de<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <MILESTONE N="1512"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">But Floripas advises him to detain them as hostages, and</NOTE></L>
<L>Ye shulle be avysed of this cas,</L>
<L>How and in what manere</L>
<L>My brothir, þat is to prison̄ take,</L>
<L>May be delyu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ed by hem nowe, <MILESTONE N="1516"/></L>
<L>By cause of these two knight<HI REND="italic">es</HI> sake,</L>
<L>That bene in warde here with yoū.</L>
<L>Wherefore I counsaile yoū, my fader dere,</L>
<L>To have mynde of Sir Ferumbras. <MILESTONE N="1520"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">to remember his son Ferumbras,</NOTE></L>
<L>Pute hem in youre prison̄ here,</L>
<L>Tille ye haue better space.</L>
<L>So that ye haue my brother agayn̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">for whom they might be exchanged.</NOTE></L>
<L>For hem, þat ye haue here; <MILESTONE N="1524"/></L>
<L>And certeyn̄ elles wole he be slayn̄,</L>
<L>That is to you so lefe and dere."</L>
<L>"A, Floripp, I-blessed thou bee,</L>
<L>Thy counsaile is goode at nede, <MILESTONE N="1528"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">The Soudan finds her counsel good,</NOTE></L>
<L>I wolde not leve my sone so free,</L>
<L>So Mahounde moost me spede,</L>
<L>For al the Realme of hethen Spayne, <MILESTONE N="38" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>That is so brode and large. <MILESTONE N="1532"/></L>
<L>Sone clepe forth my gaylo<HI REND="italic">ur</HI> Bretomayne, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and orders his gaoler Bretomayn to imprison them,</NOTE></L>
<L>That he of hem hadde his charge,</L>
<L>"Caste hem in your prison̄ depe,</L>
<L>Mete and drinke gyfe hem none, <MILESTONE N="1536"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">but to leave them without food.</NOTE></L>
<L>Chayne hem faste, þat thay not slepe;</L>
<L>For here goode daies bene a-gone."</L>
<L>Tho were thay cast in prison depe <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'dirke.'</NOTE></L>
<L><PB N="45" REF="116"/>
Every tyde the see came inne. <MILESTONE N="1540"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">At high tide the sea filled their deep cells.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thay myght not see, so was it myrke,</L>
<L>The watir wente to her chynne.</L>
<L>The salte watir hem greved sore, <NOTE PLACE="marg">They suffered much from the salt water, from their wounds, and from hunger.</NOTE></L>
<L>Here woundis sore did smerte. <MILESTONE N="1544"/></L>
<L>Hungir and thurste greved heme yet more,</L>
<L>It wente yet more nere here herte.</L>
<L>Who maye live withoute mete?</L>
<L>vj dayes hadde thay rigħt none, <MILESTONE N="1548"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">On the sixth day,</NOTE></L>
<L>Ner drinke that thay mygħt gete,</L>
<L>Bute loked vppon the harde stone.</L>
<L>So on a daye, as God it wolde,</L>
<L>Floripas to hir garden̄ wente, <MILESTONE N="1552"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Floripas, who was gathering flowers in her garden,</NOTE></L>
<L>To geder Floures in morne colde.</L>
<L>Here maydyns from̄ hir she sente,</L>
<L>For she herde grete lamentacion̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">heard them lament.</NOTE></L>
<L>In the Prison̄, that was ther nye; <MILESTONE N="1556"/></L>
<L>She supposed by ymagynacion̄,</L>
<L>That it was the prisoners sory.</L>
<L>She wente he<ABBR>r</ABBR> ner<ABBR>r</ABBR> to here more,</L>
<L>Thay wailed for defaute of mete. <MILESTONE N="1560"/></L>
<L>She rued on hem anoon̄ ful sore, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Moved to compassion,</NOTE></L>
<L>She thought, how she myght hem beste it gete.</L>
<L>She spake to her Maistras Maragounde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">she asks her governess Mara∣gound to help her in getting food for the prisoners.</NOTE></L>
<L>Howe she wolde the prisoneres fede. <MILESTONE N="1564"/></L>
<L>The develle of helle hir confounde,</L>
<L>She wolde not assente to þat dede, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Maragound refuses, and reminds Floripas of her father's command.</NOTE></L>
<L>But saide "Damesel, thou arte woode,</L>
<L>Thy Fadir did vs alle defende, <MILESTONE N="1568"/></L>
<L>Both mete and drinke and othere goode <MILESTONE N="39" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>That no man shulde hem thider sende."</L>
<L>Floripe by-thought hir on a gyle <NOTE PLACE="marg">Floripas, thinking of a trick, called to her governess to come to a window and</NOTE></L>
<L>And cleped Maragounde anoon rigħt, <MILESTONE N="1572"/></L>
<L>To the wyndowe to come a while</L>
<L>And se ther a wonder syght:</L>
<L>"Loke oute" she saide "and see a fer<ABBR>r</ABBR></L>
<L><PB N="46" REF="117"/>
The Porpais pley as thay were wode." <MILESTONE N="1576"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">see the porpoises sporting beneath. Maragound looking out, is pushed into the flood.</NOTE></L>
<L>Maragounde lokede oute, Floripe come ne<ABBR>r</ABBR></L>
<L>And shofed hire oute in to the flode.</L>
<L>"Go there" she saide "the devel the spede!</L>
<L>My counsail shaltowe never biwry. <MILESTONE N="1580"/></L>
<L>Who so wole not helpe a man̄ at nede,</L>
<L>On evel deth mote he dye!"</L>
<L>She toke witħ hire maidyns two,</L>
<L>To Britomayne she wente hir waye <MILESTONE N="1584"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Floripas asks Bretomayn to let her see the prisoners.</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide to him, she moste go</L>
<L>To viseten̄ the prisoneris that daye,</L>
<L>And saide "sir, for alle loues,</L>
<L>Lete me thy prisoneres seen̄. <MILESTONE N="1588"/></L>
<L>I wole the gife botħ goolde and gloues,</L>
<L>And counsail shalle it been̄."</L>
<L>Brytomayne that Iaylor kene</L>
<L>Answered to hir sone agayne <MILESTONE N="1592"/></L>
<L>And saide "Damesel, so mote I then̄,</L>
<L>Than̄ were I worthy to be slayn̄.</L>
<L>Hath not youre Fader charged me,</L>
<L>To kepe hem from̄ every wyght? <MILESTONE N="1596"/></L>
<L>And yet ye wole these trayto<HI REND="italic">ur</HI>s see?</L>
<L>I wole goo telle him Anoon̄ right." <NOTE PLACE="marg">The gaoler threatened to complain to her father,</NOTE></L>
<L>He gan to turne him anone for to go,</L>
<L>To make a playnte on Floripas. <MILESTONE N="1600"/></L>
<L>She sued him as faste as she myghte go, <NOTE PLACE="marg">but Floripas,</NOTE></L>
<L>For to gif him harde grace.</L>
<L>With the keye cloge, þat she caugħt, <NOTE PLACE="marg">having seized his key-clog,</NOTE></L>
<L>Witħ goode wille she maute <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'mente.'</NOTE> than, <MILESTONE N="1604"/></L>
<L>Such a stroke she hym the<ABBR>r</ABBR> raught, <NOTE PLACE="marg">dashed out his brains.</NOTE></L>
<L>The brayne sterte oute of his hede þan̄.</L>
<L>To hire Fader forth she gotħ <NOTE PLACE="marg">She then went to tell her father,</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "Sire, I telle you here, <MILESTONE N="1608"/> <MILESTONE N="40" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>I saugħ a sight, that was me lotħ, <NOTE PLACE="marg">she had surprised the gaoler feeding the prisoners and</NOTE></L>
<L>Howe the fals Iailo<HI REND="italic">ur</HI> fedde your prisone<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L><PB N="47" REF="118"/>
And how the coven<HI REND="italic">au</HI>nte made was, <NOTE PLACE="marg">promising to deliver them;</NOTE></L>
<L>Whan thai shulde delyu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ed be; <MILESTONE N="1612"/></L>
<L>Wherefore I slougħ him witħ a mace. <NOTE PLACE="marg">wherefore she had slain him.</NOTE></L>
<L>Dere Fadir, forgif it me!"</L>
<L>"My doghtir dere, that arte so free, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'trew.'</NOTE></L>
<L>The warde of hem now gif I the. <MILESTONE N="1616"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">The Soudan gives the prisoners into her guard.</NOTE></L>
<L>Loke, here sorowe be evere newe,</L>
<L>Tille that Ferumbras delyu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ed be."</L>
<L>She thanked her Fadere fele sithe</L>
<L>And toke her maydyns, and forth she gotħ, <MILESTONE N="1620"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">She now proceeded to the prison,</NOTE></L>
<L>To the prisone she hyed hire swytħ.</L>
<L>The prison̄ dore vp she dothe</L>
<L>And saide "sires, what be ye,</L>
<L>That make here this ruly moone? <MILESTONE N="1624"/></L>
<L>What yoū lakkitħ, tellyth me; <NOTE PLACE="marg">asked the prisoners what they wanted,</NOTE></L>
<L>For we be here nowe alle alone."</L>
<L>Tho spake Roulande with hevy chere</L>
<L>To Floripe, that was bothe gente and fr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> <MILESTONE N="1628"/></L>
<L>And saide "lo, we two caytyfes here</L>
<L>For defaute of mete dede moste be.</L>
<L>vj dayes be comyn̄ and goon̄,</L>
<L>Sith we were loked in prison̄ here, <MILESTONE N="1632"/></L>
<L>That mete nor drinke hade we noon̄</L>
<L>To comforte witħ oure hevy che<ABBR>r</ABBR>.</L>
<L>But woolde god of myght<HI REND="italic">es</HI> moost,</L>
<L>the Sowdon̄ wolde let vs oute goon̄, <MILESTONE N="1636"/></L>
<L>We to fight witħ alle his Ooste,</L>
<L>To be slayn̄ in feelde anoon̄.</L>
<L>To murthir men̄ for defaute of mete,</L>
<L>It is grete shame tille a kinge; <MILESTONE N="1640"/></L>
<L>For every man most nedes ete,</L>
<L>Or ellis may he do no thinge."</L>
<L>Tho saide Floripe with wordes mylde,</L>
<L>"I wolde fayne, ye were now here, <MILESTONE N="1644"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">and promised to protect them from any harm.</NOTE></L>
<L>From harme skatħ <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'harme &amp; skathe.'</NOTE> I wole you shelde,</L>
<L><PB N="48" REF="119"/>
And gife you mete with right gode che<ABBR>r</ABBR>."</L>
<L>A rope to hem she lete down̄ goon̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">She let down a rope,</NOTE></L>
<L>That aboven̄ was teyde faste. <MILESTONE N="1648"/> <MILESTONE N="41" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>She and hir maydyns drewe þer vppon̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and drew up both,</NOTE></L>
<L>Tille vp thay hadde hem at the last.</L>
<L>She led hem into here chambir dere, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and led them to her apartments.</NOTE></L>
<L>That arrayed for hem was rigħt wele, <MILESTONE N="1652"/></L>
<L>Both Roulande and Olyvere,</L>
<L>And gafe hem̄ there a right gode mele. <NOTE PLACE="marg">There they ate,</NOTE></L>
<L>And whan thay hadde eten̄ alle her fille,</L>
<L>A batħ for hem was redy there, <MILESTONE N="1656"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">took a bath,</NOTE></L>
<L>Ther-to thay went ful fayre and stille,</L>
<L>And aftyr to bedde with right gode che<ABBR>r</ABBR>. <NOTE PLACE="marg">and went to bed.</NOTE></L>
<L>Now Floripas chamber is here prisone,</L>
<L>Withouten̄ wetinge of the Sowdon̄; <MILESTONE N="1660"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">The Soudan knew nothing of his prisoners being in Floripas' chamber.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thai were ful mery in that Dongeon̄,</L>
<L>For of hem̄ wiste man̄ never oone.</L>
<L>Now lete we hem be and mery make,</L>
<L>Tille god sende hem gode delyueraunce. <MILESTONE N="1664"/></L>
<L>Aftir the tyme, þat thay were take,</L>
<L>What did Charles, the kinge of Fraunce, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Meanwhile Charlemagne</NOTE></L>
<L>Ther-of wole we speke nowe,</L>
<L>Howe he cleped forth Sir Gy <MILESTONE N="1668"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">tells Guy that he must go to the Soudan to</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "on my message shaltowe,</L>
<L>Therfore make the faste redy,</L>
<L>To bidde the Sowden̄ sende me my Nevewes botħ <NOTE PLACE="marg">demand the surrender of Roland and Oliver, and of the relies of Rome.</NOTE></L>
<L>And the Releqes also of Rome; <MILESTONE N="1672"/></L>
<L>Or I shal make him so wortħ,</L>
<L>He shałł not wete what to done.</L>
<L>And by þat god, þat hath me wroght,</L>
<L>I shal him leve Towre ner Town̄. <MILESTONE N="1676"/></L>
<L>This bargan̄ shal so dere be bought</L>
<L>In dispite of his god Mahoun̄."</L>
<L>DUke Neymes of Baue<ABBR>r</ABBR> vp stert than̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">Naymes of Bavaria repre∣sents that a messenger to the Soudan should</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "Sir, hastowe no mynde, <MILESTONE N="1680"/></L>
<L>How the cursed Sowdan̄ Laban</L>
<L><PB N="49" REF="120"/>
Alle messengeris doth he shende? <NOTE PLACE="marg">certainly be slain; and that they ought to be anxious not to lose any more besides Rouland and Oliver. Then said the</NOTE></L>
<L>Ye haue lost inowe, lese no mo</L>
<L>Onworthily Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR> and Roulande." <MILESTONE N="1684"/></L>
<L>"By god, and thou shalt with him go,</L>
<L>For al thy grete brode londe."</L>
<L>THo Ogere Danoys, þat worthy man̄, <MILESTONE N="42" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>"Sir" he saide "be not wrotħ! <MILESTONE N="1688"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">king, 'By god, thou shalt go with Guy.' Ogier the Dane remonstrates, but is ordered to go too.</NOTE></L>
<L>For he saitħ soutħ."—"go tho<ABBR>u</ABBR> than̄!</L>
<L>By Gode thou shalte, be tho<ABBR>u</ABBR> never so loth."</L>
<L>"A Sire" quod Bery Lardeneys,</L>
<L>"Tho<ABBR>u</ABBR> shalte hem se never more."— <MILESTONE N="1692"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">So are Thierry of Ardane</NOTE></L>
<L>"Go thou forth in this same rees,</L>
<L>Or it shalle the repente ful sore."</L>
<L>FOlk Baliante saide to the kinge, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and Folk Baliant,</NOTE></L>
<L>"Liste ye youre Barons to lese?"- <MILESTONE N="1696"/></L>
<L>"Certis, this is a wondir thinge!</L>
<L>Go thou also, tho<ABBR>u</ABBR> shalte not chese!"</L>
<L>A Leroyse rose vp anone <NOTE PLACE="marg">Aleroys</NOTE></L>
<L>And to the kinge þan gan̄ he speke <MILESTONE N="1700"/></L>
<L>And saide "what thinke ye, sir, to done?"—</L>
<L>"Dresse the forth witħ hem̄ eke!"</L>
<L>MIron of Brabane spake an worde <NOTE PLACE="marg">and Miron of Brabant.</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "Sir, thou maiste do þy wille. <MILESTONE N="1704"/></L>
<L>Knowist thou not that cruel lorde,</L>
<L>How he wole thy Barons spille?"—</L>
<L>"Trusse the forth eke, sir Dasaberde,</L>
<L>Or I shalle the sone make! <MILESTONE N="1708"/></L>
<L>For of all thinge thou arte aferde,</L>
<L>Yet arte tho<ABBR>u</ABBR> neyther hurte ner take."</L>
<L>BIsshope Turpyn̄ kneled adown̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">Bishop Turpin kneels down to implore the king's mercy, but he must go too,</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "lege lorde, mercy!" <MILESTONE N="1712"/></L>
<L>The kinge him swore by seynt Symon̄:</L>
<L>"Thou goist eke, make the in hast redye!"</L>
<L>BErnarde of Spruwse, þat worthy knygħt, <NOTE PLACE="marg">as well as Bernard of Spruwse</NOTE></L>
<L>Saide "sir, avyse yo<ABBR>u</ABBR> bette, <MILESTONE N="1716"/></L>
<L>Set not of youre Barons so ligħt,</L>
<L><PB N="50" REF="121"/>
Thou maiste haue nede to hem̄ yette."—</L>
<L>"Thou shalte goon̄ eke for alle thy boost,</L>
<L>Haue done and make the fast yare! <MILESTONE N="1720"/></L>
<L>Of my nede gyfe tho<ABBR>u</ABBR> no coost,</L>
<L>Ther-of haue thou right no care!"</L>
<L>BRye<ABBR>r</ABBR> of Mounteȝ, þat marqwyȝ bolde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and Brier of Mountdidier.</NOTE></L>
<L>Was not aferde to him to speke. <MILESTONE N="1724"/></L>
<L>To the kinge sharply he tolde,</L>
<L>His witte was not worth a leke: <MILESTONE N="43" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>"Woltowe for Angre thy Barons sende</L>
<L>To þat Tiraunte, þat alle men sleitħ? <MILESTONE N="1728"/></L>
<L>Or thou doist for þat ende,</L>
<L>To bringe thy xij peres to the detħ."</L>
<L>The kinge was wrotħ and swore in halle</L>
<L>By him, þat boght him witħ his blode: <MILESTONE N="1732"/></L>
<L>"On my messange shall ye gon̄ alle!</L>
<L>Be ye never so wrotħ or wode."</L>
<L>Thay toke here lefe and fortħ thay yede, <NOTE PLACE="marg">The knights take leave and start.</NOTE></L>
<L>It availed not agayne him to sayne. <MILESTONE N="1736"/></L>
<L>I pray, god gif hem gode spede!</L>
<L>Ful harde it was to comen̄ agayn̄.</L>
<L>NOwe let hem passe in goddis name,</L>
<L>And speke we of the Sowdon̄, <MILESTONE N="1740"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">The Soudan assembled his council.</NOTE></L>
<L>Howe he complayned him of his grame,</L>
<L>And what that he myght beste done.</L>
<L>"Sortybrau<HI REND="italic">n</HI>nce and Bronlande <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE>" seyde he, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Sortibrance and Brouland</NOTE></L>
<L>"Of counsail ye be fulle wyse. <MILESTONE N="1744"/></L>
<L>How shal I do to avenge me</L>
<L>Of kinge Charles, and in what wyse?</L>
<L>He brennyth my Toures and my Citees,</L>
<L>And Burges he levethe me never oon̄. <MILESTONE N="1748"/></L>
<L>He stroieth my men̄, my londe, my fees.</L>
<L>Thus shalle it not longe goon̄.</L>
<L>And yet me greveth most of alle,</L>
<L>He hath made Ferumbras renay his laye. <MILESTONE N="1752"/></L>
<L><PB N="51" REF="122"/>
Therfore my counselors I calle,</L>
<L>To remedy this, howe thay best maye.</L>
<L>For me were lever that he were slayn̄,</L>
<L>Thane he a Cristen̄ hounde shulde be, <MILESTONE N="1756"/></L>
<L>Or witħ Wolfes be rente and slayn̄,</L>
<L>By Mahounde mygħty of dignyte."</L>
<L>To answerde Sortybraunce and Broulande <NOTE PLACE="marg">advise him</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "gode counsaile we shal yo<ABBR>u</ABBR> gyfen̄, <MILESTONE N="1760"/></L>
<L>If thoue wilte do aftyr coven<HI REND="italic">au</HI>nte,</L>
<L>It shal yo<ABBR>u</ABBR> profit, while yo<ABBR>u</ABBR> lyven̄.</L>
<L>Take xij knightis of worthy dede <NOTE PLACE="marg">to send 12 knights, and to bid Charles</NOTE></L>
<L>And sende hem to Charles on message nowe. <MILESTONE N="1764"/></L>
<L>A-raye hem welle in roial wede,</L>
<L>For thȳ honou<ABBR>r</ABBR> and for thy prowe. <MILESTONE N="44" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Bidde Charles sende thy sone to the <NOTE PLACE="marg">to give up Ferumbras and to withdraw from his country.</NOTE></L>
<L>And voyde thy londe in alle haste, <MILESTONE N="1768"/></L>
<L>Or ellis thou shalt him honge on a tr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI></L>
<L>As hye, as any shippes maste."</L>
<L>"Nowe by Mahoude" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Laban,</L>
<L>"This counseil is both trewe and goode, <MILESTONE N="1772"/></L>
<L>I shalle him leve for no man̄</L>
<L>To parforme this, though he we<ABBR>r</ABBR> woode."</L>
<L>He did his lettris write in haste,</L>
<L>The knight<HI REND="italic">es</HI> were called to goo þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI>witħ, <MILESTONE N="1776"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">The knights are dispatched.</NOTE></L>
<L>That thay hyȝe hem̄ to Charles faste</L>
<L>And charke <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Sic in MS. Query—</HI>'char<HI REND="italic">g</HI>e.'</NOTE> hym̄ vppon̄ life and lithe.</L>
<L>Fortħ thai ride towarde Mantrible þan̄,</L>
<L>In a medowe, was fayre and grene, <MILESTONE N="1780"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Near Mantrible they meet with the Christian messengers.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thai mette witħ Charles messageris ten̄.</L>
<L>Duke Neymes axed hem̄, what thai wolde mene,</L>
<L>And saide "Lordynges, whens come ye? <NOTE PLACE="marg">Duke Naymes inquires whither they intend to go.</NOTE></L>
<L>And whider ye are mente, telle vs this tyde." <MILESTONE N="1784"/></L>
<L>"From̄ the worthy Sowdon̄" than̄ saide he,</L>
<L>"To Charles on message shalle we ride,</L>
<L><PB N="52" REF="123"/>
Euel tithyngg<HI REND="italic">es</HI> we shalle him telle,</L>
<L>Fro Laban, that is lorde of Spayne. <MILESTONE N="1788"/></L>
<L>Farewele, felowes, we may not dwelle."</L>
<L>"A-byde" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Gy "and turne agayne, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Having heard their message,</NOTE></L>
<L>We wole speke with yo<ABBR>u</ABBR>, er ye goon̄,</L>
<L>For we be messengeris of his. <MILESTONE N="1792"/></L>
<L>Ye shal aby everichone,</L>
<L>So God brynge me to blis."</L>
<L>Anoon̄ here swerdes oute thay brayde</L>
<L>And smoten̄ down̄ right al a-boute. <MILESTONE N="1796"/></L>
<L>Tille the hethen̄ were down̄ layde,</L>
<L>Thai reseyued many a sore cloute.</L>
<L>Thai smyten̄ of here hedes alle, <NOTE PLACE="marg">the delegates of Charles cut off their heads, which they take with them to present to the Soudan at Agremore.</NOTE></L>
<L>Eche man̄ toke one in his lappe. <MILESTONE N="1800"/></L>
<L>Fal what so euer byfalle,</L>
<L>To the Soudon̄ wole they trappe.</L>
<L>Tille thai come to Egremoure,</L>
<L>Thai stynte for no worldes thinge; <MILESTONE N="1804"/></L>
<L>Anone thai fonde the Sawdan̄ thore,</L>
<L>At his mete proudely sittynge, <MILESTONE N="45" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>And þat maide fai<ABBR>r</ABBR> Dame Floripas <NOTE PLACE="marg">The Soudan was just dining.</NOTE></L>
<L>And xiiij princes of grete price <MILESTONE N="1808"/></L>
<L>And kinge Lukafe<ABBR>r</ABBR> of Baldas,</L>
<L>Thas was both bolde, hardy and wyse.</L>
<L>Doughty Duke Neymes of Baue<ABBR>r</ABBR> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Naymes delivers his message:</NOTE></L>
<L>To the Sowdone his message tolde <MILESTONE N="1812"/></L>
<L>And saide "god, þat made heven̄ so cle<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">'God confound Laban and all his Saracens, and save Charles,</NOTE></L>
<L>He saue kinge Charles so bolde</L>
<L>And confounde Laban̄ and all his men̄,</L>
<L>That on Mahounde byleved, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'byleven.'</NOTE> <MILESTONE N="1816"/></L>
<L>And gife hem evel endinge! amen̄.</L>
<L>To morue, longe er it be even̄,</L>
<L>He co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>maundith the vppon̄ thy life <NOTE PLACE="marg">who commands thee to send back his two nephews and to restore the relics.'</NOTE></L>
<L>His Nevewes home to him sende, <MILESTONE N="1820"/></L>
<L>And the Religes <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'reliqes.'</NOTE> of Rome withoute strife;</L>
<L><PB N="53" REF="124"/>
And ellis getist thou an evel ende!</L>
<L>xij lurdeynes mette vs on the waye;</L>
<L>Thai saide, thay come streight fro the. <MILESTONE N="1824"/></L>
<L>Thai made it botħ stoute and gay;</L>
<L>Here hed<HI REND="italic">is</HI> here maistowe see. <NOTE PLACE="marg">They then produce the heads of the Soudan's messengers.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thai saide, thai wolde to Charles goon̄,</L>
<L>Evel tidingg<HI REND="italic">es</HI> him to telle. <MILESTONE N="1828"/></L>
<L>Loo here here heddis eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ychone,</L>
<L>Here soulis bene in helle."</L>
<L>"O" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Lavane "what may this be,</L>
<L>To suff<ABBR>r</ABBR> this amonge my knight<HI REND="italic">es</HI> alle? <MILESTONE N="1832"/></L>
<L>To be rebuked thus here of the</L>
<L>At mete in myn owen̄ halle!</L>
<L>To Mahounde myghty I make a vowe, <NOTE PLACE="marg">The Soudan vowed a vow that they should all ten be hanged as soon as he had finished his dinner.</NOTE></L>
<L>Ye shall be hanged alle ten, <MILESTONE N="1836"/></L>
<L>Anoon as I have eten̄ I-nowe,</L>
<L>In presence of alle my men̄."</L>
<L>Maide Floripas answered tho <NOTE PLACE="marg">But Floripas recommended him to put off his resolution, until a general council of his barons had determined on the best way of the liberation of Ferumbras.</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "my derworth Fadir de<ABBR>r</ABBR>! <MILESTONE N="1840"/></L>
<L>By my counsaile ye shal not so,</L>
<L>Tille ye haue your Barons alle in fe<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>That thai may se what is the best,</L>
<L>For to delyu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>e my brother Sir Ferumbras. <MILESTONE N="1844"/></L>
<L>And aftirward, if þat ye liste,</L>
<L>Ye may gife hem ful evel grace."</L>
<L>"Gramercy, doghter, thou saieste welle, <MILESTONE N="46" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Take hem alle into thy warde. <MILESTONE N="1848"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">The Soudan gives them into her guard.</NOTE></L>
<L>Do feter hem faste in Iren̄ and stele</L>
<L>And set hem in strayȝte garde.</L>
<L>Thus was I neuer rebukede er nowe;</L>
<L>Mahounde myghty gyfe hem̄ sorowe! <MILESTONE N="1852"/></L>
<L>Thay shalle be flayn and honged on a bowe,</L>
<L>Longe ere tyme <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'I dyne.' <HI REND="italic">See the note.</HI></NOTE> to morowe."</L>
<L>Florip̄ toke these messangeris <NOTE PLACE="marg">Floripas leads the knights into her tower, where</NOTE></L>
<L>And ladde hem vp in-to here tou<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <MILESTONE N="1856"/></L>
<L><PB N="54" REF="125"/>
There thai founde two of here feris. <NOTE PLACE="marg">they were glad to find Roland and Oliver.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thay thanked thereof god of honoure.</L>
<L>Tho sayde Duke Neymys of Baue<ABBR>r</ABBR>:</L>
<L>"Gladde men we be nowe here, <MILESTONE N="1860"/></L>
<L>To fynde Roulande and Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR></L>
<L>In helthe of bodye and of goode che<ABBR>r</ABBR>."</L>
<L>Thai kissed eche other with herte gladde</L>
<L>And thanked god of his grace; <MILESTONE N="1864"/></L>
<L>And eche toolde othir, howe thay sped hadde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">They told each other how they had fared.</NOTE></L>
<L>And howe thay come in-to that place</L>
<L>By helpe of mayde Florip̄ hire self,</L>
<L>"God kepe hir in honoure! <MILESTONE N="1868"/></L>
<L>For thus hath she brought vs hider alle twelfe,</L>
<L>To dwelle in hir owen̄ boure."</L>
<L>Tho thay wessh and wente to mete, <NOTE PLACE="marg">After washing,</NOTE></L>
<L>And were served welle and fyne <MILESTONE N="1872"/></L>
<L>Of suche goode, as she myght gete,</L>
<L>Of Venyson̄, brede and gode wyne. <NOTE PLACE="marg">they dined off venison, bread and wine,</NOTE></L>
<L>There thai were gladde and wel at ease;</L>
<L>The Soudon̄ ne wist it noght. <MILESTONE N="1876"/></L>
<L>Aftyr thay slepe and toke her ese, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and then went to sleep.</NOTE></L>
<L>Of no man than̄ thay ne roght.</L>
<L>On the morowe Florip̄, that mayde fre, <NOTE PLACE="marg">The following day, Floripas asks Naymes his name,</NOTE></L>
<L>To Duke Neymes spake in game: <MILESTONE N="1880"/></L>
<L>"Sir gentil knigħt," tho saide she,</L>
<L>"Telle me, what is your name."</L>
<L>"Whi axe ye, my lady dere,</L>
<L>My name here to knowe alle?" <MILESTONE N="1884"/></L>
<L>"For he <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Sic in MS. Read:</HI> 'ye.'</NOTE> spake with so bolde chere</L>
<L>To my Fadir yestirdaye in his halle. <NOTE PLACE="marg">and enquires after Guy of Burgundy,</NOTE></L>
<L>Be not ye the Duke of Burgoyne, sir Gȳ,</L>
<L>Nevewe unto the king<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Charles so fre?" <MILESTONE N="1888"/> <MILESTONE N="47" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>"Noe, certes, lady, it is not I,</L>
<L>It is yondir knight, þat ye may see."</L>
<L>"A, him have I loved many a day; <NOTE PLACE="marg">whom she had loved for a long time, and for</NOTE></L>
<L><PB N="55" REF="126"/>
And yet knowe I him noght. <MILESTONE N="1892"/></L>
<L>For his loue I do alle that I maye, <NOTE PLACE="marg">whom she would do all she could for their benefit,</NOTE></L>
<L>To chere yoū witħ dede and thought.</L>
<L>For his love wille I cristenede be <NOTE PLACE="marg">and would be baptised,</NOTE></L>
<L>And lefe Mahoundes laye. <MILESTONE N="1896"/></L>
<L>Spekith to him nowe for me,</L>
<L>As I yoū truste maye;</L>
<L>And but he wole gr<HI REND="italic">a</HI>unte me his loue, <NOTE PLACE="marg">if he would agree to love her in return.</NOTE></L>
<L>Of yoū askape shalle none here. <MILESTONE N="1900"/></L>
<L>By him, þat is almyghty aboue,</L>
<L>Ye shalle abye it ellis ful dere."</L>
<L>Tho wente Duke Neymes to Sir Gye</L>
<L>And saide "This ladye lovetħ the, <MILESTONE N="1904"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Naymes tells Guy</NOTE></L>
<L>For thy loue she maketħ us alle merye,</L>
<L>And Baptizede wole she be.</L>
<L>Ye shalle hir take to your wedded wife, <NOTE PLACE="marg">to take her for his wife,</NOTE></L>
<L>For alle vs she may saue." <MILESTONE N="1908"/></L>
<L>"By God" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Gye "þat gafe me life, <NOTE PLACE="marg">but Guy refuses,</NOTE></L>
<L>Hire wole I never haue,</L>
<L>Wyle I neuer take hire ner no woman̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">as he never will take a wife, unless she be given him by Charles.</NOTE></L>
<L>But Charles the kinge hir me gife. <MILESTONE N="1912"/></L>
<L>I hight him, as I was trewe man̄,</L>
<L>To holden̄ it, while I lyve."</L>
<L>Tho spake Roulande and Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Rouland and Oliver persuaded him,</NOTE></L>
<L>Certyfyinge him of he<ABBR>r</ABBR> myschefe, <MILESTONE N="1916"/></L>
<L>Tellinge him of the parelles, þ<HI REND="italic">a</HI>t þay in we<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>For to take this lady to his wedded wife.</L>
<L>"But thoū helpe in this nede,</L>
<L>We be here in grete doute. <MILESTONE N="1920"/></L>
<L>Almyghty god shalle quyte thy mede,</L>
<L>Elles come we nevere he<HI REND="italic">n</HI>nys oute."</L>
<L>Thus thay treted him to and fro;</L>
<L>At the laste he sayde, he wolde. <MILESTONE N="1924"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">so that he at last consented.</NOTE></L>
<L>Floripas thay cleped fortħ tho;</L>
<L>And brought fourth a Cuppe of golde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Floripas, holding a golden cup of wine,</NOTE></L>
<L>Ful of noble myghty wyne,</L>
<L><PB N="56" REF="127"/>
And saide "my loue and my lorde, <MILESTONE N="1928"/> <MILESTONE N="48" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Myn herte, my body, my goode is thyn̄,"</L>
<L>And kissed him witħ that worde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">kissed him,</NOTE></L>
<L>And "sir" she saide "drinke to me, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and requested him to drink to her after the fashion of her country.</NOTE></L>
<L>As the Gyse is of my londe; <MILESTONE N="1932"/></L>
<L>And I shalle drinke agayn̄ to the,</L>
<L>As to my worthy hosbonde." <NOTE PLACE="marg">She also drinks to him.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thay clipped and kissed botħ in fere</L>
<L>And made grete Joye and game, <MILESTONE N="1936"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">They all make merry.</NOTE></L>
<L>And so did alle, that were the<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>Thai made ful mery alle in same.</L>
<L>Tho spake Floripas to the Barons boolde</L>
<L>And saide "I haue armu<ABBR>r</ABBR> I-nowe; <MILESTONE N="1940"/></L>
<L>Therfore I tel yoū, what I wolde,</L>
<L>And þat ye dide for your prowe.</L>
<L>To morue, whan̄ my Fadir is at his soupe<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">For the following day</NOTE></L>
<L>Ye shalle come in alle attonys; <MILESTONE N="1944"/></L>
<L>Loke ye spare for no fere,</L>
<L>Sle down̄ and breke botħ bake and bones;</L>
<L>Kithe yoū knightis of hardynesse!</L>
<L>Ther is none helpe, but in this wyse, <MILESTONE N="1948"/></L>
<L>Then moste ye shewen̄ youre prowes,</L>
<L>And wynne this Castel in this guyse."</L>
<L>Thai sayden alle, it was welle saide,</L>
<L>And gladde thay were of this counsaile. <MILESTONE N="1952"/></L>
<L>Here armu<ABBR>r</ABBR> was fortħ layde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">they all prepare to assail the Soudan at supper.</NOTE></L>
<L>At souper the Sowdon̄ to assaile.</L>
<L>Kinge Lucafere prayde the Sawdon̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Lukafer comes to the Soudan and asks leave to see the prisoners, in order to know the manner of their detention.</NOTE></L>
<L>That he wolde gif him lysence, <MILESTONE N="1956"/></L>
<L>To the prisoners for to goon̄,</L>
<L>To see the maner of her presence.</L>
<L>He gafe him lefe, and forth he wente</L>
<L>Vp vnto Floripas Toure. <MILESTONE N="1960"/></L>
<L>To asspie the maner was his enten<ABBR>t</ABBR>,</L>
<L>Hem̄ to accuse agayne honoure.</L>
<L>Whan̄ he come, he founde the dore fast I-stoke, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Finding the door locked, he burst it</NOTE></L>
<L><PB N="57" REF="128"/>
He smote there-on with his fist, <MILESTONE N="1964"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">open with a blow of his fist.</NOTE></L>
<L>That the bar<ABBR>r</ABBR> began̄ to broke.</L>
<L>To make debate, wel him list.</L>
<L>"Who artowe" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Floripas <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">These two lines are written as one in the MS.</NOTE></L>
<L>"Þ<HI REND="italic">a</HI>t maketh he<ABBR>r</ABBR> sucħ araye <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">These two lines are written as one in the MS.</NOTE>?" <MILESTONE N="1968"/></L>
<L>"I am kinge Lucafere of Baldas, <MILESTONE N="49" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>The Sowdon̄ sente me hidir in faye;</L>
<L>To seen̄ his prisoneris is my desire</L>
<L>And speke with hem everychon̄, <MILESTONE N="1972"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">He told them that he was come to speak to them,</NOTE></L>
<L>To talke with hem by the fire</L>
<L>And speke of dedis of Armes amonge."</L>
<L>Tho saide Duke Neymes "welcome be ye</L>
<L>To us prisoners here! <MILESTONE N="1976"/></L>
<L>What is your wille, nowe telle ye;</L>
<L>For we be men̄ of feble chere."</L>
<L>"I woolde wete of Charles the kinge, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and to enquire after Charlemagne.</NOTE></L>
<L>What man̄ he is in his contre, <MILESTONE N="1980"/></L>
<L>And what meyne he hatħ, and of what thinge</L>
<L>He rekyneth moost his dignyte."</L>
<L>Duke Neymes saide "an Emp<HI REND="italic">er</HI>oure <NOTE PLACE="marg">Duke Naymes answers.</NOTE></L>
<L>And kinge he is of many a londe, <MILESTONE N="1984"/></L>
<L>Of Citeis, Castels, and many a Toure,</L>
<L>Dukes, Erles, Barons bowynge to his honde."</L>
<L>"But saye me, felowe, what is your vse,</L>
<L>To do in cont<ABBR>r</ABBR> aftyr the none. <MILESTONE N="1988"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">He then asks what amusements they have after dinner.</NOTE></L>
<L>And what is the custome of your hous,</L>
<L>Tille men̄ to souper shalle gone?"</L>
<L>"Sir, so<HI REND="italic">m</HI>me men̄ iouste <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">MS. iuste.</NOTE> witħ spe<ABBR>r</ABBR> and shelde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Naymes says, 'Some joust, some sing, some play at chess.'</NOTE></L>
<L>And so<HI REND="italic">m</HI>me men̄ Carol and singe gode songes, <MILESTONE N="1992"/></L>
<L>Some shote with dartis in the feelde,</L>
<L>And so<HI REND="italic">m</HI>me play at Chesse amonge."</L>
<L>"Ye bene but foulis of gode dissporte;</L>
<L>I wole yoū tech a newe play. <MILESTONE N="1996"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">'I will teach you a new game,' says Lukafer.</NOTE></L>
<L>Sitte down̄ here by one assorte,</L>
<L><PB N="58" REF="129"/>
And bett<HI REND="italic">er</HI> myrthe never ye saye."</L>
<L>He teyde a tredde on a pole <NOTE PLACE="marg">With a thread he fastened a needle on a pole and put a burning coal upon it.</NOTE></L>
<L>With an nedil ther-on I-fest, <MILESTONE N="2000"/></L>
<L>And ther vppon̄ a qwi<ABBR>k</ABBR> cole.</L>
<L>He bade every man blowe his blast.</L>
<L>Duke Neymes hade a long berde,</L>
<L>Kinge Lucafe<ABBR>r</ABBR> blewe even̄ to hym̄, <MILESTONE N="2004"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">He blew it at Naymes's beard and burnt it.</NOTE></L>
<L>That game hade he never before lered.</L>
<L>He brent the he<ABBR>r</ABBR> of Neymes berde to the skyne.</L>
<L>Duke Neymes than̄ gan wex wrotħ, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Naymes waxed wroth, and</NOTE></L>
<L>For he hade brente his berde so white <MILESTONE N="2008"/> <MILESTONE N="50" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>To the Chymneye forth he goth <NOTE PLACE="marg">snatching a burning brand from the fire</NOTE></L>
<L>And caught a bronde him witħ to smyte.</L>
<L>Witħ a goode wille he him smote, <NOTE PLACE="marg">he smites at Lukafer and throws him into the fire,</NOTE></L>
<L>That both his eyen̄ bresten̄ oute. <MILESTONE N="2012"/></L>
<L>He caste him in the fire al hote;</L>
<L>For sothe he hadde a rigħt gode cloute.</L>
<L>And with a fyre forke he helde him doune,</L>
<L>Tille he were rosted to colis ilkadele. <MILESTONE N="2016"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">where he was roasted to charcoal.</NOTE></L>
<L>His soule hade his god Mahoun̄.</L>
<L>Florip̄ bade him̄ warme him wele. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Floripas applauds this,</NOTE></L>
<L>"Sires" tho saide Floripas,</L>
<L>"Entendith nowe al to me! <MILESTONE N="2020"/></L>
<L>This Lucafe<ABBR>r</ABBR> of Baldas</L>
<L>Was a lorde of grete mayne.</L>
<L>My Fadir hade him eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> yn che<ABBR>r</ABBR> <NOTE PLACE="marg">but points out their danger,</NOTE></L>
<L>I telle you for sothe everydele, <MILESTONE N="2024"/></L>
<L>He wolde anoon̄ aftyr him enque<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>And therefore loke, ye arme you wełł!" <NOTE PLACE="marg">and advises them to arm.</NOTE></L>
<L>Florip wente in, as the maner was,</L>
<L>To here Fadir at soup<HI REND="italic">er</HI> tyme. <MILESTONE N="2028"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">At supper time she goes to her father.</NOTE></L>
<L>No man spake worde of kinge Baldas,</L>
<L>Ner no man knewe of his sharp pyne.</L>
<L>The xij peris armed hem wel and fyne</L>
<L>With swerdes drawe and eg<ABBR>r</ABBR> chere. <MILESTONE N="2032"/></L>
<L>While they mery <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Miswritten for</HI> 'were'?</NOTE> drinkyn<ABBR>g</ABBR> the wyne</L>
<L><PB N="59" REF="130"/>
And sittinge alle at here soupe<ABBR>r</ABBR>. <NOTE PLACE="marg">As they were sitting at table, the twelve peers rushed in and slew all whom they met.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thai reheted the Sowdon̄ and his Barons alle</L>
<L>And maden̄ orders wondir fast, <MILESTONE N="2036"/></L>
<L>Thai slowe down̄ alle, þat were in the halle,</L>
<L>And made hem wondirly sore a-gast.</L>
<L>Olyvere egerly sued Laban̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">Laban, pursued by Oliver,</NOTE></L>
<L>With swerd I-drawe in his honde. <MILESTONE N="2040"/></L>
<L>Oute at the wyndowe lepte he þan̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">jumps out of a window on to the sea-shore and escaped</NOTE></L>
<L>Vppon̄ the salte see stronde, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">MS.</HI> strowde.</NOTE></L>
<L>And he skaped away from̄ hime,</L>
<L>But woo was he þerfore, <MILESTONE N="2044"/></L>
<L>That he went awaye witħ lym̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">without injury.</NOTE></L>
<L>To worche hem sorowe more.</L>
<L>Roulande than̄ came rennynge</L>
<L>And axed, where was Laban. <MILESTONE N="2048"/></L>
<L>Olyuere answerede moornynge <MILESTONE N="51" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>And saide, howe he was agoon̄.</L>
<L>Tho thai voided the Court<HI REND="italic">es</HI> at the last <NOTE PLACE="marg">They killed all in the castle,</NOTE></L>
<L>And slowen̄ tho, that wolde a-byde, <MILESTONE N="2052"/></L>
<L>And drewe the brigge and teyed it fast, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and then drew up the bridges and shut the gates.</NOTE></L>
<L>And shitte the gatis, that were so wyde.</L>
<L>Laban, that by the ebbe escapede,</L>
<L>Of harde, er he come to londe, <MILESTONE N="2056"/></L>
<L>He alle astonyed and a-mapide, <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'a-<HI REND="italic">w</HI>apide.'</NOTE></L>
<L>For sorowe he wronge botħ his honde</L>
<L>And made a vowe to Mahounde of myght, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Laban vowed a vow</NOTE></L>
<L>He wolde that Cite wynne <MILESTONE N="2060"/></L>
<L>And never go thens by day nor nyght,</L>
<L>For foo, for frende, ner for kynne.</L>
<L>"And tho traytouris will I do honge, <NOTE PLACE="marg">that he would hang them all</NOTE></L>
<L>On a Galowes hye with-oute the gate; <MILESTONE N="2064"/></L>
<L>And my Doghter, þat hore stronge, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and burn his daughter.</NOTE></L>
<L>I-brente shal be there-ate.</L>
<L>To mauntryble he gan sende anoon̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">He sent to Mantrible for troops and</NOTE></L>
<L>Aftir men and tentis goode, <MILESTONE N="2068"/></L>
<L><PB N="60" REF="131"/>
And Engynes to throwe witħ stoon̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">engines,</NOTE></L>
<L>And goode armu<ABBR>r</ABBR> many foolde.</L>
<L>The sege he did leyen a-bowte <NOTE PLACE="marg">and besieged Agremore.</NOTE></L>
<L>On every side of that Cite. <MILESTONE N="2072"/></L>
<L>To wallis with Engynes thai gan rowte,</L>
<L>To breke the Toures so fre.</L>
<L>Tho saide Florip̄, "lordingg<HI REND="italic">es</HI> goode, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Floripas recom∣mends the peers</NOTE></L>
<L>Ye bene biseged in this toure, <MILESTONE N="2076"/></L>
<L>As ye bene wight of mayne and moode,</L>
<L>Proveth here to saue youre honou<ABBR>r</ABBR>.</L>
<L>The toure is stronge, drede yoū nought,</L>
<L>And vitayle we have plente. <MILESTONE N="2080"/></L>
<L>Charles wole not leve yoū vnsougħt;</L>
<L>Truste ye welle alle to me.</L>
<L>Therefore go we soupe and make merye, <NOTE PLACE="marg">to enjoy them∣selves.</NOTE></L>
<L>And takith ye alle your ease; <MILESTONE N="2084"/></L>
<L>And xxx<SUP>ti</SUP> maydens lo here of Assyne, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'Assye.'</NOTE></L>
<L>The fayrest of hem ye chese.</L>
<L>Take your sporte, and kith yoū knyght<HI REND="italic">es,</HI></L>
<L>Whan ye shalle haue to done; <MILESTONE N="2088"/></L>
<L>For to morowe, when the day is light, <MILESTONE N="52" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Ye mooste to the wallis goon̄</L>
<L>And defende this place witħ caste of stoon̄</L>
<L>And with shotte of quarelles and darte. <MILESTONE N="2092"/></L>
<L>My maydyns and I shałł bringe goode wone,</L>
<L>So eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>yche of us shalle bere hir parte."</L>
<L>On morowe the Sowdon̄ made assaute <NOTE PLACE="marg">In the morning the soudan attacks the castle,</NOTE></L>
<L>To hem, that were witħ-Inne, <MILESTONE N="2096"/></L>
<L>And certes in hem was no defaute,</L>
<L>For of hem̄ myght thay nought wynne.</L>
<L>Here shotte, here cast was so harde,</L>
<L>Thay durste not nyȝhe the walle. <MILESTONE N="2100"/></L>
<L>Thay drowen̄ hem bakwarde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">but is repulsed.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thay were beten̄ over alle.</L>
<L>King Laban̄ turnede to his tent<HI REND="italic">es</HI> agayn̄,</L>
<L><PB N="61" REF="132"/>
He was nere wode for tene, <MILESTONE N="2104"/></L>
<L>He cryede to Mahounde and Apolyne <NOTE PLACE="marg">He accuses his gods of sleepiness, and shakes them to wake up.</NOTE></L>
<L>And to Termagaunte, þat was so kene,</L>
<L>And saide "ye goddes, ye slepe to longe,</L>
<L>Awake and helpe me nowe, <MILESTONE N="2108"/></L>
<L>Or ellis I may singe of sorowe a songe,</L>
<L>And of mournynge right I-nowe.</L>
<L>Wete ye not wele, that my tresoure</L>
<L>Is alle witħ-inne the walle? <MILESTONE N="2112"/></L>
<L>Helpe me nowe, I saye therfore,</L>
<L>Or ellis I forsake yoū alle."</L>
<L>He made grete lamentacion̄,</L>
<L>His goddis byganne to shake. <MILESTONE N="2116"/></L>
<L>Ye that comfortede his meditacion̄,</L>
<L>Supposinge thay didde awake.</L>
<L>He cleped Brenlande to aske counsaile,</L>
<L>What was beste to done, <MILESTONE N="2120"/></L>
<L>And what thinge myght him̄ moste avayle,</L>
<L>To wynne the Cite sone.</L>
<L>"Thou wotist welle, þat alle my tresou<ABBR>r</ABBR></L>
<L>Is there in here kepinge, <MILESTONE N="2124"/></L>
<L>And my doughter, þat stronge hore,</L>
<L>God yif her evelle endyn<ABBR>g</ABBR>!" <MILESTONE N="53" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>"Sir" he saide "ye knowe welle, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Brouland tells him, as the castle is strong and well stored with pro∣visions, the peers will hold it very long;</NOTE></L>
<L>That Toure is wondir stronge. <MILESTONE N="2128"/></L>
<L>While þay haue vitayle to mele,</L>
<L>Kepen̄ it thay wole fulle longe.</L>
<L>Sende to Mauntreble, you<ABBR>r</ABBR> cheif Cite,</L>
<L>That is the keye of this londe, <MILESTONE N="2132"/></L>
<L>That non̄ passe, where it so be,</L>
<L>With-oute youre speciall sonde,</L>
<L>To Alagolofu<ABBR>r</ABBR>, þat geaunte stronge, <NOTE PLACE="marg">but if he would send orders to Alagolafre, the bridge-keeper at Mantrible, not to allow any one to pass without leave,</NOTE></L>
<L>That is wardeyne of þat pas, <MILESTONE N="2136"/></L>
<L>That no man passe that brigge alonge,</L>
<L>But he have special grace.</L>
<L>So shalle not Charles witħ his meyne</L>
<L><PB N="62" REF="133"/>
Reskowe than̄ Agramoure. <MILESTONE N="2140"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">they would get no assistance from Charles, and die from hunger.</NOTE></L>
<L>Than̄ thay shalle enfamyched be,</L>
<L>That shalle hem rewe ful sore."—</L>
<L>"Mahoundis blessynge have thoū and myne,</L>
<L>Sortybraunce, for thy rede."— <MILESTONE N="2144"/></L>
<L>"Espyarde, messange<ABBR>r</ABBR> myne, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Espiard is despatched to Mantrible,</NOTE></L>
<L>In haste thou most the spede</L>
<L>To my Cite Mavntreble,</L>
<L>To do my message there, <MILESTONE N="2148"/></L>
<L>To Alogolof<ABBR>r</ABBR>, þat giaunte orrible.</L>
<L>Bydde him his charge wele lere,</L>
<L>And tel him, howe that the last daye</L>
<L>Ten fals trayto<HI REND="italic">ur</HI>s of Fraunce <MILESTONE N="2152"/></L>
<L>Passed by that same waye</L>
<L>By his defaute witħ myschaunce,</L>
<L>Charginge him vppon̄ his hede to lese,</L>
<L>That no man by the brigge, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> <MILESTONE N="2156"/></L>
<L>Be it rayne, snowe or freze,</L>
<L>But he his heede down̄ ligge."</L>
<L>Espiarde spedde him in his waye,</L>
<L>Tille he to Mauntrible came, <MILESTONE N="2160"/></L>
<L>To seke the geaunte, ther he laye</L>
<L>On the banke bysyde the Dame,</L>
<L>And saide "the worthy Sowdon̄,</L>
<L>That of alle Spayn̄ is lorde and si<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <MILESTONE N="2164"/></L>
<L>Vppon̄ thy life co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>maundeth the anoon̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and commands the giant</NOTE></L>
<L>To deserue bett<HI REND="italic">er</HI> thyn hire.</L>
<L>The laste day thoū letist here passe</L>
<L>Ten trattoures of douse Fraunce. <MILESTONE N="2168"/></L>
<L>God giffe the evel grace,</L>
<L>And hem̄ also moche myschaunce!</L>
<L>He charged the vppon̄ life and detħ,</L>
<L>To kepe this place sikerlye; <MILESTONE N="2172"/></L>
<L>While in thy body lastetħ the bretħ,</L>
<L>Lette noon̄ enemye passe the<ABBR>r</ABBR>-bye." <NOTE PLACE="marg">not to suffer any one to pass the bridge.</NOTE></L>
<L><PB N="63" REF="134"/>
Alagolofur rolled his yen̄</L>
<L>And smote with his axe on̄ the stone <MILESTONE N="2176"/></L>
<L>And swore by Termag<HI REND="italic">a</HI>unte and Apolyne,</L>
<L>That ther-by shulde passe<HI REND="italic">n</HI> never one,</L>
<L>But if he smote of his hede,</L>
<L>And brought it to his lorde Laban̄, <MILESTONE N="2180"/></L>
<L>He wolde never ete no brede,</L>
<L>Nere never loke more on man̄.</L>
<L>xxiiij<SUP>ti</SUP> Cheynes he didde ou<HI REND="italic">er</HI>-drawe, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Alagolafre drew 24 chains across the bridge.</NOTE></L>
<L>That noo man passe mygħt, <MILESTONE N="2184"/></L>
<L>Neyther for loue nere for awe,</L>
<L>No tyme by daye, nere by nyghte.</L>
<L>"Go, telle my lorde, I shalle it kepe;</L>
<L>On payne of my grete heede <MILESTONE N="2188"/></L>
<L>Shalle ther no man̄ goo ner crepe,</L>
<L>But he be take or dede."</L>
<L>This geaunte hade a body longe</L>
<L>And hede, like an libarde. <MILESTONE N="2192"/></L>
<L>Ther-to he was devely stronge,</L>
<L>His skynne was blake and harde.</L>
<L>Of Ethiope he was bore,</L>
<L>Of the kinde of Ascopartes. <MILESTONE N="2196"/></L>
<L>He hade tuskes, like a bore,</L>
<L>An hede, like a liberde.</L>
<L>Laban nolde not forgete <NOTE PLACE="marg">The soudan assaults the castle again,</NOTE></L>
<L>The saute to renewe, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">These two lines are written as one in the MS.</NOTE> <MILESTONE N="2200"/></L>
<L>To wynne the Toure, he wolde not lete.</L>
<L>Here trumpes lowde thay blewe.</L>
<L>Every man wente to the walle,</L>
<L>With pikeys or witħ bowe. <MILESTONE N="2204"/> <MILESTONE N="55" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Thai made assaute generalle,</L>
<L>The walles downe to throwe.</L>
<L>But thay witħ-inne bare hem̄ soo, <NOTE PLACE="marg">but the 12 peers slay 300 Saracens.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thay slowe of the Saresyns iij hundre<ABBR>d</ABBR>. <MILESTONE N="2208"/></L>
<L>Thay wroghten̄ hem both care and woo,</L>
<L><PB N="64" REF="135"/>
Vppon̄ her fightinge thay wondride.</L>
<L>Tho cryed Laban̄ to hem on hye,</L>
<L>"Trayto<HI REND="italic">u</HI>rs, yelde yoū to me, <MILESTONE N="2212"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Laban threatens to hang them, and utters impreca∣tions</NOTE></L>
<L>Ye shall be hongede els by and bye</L>
<L>Vppon̄ an hye Galowe tree."</L>
<L>Tho spake Florip̄ to the Sowdon̄</L>
<L>And sayde "thou fals tyraunte, <MILESTONE N="2216"/></L>
<L>Were Charles come, thy pride we<ABBR>r</ABBR> done</L>
<L>Nowe, cursede myscreaunte. <NOTE PLACE="marg">against Floripas, who returns them.</NOTE></L>
<L>Alas! that thou ascapediste soo</L>
<L>By the wyndowe vppon̄ the stronde. <MILESTONE N="2220"/></L>
<L>That thy ne<ABBR>k</ABBR> hade broke a-twoo!</L>
<L>God sende the shame and shonde!"—</L>
<L>"A! stronge hore, god gife the sorowe!</L>
<L>Tho[u] venemouse serpente. <MILESTONE N="2224"/></L>
<L>Withe wilde horses <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> thoū shalt be drawe to morowe,</L>
<L>And on this hille be brente,</L>
<L>That al men may be wa<ABBR>r</ABBR> by the,</L>
<L>That cursed bene of kynde. <MILESTONE N="2228"/></L>
<L>And thy love shalle honged be,</L>
<L>His hondes bou<HI REND="italic">n</HI>de him byhynde."</L>
<L>He called forth Mavon̄, his Engynou<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">The soudan calls for Mavon, his engineer, and orders him to direct a mangonel against the walls.</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "I charge the, <MILESTONE N="2232"/></L>
<L>To throwe a magnelle to yon tou<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>And breke it downe on thre."</L>
<L>Mavon set vp his engyne <NOTE PLACE="marg">Mavon knocked down a piece of the battlements.</NOTE></L>
<L>With a stoon̄ of .vj. C wigħt, <MILESTONE N="2236"/></L>
<L>That wente as even̄ as eny lyne,</L>
<L>And smote a cornell down̄ right.</L>
<L>Woo was Roulande and Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Roland and Oliver lament;</NOTE></L>
<L>That þat myschief was be-falle, <MILESTONE N="2240"/></L>
<L>And so were alle the xij peres;</L>
<L>But Florip̄ than̄ comforte hem alle: <NOTE PLACE="marg">they are com∣forted by Floripas.</NOTE></L>
<L>"Sires" she saide "beitħ of goode chere!</L>
<L>This Toure is stronge I-nowe. <MILESTONE N="2244"/></L>
<L><PB N="65" REF="136"/>
He may cast twies or thries or he hit ayen þ<HI REND="italic">er,</HI> <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> <MILESTONE N="56" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>For sothe I telle it yoū.</L>
<L>Marsedage, the roialle kinge,</L>
<L>Rode in riche weede, <MILESTONE N="2248"/></L>
<L>Fro Barbary co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>myng,</L>
<L>Vppon̄ a sturdy stede,</L>
<L>Cryinge to hem vppon̄ the walle:</L>
<L>"Trayto<HI REND="italic">u</HI>ris, yelde yoū here! <MILESTONE N="2252"/></L>
<L>Brenne you alle ellis I shalle,</L>
<L>By myghty god Iubyte<ABBR>r</ABBR>."</L>
<L>Gy aspied, that he came ne<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Guy kills Marsedage the king of Barbary, by throwing a dart at him.</NOTE></L>
<L>A darte to hime he threwe ful even̄, <MILESTONE N="2256"/></L>
<L>He smote him throwe herte &amp; liver in fe<ABBR>r</ABBR>.</L>
<L>Dame Florip<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lough witħ loude steven̄</L>
<L>And saide "Sir Gye, my loue so free,</L>
<L>Thou kanste welle hit the prikke. <MILESTONE N="2260"/></L>
<L>He shall make no booste in his contre;</L>
<L>God giffe him sorowe thikke!"</L>
<L>Whan̄ Laban̄ herde of this myschie<ABBR>f</ABBR>,</L>
<L>A sory man̄ was he. <MILESTONE N="2264"/></L>
<L>He trumped, his mene to relefe; <NOTE PLACE="marg">They stop the attack</NOTE></L>
<L>For to cease that tyme mente he.</L>
<L>Mersadage, kinge of Barbarye,</L>
<L>He did carye to his tente, <MILESTONE N="2268"/></L>
<L>And beryed him by right of Sarsenye <NOTE PLACE="marg">to bury Marse∣dage,</NOTE></L>
<L>With brennynge fire and riche oynemente,</L>
<L>And songe the Dirige of Alkaron̄,</L>
<L>That bibill is of here laye, <MILESTONE N="2272"/></L>
<L>And wayled his deth everychon̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and bewail him 7 days and nights.</NOTE></L>
<L>vij nyghtis and vij dayes.</L>
<L>Anoon̄ the Sowdon̄, south to say, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Then the soudan more closely blockades the castle.</NOTE></L>
<L>Sente iij hundrid of knightis, <MILESTONE N="2276"/></L>
<L>To kepe the brigge and the waye</L>
<L>Oute of that Castil rightis,</L>
<L>That noon̄ of hem shulde issue oute,</L>
<L><PB N="66" REF="137"/>
To feche vitayle by no waye. <MILESTONE N="2280"/></L>
<L>He charged hem to wacche wel ałł abowte,</L>
<L>That thay for-fameli<ABBR>d</ABBR> myght dye.</L>
<L>Thus thay kepte the place vij dayes, <MILESTONE N="57" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Tille alle hire vitaile was nyȝe spente. <MILESTONE N="2284"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">The provisions being exhausted,</NOTE></L>
<L>The yates thai pas the streyte weyes.</L>
<L>Tho helde thai hem with-in I-shente.</L>
<L>Tho spake Roulande with hevy chere</L>
<L>Woordes lamentable, <MILESTONE N="2288"/></L>
<L>Whan̄ he saugħ the ladies so whiȝte of le<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>Faile brede on here table,</L>
<L>And saide "Charles, thoū curteys kinge, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Roland complains of Charles's forgetfulness;</NOTE></L>
<L>Why forgetist thoū vs so longe? <MILESTONE N="2292"/></L>
<L>This is to me a wondir thinge;</L>
<L>Me thinkitħ, thou doiste vs grete wronge,</L>
<L>To let vs dye for faute of mete,</L>
<L>Closed thus in a dongeon̄. <MILESTONE N="2296"/></L>
<L>To morowe wol we asaye what we kon̄ gete,</L>
<L>By god, that berithe the crown̄."</L>
<L>Tho saide Floripas "sires, drede noghte <NOTE PLACE="marg">but Floripas cheers him up,</NOTE></L>
<L>For noon̄ houng<ABBR>r</ABBR> that may befalle. <MILESTONE N="2300"/></L>
<L>I knowe a medycyne in my thoughte</L>
<L>To comforte yoū witħ alle.</L>
<L>I have a girdil in my Force<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">saying she pos∣sessed a magic girdle which was a talisman against hunger and thirst for those who wore it.</NOTE></L>
<L>Who so girde hem̄ ther-with aboute, <MILESTONE N="2304"/></L>
<L>Hunger ner thirste shal him neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> dere,</L>
<L>Though he were vij yere witħ-oute."</L>
<L>"O" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Sir Gy "my loue so trewe,</L>
<L>I-blessed mote ye be! <MILESTONE N="2308"/></L>
<L>I pray yoū, that ye wole us alle hit shewe,</L>
<L>That we may haue oure saule.</L>
<L>She yede and set it fortħ anoon̄,</L>
<L>Thai proved alle the vertue, <MILESTONE N="2312"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">They all suc∣cessively put it on and felt as if they had feasted.</NOTE></L>
<L>And diden it aboute hem̄ eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ychon̄.</L>
<L>It comforted alle both moo and fewe,</L>
<L>As thai hade bene at a feste.</L>
<L><PB N="67" REF="138"/>
So were thay alle wele at ease, <MILESTONE N="2316"/></L>
<L>Thus were thai refresshed botħ moost &amp; lest</L>
<L>And weren bifore in grete disese.</L>
<L>Laban̄ wondred, how thai myght endu<ABBR>r</ABBR> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Laban wondered at their endur∣ance,</NOTE></L>
<L>Witħ-outen̄ vitaile so longe. <MILESTONE N="2320"/></L>
<L>He reme<HI REND="italic">m</HI>bred him on Floripas senctu<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">but at last remembering the girdle,</NOTE></L>
<L>And of the vertue so stronge.</L>
<L>Tho wiste he welle, that throgħ famyne <MILESTONE N="58" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Might he hem̄ never wynne. <MILESTONE N="2324"/></L>
<L>He cleped to him fals Mapyne, <NOTE PLACE="marg">he induced Mapyne</NOTE></L>
<L>For he coude many a fals gynne:</L>
<L>He coude scale Castel and Toure</L>
<L>And over the walles wende. <MILESTONE N="2328"/></L>
<L>"Mapyne" he saide "for myn̄ honoure,</L>
<L>Thou mooste haue this in mynde:</L>
<L>That hore, my doght<HI REND="italic">er,</HI> a girdil hatħ she,</L>
<L>From̄ hounger it savyth hem̄ alle, <MILESTONE N="2332"/></L>
<L>That wonnen may thay never be,</L>
<L>That foule mote hir bifalle!</L>
<L>Kanstowe gete me that gyrdill by craft, <NOTE PLACE="marg">to attempt to steal it at night.</NOTE></L>
<L>A thousande pounde than̄ shal I gefe the; <MILESTONE N="2336"/></L>
<L>So that it be there not lefte, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'lafte.'</NOTE></L>
<L>But bringe it hithi<ABBR>r</ABBR> to me.</L>
<L>Thoū kanste see by nyghte as welle</L>
<L>As any man doth by daye. <MILESTONE N="2340"/></L>
<L>Whan thay bene in here beddes ful stiłł,</L>
<L>Than go forth thider right in thy waye.</L>
<L>Thou shalt it in here Chamber fynde,</L>
<L>Thou maist be thereofe sure." <MILESTONE N="2344"/></L>
<L>"Sir, there-to I wole me bynde,</L>
<L>If my life may endure."</L>
<L>Fortħ wente this fals Mapyne</L>
<L>By nyght into the Tou<ABBR>r</ABBR> <MILESTONE N="2348"/></L>
<L>God gife him evel endinge!—<NOTE PLACE="marg">Mapyne entered the chamber of Floripas through</NOTE></L>
<L>Euen in to Floripas bou<ABBR>r</ABBR>.</L>
<L><PB N="68" REF="139"/>
By a Chemney he wente inne; <NOTE PLACE="marg">a chimney;</NOTE></L>
<L>Fulle stilly there he soughte it. <MILESTONE N="2352"/></L>
<L>He it founde and girde it aboute him, <NOTE PLACE="marg">he finds the girdle and puts it on,</NOTE></L>
<L>And aftyr ful dere he bogħt it;</L>
<L>For by the light of a lampe the<ABBR>r</ABBR></L>
<L>Floripas gan̄ him aspye, <MILESTONE N="2356"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">but Floripas perceives him</NOTE></L>
<L>Alle a-frayed oute of hir slepe for fere,</L>
<L>But lowde than gan she crye <NOTE PLACE="marg">and cries out.</NOTE></L>
<L>And saide "a thefe is in my boure,</L>
<L>Robbe me he wole or sloo." <MILESTONE N="2360"/></L>
<L>Ther-with come Rouland fro his tou<ABBR>r</ABBR> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Roland hurries to her assistance,</NOTE></L>
<L>To wete of hir woo. <MILESTONE N="59" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>He founde Mapyne bysyde hir bedde,</L>
<L>Stondinge amased for drede, <MILESTONE N="2364"/></L>
<L>To the wyndowe he him ladde, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE></L>
<L>And there he smote of his hedde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">cuts off Mapine's head, and throws him out through the window without noticing the girdle.</NOTE></L>
<L>And caste him oute in-to the see.</L>
<L>Of the gyrdille was he not wa<ABBR>r</ABBR>; <MILESTONE N="2368"/></L>
<L>But whan̄ he wist, the girdel hade he,</L>
<L>Tho hadde he sorowe and care.</L>
<L>Florip<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to the Cheste wente <NOTE PLACE="marg">Floripas, seeing her girdle lost, is much grieved;</NOTE></L>
<L>And aspyed, hire gyrdel was goon̄, <MILESTONE N="2372"/></L>
<L>"Alas!" she saide, "alle is it shente!</L>
<L>Sir, what haue ye done?</L>
<L>He hath my girdel aboute hym̄.</L>
<L>Alas! þat harde while! <MILESTONE N="2376"/></L>
<L>A rebelle hounde dotħ ofte grete tene;</L>
<L>Howe be we alle begilede."</L>
<L>Tho spake Roulande witħ che<ABBR>r</ABBR> boolde,</L>
<L>"Dameselle! beytħ noughte aferde! <MILESTONE N="2380"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Roland comforts her.</NOTE></L>
<L>If any vitaile be aboute this hoolde,</L>
<L>We wole hem wynne withe dinte of swerde.</L>
<L>To morowe wole wee oute-goon̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">They agree to attempt a sally to obtain food.</NOTE></L>
<L>And assaye, howe it wole it be. <MILESTONE N="2384"/></L>
<L>I make a vowe to god alone,</L>
<L><PB N="69" REF="140"/>
Assaile hem wole we!</L>
<L>And if thay haue any mete,</L>
<L>Parte withe hem̄ wole we. <MILESTONE N="2388"/></L>
<L>Or elles strokes thay shal gete</L>
<L>By God and seynte Mary myn̄ avou<ABBR>r</ABBR>! <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE></L>
<L>In the morne, er the larke songe, <NOTE PLACE="marg">In the morning</NOTE></L>
<L>Thai ordeynede hem to ride <MILESTONE N="2392"/></L>
<L>To the Saresyns, þat hade so longe</L>
<L>Leyen hem besyde.</L>
<L>Duke Neymes and Oge<ABBR>r</ABBR> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Naymes and Ogier remain in the castle,</NOTE></L>
<L>Were ordeynede to kepe the place. <MILESTONE N="2396"/></L>
<L>The x othir of the xij peres <NOTE PLACE="marg">the others start</NOTE></L>
<L>Wente oute to assaye here grace.</L>
<L>Thay founden̄ hem in logges slepynge, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and surprise the Saracens still sleeping in their huts.</NOTE></L>
<L>Of hem hade thay no thought. <MILESTONE N="2400"/></L>
<L>Thai slowen̄ down̄ þat came to honde,</L>
<L>Mahounde availed hem noghte. <MILESTONE N="60" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>In shorte tyme the ende was made,</L>
<L>Thay ten slough iij hundred the<ABBR>r</ABBR>. <MILESTONE N="2404"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">They slew 300 and carried off as much food as they could bear.</NOTE></L>
<L>Tho founde thai vitaile, thay were glad,</L>
<L>As moche as thay myghte home be<ABBR>r</ABBR>.</L>
<L>Duke Neymes and Oge<ABBR>r</ABBR>, that kept the tou<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>Say hem witħ here praye. <MILESTONE N="2408"/></L>
<L>Thai thanked god hye of honoure,</L>
<L>That thai spedde so þat day.</L>
<L>Thay avaled the brigge and lete him yn,</L>
<L>Florip̄ and here maydyns were gladde, <MILESTONE N="2412"/></L>
<L>And so were thay, that were with-yn;</L>
<L>For alle grete hounger thay hadde.</L>
<L>Thai eten̄ and dronken right I-nowe</L>
<L>And made myrtħ ever amonge. <MILESTONE N="2416"/></L>
<L>But of the Sowdon̄ laban speke we nowe,</L>
<L>Howe of sorowe was his songe.</L>
<L>WHan tidyngges came to him,</L>
<L>That his men̄ were slayn̄, <MILESTONE N="2420"/></L>
<L>And howe thai hade stuffed hem̄ also <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE></L>
<L><PB N="70" REF="141"/>
With vitaile in agayne,</L>
<L>For sorowe he woxe nere wode. <NOTE PLACE="marg">The soudan is enraged,</NOTE></L>
<L>He cleped Brenlande and Sortybraunce. <MILESTONE N="2424"/></L>
<L>And tolde hem̄ witħ angry mode</L>
<L>Of his harde myschaunce.</L>
<L>"Remedye ordeyne me,</L>
<L>Ye be chief of my counsaile; <MILESTONE N="2428"/></L>
<L>That I of hem may vengede be,</L>
<L>It shalle you bouth availe.</L>
<L>O ye goddes, ye faile at nede,</L>
<L>That I have honoured so longe, <MILESTONE N="2432"/></L>
<L>I shalle yoū bren̄, so mote <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">MS.</HI> mete.</NOTE> I spede, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and is going to burn his gods,</NOTE></L>
<L>In a fayre fyre ful stronge;</L>
<L>Shalle I neuer more on yoū bileve,</L>
<L>But renaye yoū playnly alle. <MILESTONE N="2436"/></L>
<L>Ye shalle be brente this day er eve,</L>
<L>That foule mote yoū befalle!"</L>
<L>The fire was made, the goddes were broght</L>
<L>To have be caste the<ABBR>r</ABBR>-inne. <MILESTONE N="2440"/> <MILESTONE N="61" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Tho alle his counsaile him by-sought, <NOTE PLACE="marg">but, appeased by his wise men,</NOTE></L>
<L>He shulde of þat erroure blynne,</L>
<L>And saide "Sir, what wole ye done?</L>
<L>Wole ye your goddis for-sake? <MILESTONE N="2444"/></L>
<L>Vengeaunce shalle than̄ on yoū come,</L>
<L>With sorowe, woo and wrake!</L>
<L>Ye moste make offrynge for youre offence,</L>
<L>For drede of grete vengeaunce, <MILESTONE N="2448"/></L>
<L>With oyle, mylke and ffranken̄cense</L>
<L>By youre prestis ordynaunce."</L>
<L>Tho he dide bere hem in ayen̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">he sacrifices again,</NOTE></L>
<L>And to hem made dewe offerynge. <MILESTONE N="2452"/></L>
<L>The prestis assoyled him of þat synne, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and is assoiled by the priests.</NOTE></L>
<L>Ful lowly for him prayinge.</L>
<L>Tho he cleped his counselers <NOTE PLACE="marg">Laban holds council.</NOTE></L>
<L>Brulande and Sortybraunce, <MILESTONE N="2456"/></L>
<L><PB N="71" REF="142"/>
Axynge, howe he myght destroy<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the xij peres,</L>
<L>That Mahounde gife hem myschaunce.</L>
<L>Thay cowde no more ther-on̄,</L>
<L>But late saile ayen̄ the toure. <MILESTONE N="2460"/></L>
<L>Witħ xx<SUP>ti</SUP> thousande thai gan̄ gon̄,</L>
<L>And bigo<HI REND="italic">n</HI>ne a newe shoure <NOTE PLACE="marg">A new assault begins,</NOTE></L>
<L>To breke down̄ the Walles,</L>
<L>With mattok<HI REND="italic">es</HI> and witħ pike, <MILESTONE N="2464"/></L>
<L>Tille iiij hundred of hem alle <NOTE PLACE="marg">but the ditches are filled with assailants, who were slain by the showers of stones hurled down by the peers.</NOTE></L>
<L>Lay slayne in the dike.</L>
<L>So stronge was the cast of stoone.</L>
<L>The Saresyns drewe hem̄ abakke, <MILESTONE N="2468"/></L>
<L>Tille it was at hye none; <NOTE PLACE="marg">The Saracens retire.</NOTE></L>
<L>Tho go<HI REND="italic">n</HI>ne thay ayen̄ to shake. <NOTE PLACE="marg">A second attack ensues.</NOTE></L>
<L>Tho fayled hem cast, þat were w<HI REND="italic">i</HI>t<HI REND="italic">h</HI>-inne; <NOTE PLACE="marg">There being no stones,</NOTE></L>
<L>Tho cowde thai no rede, <MILESTONE N="2472"/></L>
<L>For stoone was ther noone to wy<HI REND="italic">n</HI>ne.</L>
<L>Tho were thay in grete drede.</L>
<L>Than saide Florip, "beitħ not dismayde!</L>
<L>Ye shalle be holpe anoon̄. <MILESTONE N="2476"/></L>
<L>Here is syluer vessel and now," <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">? I now.</NOTE> she sayde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Floripas gave them her father's silver and gold to cast amongst the assailants.</NOTE></L>
<L>"That shulle ye prove goode woon̄."</L>
<L>She set it forth, thay caste oute faste</L>
<L>Alle that came to honde. <MILESTONE N="2480"/> <MILESTONE N="62" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Off siluer and goolde vessel thay made waste</L>
<L>That wast <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'went.'</NOTE> down̄ vppon̄ the sonde.</L>
<L>Whan̄ thai saugħ that roial sight,</L>
<L>Thai leften alle here dede; <MILESTONE N="2484"/></L>
<L>And for the tresoure thay do fight,</L>
<L>Who so myghte it awey lede.</L>
<L>Tho the Sowdon̄ wexe nere wode, <NOTE PLACE="marg">The soudan in alarm for his treasure</NOTE></L>
<L>Seinge this tresoure thus dispoyle<ABBR>d</ABBR>, <MILESTONE N="2488"/></L>
<L>That was to him so dere and goode</L>
<L>Laye in the dike thus defoule<ABBR>d</ABBR>.</L>
<L>He bade that thai shulde leue <NOTE PLACE="marg">gives up the assault.</NOTE></L>
<L><PB N="72" REF="143"/>
And turne hem̄ agayne in haste. <MILESTONE N="2492"/></L>
<L>He wente home tille his tente than</L>
<L>With grete sorowe and mournyn<ABBR>g</ABBR> mode.</L>
<L>To-fore his goddis whan̄ he came,</L>
<L>He cryed, as he were wode: <MILESTONE N="2496"/></L>
<L>"O fals goddis, that y<SUP>e</SUP> betħ, <NOTE PLACE="marg">He is enraged with his gods,</NOTE></L>
<L>I have trustid to longe youre mode.</L>
<L>We <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">? Me.</NOTE> were leve<ABBR>r</ABBR> to suff<ABBR>r</ABBR> dede,</L>
<L>Than̄ lif this life here lenger nowe. <MILESTONE N="2500"/></L>
<L>I haue almoste loste the bretħ,</L>
<L>xij fals trayto<HI REND="italic">ur</HI>s me overe-lede,</L>
<L>And stroyen alle þat I haue.</L>
<L>Ye fals goddis, the devel youe spede! <MILESTONE N="2504"/></L>
<L>Ye make me nowe for to rave;</L>
<L>Ye do fayle me at my nede."</L>
<L>In Ire he smote Mahounde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and smites Mahound</NOTE></L>
<L>That was of goolde fulle rede, <MILESTONE N="2508"/></L>
<L>That he fille down̄ to the grounde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">so that he fell on his face;</NOTE></L>
<L>As he hade bene dede.</L>
<L>Alle here bisshopes cryden̄ oute</L>
<L>And saide "Mahounde, thyn̄ ore!" <MILESTONE N="2512"/></L>
<L>And down̄ to the erthe wele lowe thay loute,</L>
<L>Howlynge and wepynge sore,</L>
<L>And saide "Sire Sowdon̄, what haue ye done?</L>
<L>Vengeaunce shalle on the falle, <MILESTONE N="2516"/></L>
<L>But thoū repente the here anone."</L>
<L>"Ye" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d he "I shrewe yoū alle!" <NOTE PLACE="marg">but the priests induce him</NOTE></L>
<L>Thai made a fyre of fran<ABBR>k</ABBR>encense</L>
<L>And blewen̄ hornes of bras, <MILESTONE N="2520"/></L>
<L>And casten in milke hony for the offence, <MILESTONE N="63" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>To-fore Mahoundes face.</L>
<L>Thay counsailed Laban to knele a down̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">to kneel down and ask forgive∣ness.</NOTE></L>
<L>And aske forgevenes in that place. <MILESTONE N="2524"/></L>
<L>And so he didde and hade pardon̄</L>
<L>Throgh prayere and specialle grace.</L>
<L><PB N="73" REF="144"/>
Then <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">? 'When.'</NOTE> this was done, þan̄ sayde Roulande <NOTE PLACE="marg">Meanwhile Roland</NOTE></L>
<L>To his Felowes xj: <MILESTONE N="2528"/></L>
<L>"Here may we not longe holde londe,</L>
<L>By God that is in heven̄.</L>
<L>Therefore sende we to Charles, the kinge,</L>
<L>That he wolde reskowe vs sone; <MILESTONE N="2532"/></L>
<L>And certyfye him o<ABBR>f</ABBR> oure strayȝte beinge, <NOTE PLACE="marg">exhorted Richard of Normandy to go on message to Charles, that he might come to their rescue.</NOTE></L>
<L>If ye thinke, it be to done.</L>
<L>Richard of Normandye, ye most goon̄,</L>
<L>I holde yoū both wyse and hende. <MILESTONE N="2536"/></L>
<L>And we shalle tomorowe, as stil as stoon̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">They all would the following morning, before day break, make an attack on the Saracens, and meanwhile he should steal off in the darkness.</NOTE></L>
<L>The Saresyns a-wake, er ye wynde. <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'wende.'</NOTE></L>
<L>And while we be mooste bysy in oure werke,</L>
<L>And medel witħ hem alle in fere, <MILESTONE N="2540"/></L>
<L>Stele ye a-waye in the derke!</L>
<L>And spede you faste, ye were there!"</L>
<L>On the morowe afti<ABBR>r</ABBR> the daye <NOTE PLACE="marg">In the morning</NOTE></L>
<L>Thay were armede ful ryghte, <MILESTONE N="2544"/></L>
<L>Thai rode fortħ stilly in here way, <NOTE PLACE="marg">they sally out.</NOTE></L>
<L>God gouerne hem, mooste of myght!</L>
<L>Florip<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and here maydyns kept the tou<ABBR>r</ABBR> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Floripas and her maidens draw up the bridges after them.</NOTE></L>
<L>And woonde vp the brigges on hye, <MILESTONE N="2548"/></L>
<L>And prayde god, to kepe here paramou<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>The Duke of Burgoyne, S<HI REND="italic">ir</HI> Gȳe.</L>
<L>She preyde to Rouland, er he wente,</L>
<L>To take goode hede of him̄, <MILESTONE N="2552"/></L>
<L>That he were neyþer take nere shente,</L>
<L>As he wolde her loue wynne.</L>
<L>On thay set with herte stronge</L>
<L>And alle hem̄ sore afrayed. <MILESTONE N="2556"/></L>
<L>Richard the whiles away he wronge, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Richard went off towards Mantrible.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thile <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">? 'while.'</NOTE> thai were alle dismayede.</L>
<L>Towarde the Mountrible he hyed him faste,</L>
<L>To passe, if that he myghte. <MILESTONE N="2560"/> <MILESTONE N="64" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Thedir he came at the laste.</L>
<L><PB N="74" REF="145"/>
God kepe him for his mocħ myght!</L>
<L>His xij <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">? xj.</NOTE> felowes besyed hem̄ soo <NOTE PLACE="marg">The others slay many Saracens;</NOTE></L>
<L>That many of hem̄ thay sloughe. <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> <MILESTONE N="2564"/></L>
<L>Gye slowe the kinge of Babyloyne tho;</L>
<L>The Babyloynes of his hors him drowe, <NOTE PLACE="marg">but Guy, overpowered by the Babylonians, is taken prisoner.</NOTE></L>
<L>And with force him drowe there</L>
<L>And bounde his hondes ful fast. <MILESTONE N="2568"/></L>
<L>A newe game thai gan̄ him lere,</L>
<L>For in depe prison̄ thay him caste.</L>
<L>But Laban̄ wolde him first se,</L>
<L>To wete what he was. <MILESTONE N="2572"/></L>
<L>"Telle me thy name nowe" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d he, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Laban asks his name.</NOTE></L>
<L>"Thy songe shalle be 'alas.'"—</L>
<L>"Sire" he saide "my name is Gye, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Guy tells him.</NOTE></L>
<L>I wole it never forsake. <MILESTONE N="2576"/></L>
<L>It were to me grete vilanye</L>
<L>An̄ othir name to take."—</L>
<L>"O fals trayto<HI REND="italic">ur</HI>" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Laban̄,</L>
<L>"My doghtir, þat stronge hore, <MILESTONE N="2580"/></L>
<L>Hath me for-sake and the hath tan̄,</L>
<L>Thoū shalte be honged therfore." <NOTE PLACE="marg">He is to be hanged.</NOTE></L>
<L>Roulande made grete moone,</L>
<L>It wolde noon̄ other be. <MILESTONE N="2584"/></L>
<L>Homwarde thai gan̄ goon̄,</L>
<L>.iij.c Saresyns ther saye he, <NOTE PLACE="marg">300 Saracens crowding near the gate of the castle, attempted to prevent the other peers from entering.</NOTE></L>
<L>That kepte the pace at the brigge-ende,</L>
<L>Armed wel in goode araye, <MILESTONE N="2588"/></L>
<L>That thai sholde not in wende,</L>
<L>But be take or slayn̄ þat daye.</L>
<L>Roulande to his felowes saide:</L>
<L>"Beth alle of right gode chere! <MILESTONE N="2592"/></L>
<L>And we shal make hem alle afrayde,</L>
<L>E<ABBR>r</ABBR> we go to oure soupere."</L>
<L>There byganne a bykeringe bolde <NOTE PLACE="marg">A fearful struggle begins.</NOTE></L>
<L>Of x Bachelers that tyde, <MILESTONE N="2596"/></L>
<L><PB N="75" REF="146" MS="y"/>
Agayne iijc men̄ I-tolde,</L>
<L>That durste righte wel a-byde.</L>
<L>Tho was Durnedale set a werke, <MILESTONE N="65" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>XL of hethen he sloughe, <MILESTONE N="2600"/></L>
<L>He spared neþe<ABBR>r</ABBR> lewde ner clerke,</L>
<L>And Floripas the<ABBR>r</ABBR>-of loughe.</L>
<L>The shotte, the caste was so stronge,</L>
<L>Syr Bryer was slayn̄ there <MILESTONE N="2604"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Sir Bryer is killed.</NOTE></L>
<L>With dartes, gauylokes and speres longe,</L>
<L>xx<SUP>ti</SUP> on hym there were.</L>
<L>Roulande was woo and Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>Thay sloughen̄ alle that thai mette. <MILESTONE N="2608"/></L>
<L>Tho fledde the Turkes alle for fe<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">At last the Saracens take to flight.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thay durste no longer lette</L>
<L>And saide, thai we<ABBR>r</ABBR> no men,</L>
<L>But develis abroken̄ oute of helle, <MILESTONE N="2612"/></L>
<L>".iij. hundred of vs agayn̄ hem ten̄.</L>
<L>Oure lorde Mahounde hem qwelle!</L>
<L>XL of vs here be ascaped,</L>
<L>And hardde we be bistadde."— <MILESTONE N="2616"/></L>
<L>"Who so wole of hem̄ more be iaped,</L>
<L>I holde him worsse than madde."</L>
<L>Tho Roulande and Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR></L>
<L>Maden̄ grete woo and sorowe, <MILESTONE N="2620"/></L>
<L>And token̄ the corps of Sir Bryere <NOTE PLACE="marg">The peers retire inside the castle, taking the corpse of Bryer with them.</NOTE></L>
<L>And beryed it on the morowe.</L>
<L>Florip<HI REND="italic">e</HI> asked Roulande anoone</L>
<L>"Where is my loue Sir Gye?"— <MILESTONE N="2624"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Floripas enquires after Guy,</NOTE></L>
<L>"Damesel" he saide "he is goon̄,</L>
<L>And therfore woo am I."—</L>
<L>"Alas" she saide "than am I dede, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and on hearing of his capture, begins to lament despairingly.</NOTE></L>
<L>Nowe Gye my lorde is slayn̄, <MILESTONE N="2628"/></L>
<L>Shall I neuer more ete brede</L>
<L>Tille that I may se him̄ agayn̄."—</L>
<L>"Be stille" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Roulande "and haue no ca<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Roland promises to rescue Guy.</NOTE></L>
<L>We shal hym̄ haue ful wele. <MILESTONE N="2632"/></L>
<L><PB N="76" REF="147"/>
Tomorowe wele we thiderward fa<ABBR>r</ABBR></L>
<L>With spere and shelde of stele.</L>
<L>But we bringe him to this Tou<ABBR>r</ABBR>—</L>
<L>Leeve me elles no more— <MILESTONE N="2636"/></L>
<L>With victorye and grete honou<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>Or thay shalle abye it ful sore." <MILESTONE N="66" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>On the morowe, whan tha daye was clere,</L>
<L>Laban ordeynede Gye honged to be. <MILESTONE N="2640"/></L>
<L>He cleped forth Sir Tampere <NOTE PLACE="marg">On the following morning Laban orders Sir Tamper to erect a gallows before the castle, where Floripas could see it.</NOTE></L>
<L>And badde him do make a Galowe tr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI></L>
<L>"And set it even̄ by-fore the tou<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>That þilke hore may him see; <MILESTONE N="2644"/></L>
<L>For by lord Mahounde of honou<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>This traito<HI REND="italic">u</HI>r there shalle honged be.</L>
<L>Take withe the .iij. hundred knigħtes</L>
<L>Of Ethiopis, Indens and Ascopartes, <MILESTONE N="2648"/></L>
<L>That bene boolde and hardy to fight</L>
<L>With Wifles, Fauchons, Gauylokes <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">MS.</HI> Gamylokes.</NOTE> and Dartes;</L>
<L>Leste þat lurdeynes come skulkynge oute,</L>
<L>For ever thay haue bene shrewes. <MILESTONE N="2652"/></L>
<L>Loke ech<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of hem̄ haue sucħ a cloute,</L>
<L>That thay neuer ete moo Sewes."</L>
<L>Forth thay wente with Sir Gye, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Guy is led bound.</NOTE></L>
<L>That bounde was as a thefe faste, <MILESTONE N="2656"/></L>
<L>Tille thay come the tow<ABBR>r</ABBR> ful nye;</L>
<L>Thai rered the Galowes in haste.</L>
<L>Roulande perceyued here doynge</L>
<L>And saide "felows, let armes <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'as armes.'</NOTE>! <MILESTONE N="2660"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Roland calls his companions to arms.</NOTE></L>
<L>I am ful gladde of here comynge,</L>
<L>Hem shall not helpe her charmes."</L>
<L>Oute thai riden a wele gode spede, <NOTE PLACE="marg">They rush forth.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thai ix towarde hem alle. <MILESTONE N="2664"/></L>
<L>Florip witħ here maydyns toke gode hede,</L>
<L>Biholdinge over the tou<ABBR>r</ABBR> walle.</L>
<L>Thai met first witħ Sir Tampe<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L><PB N="77" REF="148"/>
God gife him evelle fyne! <MILESTONE N="2668"/></L>
<L>Such a stroke lente hym Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Oliver cuts down Sir Tamper;</NOTE></L>
<L>He clefe him down̄ to the skyne.</L>
<L>Rouland bare the kinge of Ynde <NOTE PLACE="marg">Roland kills a king of India,</NOTE></L>
<L>Ther with his spere frome his stede. <MILESTONE N="2672"/></L>
<L>.iiij. fote it passed his bak byhynde,</L>
<L>His herte blode þe<ABBR>r</ABBR> didde he blede.</L>
<L>He caught the stede, he was ful goode, <NOTE PLACE="marg">takes his sword and horse,</NOTE></L>
<L>And the swerde, þat the kinge hadde, <MILESTONE N="2676"/></L>
<L>And rode to Gye, there he stode, <MILESTONE N="67" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>And onbounde hym̄ and bade him be gladde. <NOTE PLACE="marg">and gives them to Guy, having unbound him.</NOTE></L>
<L>And girde him witħ that goode swerde,</L>
<L>And lepen vppon̄ here stedes. <MILESTONE N="2680"/></L>
<L>"Be thou" he saide "righte nougħt a-ferde,</L>
<L>But helpe vs wightly at this nede."</L>
<L>An hundred of hem sone thay slowe <NOTE PLACE="marg">They slay many Saracens, and put the rest to flight.</NOTE></L>
<L>Of the beste of hem alle; <MILESTONE N="2684"/></L>
<L>The remen<HI REND="italic">au</HI>nte a-way fast thay flowe,</L>
<L>That foule motte hem byfalle!</L>
<L>Rouland and his Felowes were glad</L>
<L>That Gye was safe in dede. <MILESTONE N="2688"/></L>
<L>Thay thanked god, that thay <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> him hadde</L>
<L>Gyfen thay<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> sucħ grace to spede.</L>
<L>As thay wente towarde the Tou<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Retiring towards the castle,</NOTE></L>
<L>A litil bysyde the hye waye, <MILESTONE N="2692"/></L>
<L>Thai saugh comynge with grete vigou<ABBR>r</ABBR></L>
<L>An hundred vppon̄ a laye. <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">MS.</HI> 'alaye.' <HI REND="italic">See the note.</HI></NOTE></L>
<L>Costroye ther was, the Admyrałł, <NOTE PLACE="marg">they see admiral Costroye</NOTE></L>
<L>With vitaile grete plente, <MILESTONE N="2696"/></L>
<L>And the stondarte of the Sowdon̄ Roial. <NOTE PLACE="marg">and the soudan's standard-bearer escorting a great convoy, destined for the sultan, across a field near the high road.</NOTE></L>
<L>Towarde Mauntrible riden̄ he,</L>
<L>.iiij. Chariotes I-charged witħ flessh and brede,</L>
<L>And two othe<ABBR>r</ABBR> with wyne, <MILESTONE N="2700"/></L>
<L>Of divers colouris, yolowe, white and rede,</L>
<L>And iiij Somers of spicery fyne.</L>
<L><PB N="78" REF="149"/>
Tho saide Roulande to Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR>:</L>
<L>"With these meyne moste we shifte, <MILESTONE N="2704"/></L>
<L>To haue parte of here vitailes he<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>For therof us nedith by my thrifte."—</L>
<L>"Howe, sires" he saide "god you see! <NOTE PLACE="marg">Roland calls to them</NOTE></L>
<L>We pray youe for youre curtesye, <MILESTONE N="2708"/></L>
<L>Parte of your Vitaile gr<HI REND="italic">a</HI>unte me, <NOTE PLACE="marg">to share the provisions with them.</NOTE></L>
<L>For we may nother borowe ner bye."</L>
<L>Tho spake Cosdroye, that Admyral,</L>
<L>"Ye gete none here for nogħt. <MILESTONE N="2712"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Costroye refuses,</NOTE></L>
<L>Yf ye oght chalenge in speciałł,</L>
<L>It most be dere I-boght."—</L>
<L>"O gentil knight<HI REND="italic">es</HI>" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Olyuere,</L>
<L>"He is no felowe, þat wole haue alle." <MILESTONE N="2716"/></L>
<L>"Go fortħ" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d the stondart, "thoū getist noon here,</L>
<L>Thy parte shalle be fulle smalle."—</L>
<L>"Forsoth" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Roulande "and shift we wole, <MILESTONE N="68" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Gete the better, who gete maye! <MILESTONE N="2720"/></L>
<L>To parte with the nedy it is gode skille,</L>
<L>And so shalle ye by my faye."</L>
<L>He rode to the Admyral witħ his swerde <NOTE PLACE="marg">and is slain by Roland.</NOTE></L>
<L>And gafe him suche a cloute, <MILESTONE N="2724"/></L>
<L>No wonder thogħ he were aferde,</L>
<L>Both his eyȝen̄ braste oute.</L>
<L>Olyuere met withe the proude stondarde,</L>
<L>He smote him througħ the herte. <MILESTONE N="2728"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Oliver kills the standard-bearer.</NOTE></L>
<L>That hade he for his rewarde;</L>
<L>That wounde gan̄ sore smerte.</L>
<L>Thai were slayn̄, that wolde fight</L>
<L>Er durste bikure abyde. <MILESTONE N="2732"/></L>
<L>Thai forsoke her parte anoon̄ rigħt,</L>
<L>It lefte alle on̄ that on̄ side.</L>
<L>Forth thai drewen̄ þat vitaile <NOTE PLACE="marg">The convoy is conveyed into the castle.</NOTE></L>
<L>Streight in-to the Toure. <MILESTONE N="2736"/></L>
<L>There was no man̄ durst hem assayle,</L>
<L>For drede of here vigou<ABBR>r</ABBR>.</L>
<L><PB N="79" REF="150"/>
Florip<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hem resceyved w<HI REND="italic">i</HI>t<HI REND="italic">h</HI> honou<ABBR>r</ABBR></L>
<L>And thanked Roulande fele sythe, <MILESTONE N="2740"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Floripas thanks Roland for bringing back Sir Guy,</NOTE></L>
<L>That she saugħ Gye hir paramou<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>That wolde she him qwite and kith<HI REND="italic">e.</HI></L>
<L>Thai eten̄ and dronken and made hem gladde,</L>
<L>Hem neded ther aftyr fulle sore <MILESTONE N="2744"/></L>
<L>Of suche, as god hem sente hade,</L>
<L>I-nowe for iiij moonþes and more.</L>
<L>Florip saide to Roulande than, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and proposes that he shall choose himself a mistress from amongst her maidens. But Roland refuses to take any that is no Christian.</NOTE></L>
<L>"Ye moste chese you a love <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'leve.'</NOTE> <MILESTONE N="2748"/></L>
<L>Of alle my maydyns, white as swan̄."—</L>
<L>Q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Rouland "þat were myscheve;</L>
<L>Oure lay wole not, þat we w<HI REND="italic">i</HI>t<HI REND="italic">h</HI> youe dele,</L>
<L>Tille that ye Cristyn̄ be made; <MILESTONE N="2752"/></L>
<L>Ner of your play we wole not fele,</L>
<L>For than̄ were we cursed in dede."</L>
<L>NOwe shall ye here of Laban̄. <NOTE PLACE="marg">The soudan, on hearing such bad news,</NOTE></L>
<L>Whan tidyngg<HI REND="italic">es</HI> to him we<ABBR>r</ABBR> comen̄, <MILESTONE N="2756"/></L>
<L>Tho was he a fulle sory man̄.</L>
<L>Whan he herde, howe his vitaile were nomen̄,</L>
<L>And howe his men were slayne,</L>
<L>And Gye was go safe hem̄ froo, <MILESTONE N="2760"/> <MILESTONE N="69" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>He defyed Mahounde and Apolyne, <NOTE PLACE="marg">again defies his gods,</NOTE></L>
<L>Iubiter, Ascarot and Alcaron̄ also.</L>
<L>He co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>maundede a fire to be digħt <NOTE PLACE="marg">and threatens to throw them into the flames.</NOTE></L>
<L>With picche and Brymston̄ to bren̄. <MILESTONE N="2764"/></L>
<L>He made a vowe with alle his mygħt,</L>
<L>"Thai shal be caste ther-Inne!"</L>
<L>The prestes of he<ABBR>r</ABBR> lawe ther-on̄,</L>
<L>Thai criden̄ oute for drede <MILESTONE N="2768"/></L>
<L>And saide "alas, what wole ye done?</L>
<L>The worse than moste ye spede!"</L>
<L>The Sowdon̄ made a grete othe</L>
<L>And swore by his hye trone, <MILESTONE N="2772"/></L>
<L>That though hem were never so lotħ,</L>
<L><PB N="80" REF="151"/>
Thai sholde be brente Ichon̄.</L>
<L>Tho came the bisshop<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Cramadas <NOTE PLACE="marg">But bishop Cramadas kneels before him and appeases him.</NOTE></L>
<L>And kneled bifore the Sowdon̄, <MILESTONE N="2776"/></L>
<L>And charged him by the hye name Sathanas,</L>
<L>To saven his goddes ychon̄:</L>
<L>"For if ye brenne youre goddes he<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>Ye wynnyn̄ her malison̄, <MILESTONE N="2780"/></L>
<L>Than wole no man do yoū che<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>In feelde, Cite, ne<ABBR>r</ABBR> in town̄."</L>
<L>The Sowdon̄ was astonyed þan</L>
<L>And gan him sore repente <MILESTONE N="2784"/></L>
<L>Of the foly, that he bygan̄,</L>
<L>And els hade he be shente.</L>
<L>A thousande of Besaunt<HI REND="italic">es</HI> he offred þaym to, <NOTE PLACE="marg">The soudan makes an offering of 1000 besants to his gods.</NOTE></L>
<L>By counsail of sir Cramadas, <MILESTONE N="2788"/></L>
<L>To please witħ his goddys tho,</L>
<L>For fere of harde grace.</L>
<L>The Sowdone co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>manded eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>y daye</L>
<L>To assaile the tou<ABBR>r</ABBR> witħ caste. <MILESTONE N="2792"/></L>
<L>But thay with-in gafe not an Eye,</L>
<L>For thai wroghte in wast.</L>
<L>NOwe speke we of Richarde of Normandy,</L>
<L>That on message was sente, <MILESTONE N="2796"/></L>
<L>Howe he spede and his meyne.</L>
<L>Whan he to Mauntrible wente, <NOTE PLACE="marg">When Richard arrived as far as Mantrible, he</NOTE></L>
<L>He founde the brigge Ichayned sore;</L>
<L>xxiiij<SUP>ti</SUP> were ouere-drawen̄. <MILESTONE N="2800"/> <MILESTONE N="70" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Alagolofure stode there byfore, <NOTE PLACE="marg">found the bridge barred by 24 chains, and Alagolafre standing before it.</NOTE></L>
<L>That many a man hade slawene.</L>
<L>Whan Richard saugħ, ther was no gate,</L>
<L>But by flagot the flode, <MILESTONE N="2804"/></L>
<L>His message wolde he not lete; <NOTE PLACE="marg">Determined not to leave his errand unperformed, he knelt down and commended himself to God.</NOTE></L>
<L>His hors was botħ bigge and goode.</L>
<L>He kneled, bisechinge god of his grace,</L>
<L>To save him fro myschiefe. <MILESTONE N="2808"/></L>
<L>A white hende he saugħ anoon̄ in þ<HI REND="italic">a</HI>t place, <NOTE PLACE="marg">A hind appears</NOTE></L>
<L><PB N="81" REF="152"/>
That swam̄ ove<ABBR>r</ABBR> the cliffe. <NOTE PLACE="marg">and swims across.</NOTE></L>
<L>He blessed him in godis name</L>
<L>And folowed the same waye <MILESTONE N="2812"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Richard follows her, and, passing over in safety,</NOTE></L>
<L>The gentil hende, þat was so tame,</L>
<L>That on̄ þat othir side gan playe.</L>
<L>He thanked god fele syth<HI REND="italic">e,</HI></L>
<L>That him hade sente comforte. <MILESTONE N="2816"/></L>
<L>He hied him in his message swiþe. <NOTE PLACE="marg">hurries on to Charlemagne.</NOTE></L>
<L>To speke witħ Charles his lorde.</L>
<L>But I shalle yoū telle of a trayto<HI REND="italic">ur,</HI></L>
<L>That his name was called Genelyne, <MILESTONE N="2820"/></L>
<L>He counseiled Charles for his honou<ABBR>r</ABBR> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Meanwhile Genelyn, the traitor, had advised Charles to retire to France, because the 12 peers were all slain.</NOTE></L>
<L>To turne homewarde ageyn̄.</L>
<L>He saide "the xij peres bene alle dede,</L>
<L>And ye spende your goode in vayne, <MILESTONE N="2824"/></L>
<L>And therfore dotħ nowe by my rede,</L>
<L>Ye shalle see hem no more certeyn̄."</L>
<L>The kinge bileved þat he saide, <NOTE PLACE="marg">The king believed him, and marched home∣ward, lamenting for his peers.</NOTE></L>
<L>And homwarde gan he fare. <MILESTONE N="2828"/></L>
<L>He of his xij Dosiperes was sore dismayed,</L>
<L>His herte woxe right fulle of ca<ABBR>r</ABBR>.</L>
<L>Rycharde of Normandy came prikande <NOTE PLACE="marg">Richard overtakes him, and is recognised by Charles,</NOTE></L>
<L>And hertly to ride begane. <MILESTONE N="2832"/></L>
<L>Kinge Charles aspyed him comande;</L>
<L>He co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>maunded to abide eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>y man̄.</L>
<L>"What tidingg<HI REND="italic">es?</HI>" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d the kinge to Richarde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">who asks him about the others.</NOTE></L>
<L>"Howe fare my felowes alle?" <MILESTONE N="2836"/></L>
<L>"My lorde" he saide "god wote, ful harde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Richard tells the king, how they are besieged within the castle, and are waiting for his assistance.</NOTE></L>
<L>For thai be byseged with-in ston-walle,</L>
<L>Abydynge youre helpe and you<ABBR>r</ABBR> socou<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>As men þat haue grete nede. <MILESTONE N="2840"/></L>
<L>For Ih<HI REND="italic">es</HI>ues loue, kinge of honou<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>Thiderward ye yoū spede!"</L>
<L>"O Genelyne" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d the kinge, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles, vowing vengeance on</NOTE></L>
<L>"Nowe knowe I thy treson̄, <MILESTONE N="2844"/> <MILESTONE N="71" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>I shalle the qwite, be seynte Fremounde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Genelyn,</NOTE></L>
<L><PB N="82" REF="153"/>
Whan̄ this viage is don̄."</L>
<L>The kinge turned him ageyn̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">turned and marched to Agremore.</NOTE></L>
<L>And alle his Ooste him witħ, <MILESTONE N="2848"/></L>
<L>Towarde Mountrible certeyne.</L>
<L>And <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'God'.</NOTE> gr<HI REND="italic">a</HI>unte him gree and grith!</L>
<L>Richarde him tolde of that place,</L>
<L>Howe stronge it was I-holde <MILESTONE N="2852"/></L>
<L>With a geaunte foule of face, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Richard informed him of the giant, who kept the bridge,</NOTE></L>
<L>The brigge hath chayned many folde;</L>
<L>The River was both depe and brode,</L>
<L>Ther myght no man̄ over-ryde. <MILESTONE N="2856"/></L>
<L>"The last tyme that I over-rode, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and how he had passed the river by a miracle.</NOTE></L>
<L>By myracle I passed þat tide.</L>
<L>Therfore sir, I shal yoū telle,</L>
<L>Howe ye mote governe yoū here. <MILESTONE N="2860"/></L>
<L>In yonde wode ye moste dwelle <NOTE PLACE="marg">He proposed a plan,</NOTE></L>
<L>Priuely in this mane<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>And xij of vs shalle vs araye <NOTE PLACE="marg">that 12 knights disguised as merchants, with</NOTE></L>
<L>In gyse of stronge marchauntes, <MILESTONE N="2864"/></L>
<L>And fille oure somers withe fog and haye,</L>
<L>To passe the brigge Currauntes.</L>
<L>We shalle be armed vnder the cote <NOTE PLACE="marg">their arms hidden under their clothes,</NOTE></L>
<L>With goode swerdes wele I-gyrde, <MILESTONE N="2868"/></L>
<L>We moste paye tribute, wele I wote, <NOTE PLACE="marg">should pay the toll,</NOTE></L>
<L>And elles over we may not sterte.</L>
<L>But whan̄ the chaynes be lete down̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">and the bridge being let down,</NOTE></L>
<L>Ouer ther for to passe, <MILESTONE N="2872"/></L>
<L>Than wole I, þat ye come on̄,</L>
<L>In haste to that same place.</L>
<L>Whan̄ I see tyme for to come,</L>
<L>Than̄ shalle I my horne blowe. <MILESTONE N="2876"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">should blow a horn as a signal for the others to approach.</NOTE></L>
<L>Loke, ye be redy alle and some,</L>
<L>For that shałł ye welle knowe."</L>
<L>Forth thay wente in þat araye <NOTE PLACE="marg">They start and arrive at Mantrible.</NOTE></L>
<L>To Mountrible, that Cite. <MILESTONE N="2880"/></L>
<L><PB N="83" REF="154"/>
Alagolofu<ABBR>r</ABBR> to hem̄ gan seye, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Alagolafre asks whither they are going.</NOTE></L>
<L>"Felawes, wheder wole ye?"</L>
<L>Richarde spake to the geaunte</L>
<L>And saide "towarde the Sowdon̄, <MILESTONE N="2884"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Richard says, they are mer∣chants on their way to the Soudan,</NOTE></L>
<L>With dyu[e]rs chaffe<ABBR>r</ABBR> as trewe marchaunte,</L>
<L>We purpose for to goon̄,</L>
<L>To shewen him of pellu<ABBR>r</ABBR> and Gryse, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'gray.'</NOTE></L>
<L>Orfrays of Perse Imperyalle, <MILESTONE N="2888"/> <MILESTONE N="72" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>We wole the yefe tribute of assaye <NOTE PLACE="marg">and they are willing to pay the toll.</NOTE></L>
<L>To passe by lycence in especyałł."</L>
<L>"Licence gete ye noon̄ of me, <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Alagolafre refuses to let them pass,</NOTE></L>
<L>I am charged that noone shałł passe, <MILESTONE N="2892"/></L>
<L>For x lurdeyns of Fraunce were he<ABBR>r</ABBR>; <NOTE PLACE="marg">and tells them about the 10 knights,</NOTE></L>
<L>God yefe hem evell grace!</L>
<L>Thay passed this way to Egramou<ABBR>r</ABBR>; <NOTE PLACE="marg">who had passed there and done so much mischief to the Soudan;</NOTE></L>
<L>Thay haue done the Sowdon̄ grete tene, <MILESTONE N="2896"/></L>
<L>Thay have wonne his toure and his tresou<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>And yet holde thai it, I wene.</L>
<L>Wherfo<ABBR>r</ABBR>, felawes, I arest yoū alle, <NOTE PLACE="marg">therefore he will arrest them all.</NOTE></L>
<L>Tille I knowe, what þat ye bene." <MILESTONE N="2900"/></L>
<L>Sire Focarde brayde oute his swerde witħ-alle, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Sir Focard draws his sword and</NOTE></L>
<L>Wel sore he gan to tene</L>
<L>And saide "fye on̄ the Sarasyne!</L>
<L>For alle thy grete harde hede <MILESTONE N="2904"/></L>
<L>Shaltow never drinke wat<HI REND="italic">er</HI> ner wyne,</L>
<L>By god! thou shalte be dede."</L>
<L>He smote at him witħ egre chere <NOTE PLACE="marg">smites at him.</NOTE></L>
<L>But he gafe thereof right nought. <MILESTONE N="2908"/></L>
<L>"Alas" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Richard "thou combrest vs he<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>By god, that me de<ABBR>r</ABBR> hatħ boghte."</L>
<L>The cheynes yet we<ABBR>r</ABBR> alle faste,</L>
<L>The geaunte wexe nere wode, <MILESTONE N="2912"/></L>
<L>Richard blewe his horne in haste, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Richard blows his horn,</NOTE></L>
<L>That was both shrille and goode.</L>
<L>Kinge Charles hied him anoon̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">and Charles advances.</NOTE></L>
<L><PB N="84" REF="155"/>
Towarde the brigge so longe; <MILESTONE N="2916"/></L>
<L>The Geaunte faught with hem̄ alone,</L>
<L>He was so harde and stronge.</L>
<L>With a Clo<ABBR>g</ABBR> of an̄ Oke he faugħt, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Alagolafre fights them with a great oak club.</NOTE></L>
<L>That was wele bound with stele. <MILESTONE N="2920"/></L>
<L>He slough al þat eve<ABBR>r</ABBR> he raugħt,</L>
<L>So stronge was his dinte to dele.</L>
<L>Richard raught him witħ a bar<ABBR>r</ABBR> of bras, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Richard seizes a bar of brass and knocks him down.</NOTE></L>
<L>That he caught at the gate. <MILESTONE N="2924"/></L>
<L>He brake his legges, he cryed "alas"</L>
<L>And felle alle che<ABBR>k</ABBR>-mate.</L>
<L>Loude than̄ gan̄ he to yelle;</L>
<L>Thay herde him yelle througħ þat Cite, <MILESTONE N="2928"/></L>
<L>Like the grete develle of helle,</L>
<L>And saide "Mahounde, nowe helpe me!" <MILESTONE N="73" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>iiij men him caught the<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">4 men get hold of him</NOTE></L>
<L>So hevy he was and longe, <MILESTONE N="2932"/></L>
<L>And cast him ouer in-to the rive<ABBR>r</ABBR>. <NOTE PLACE="marg">and throw him into the river.</NOTE></L>
<L>Chese he, whither <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">? 'whether.'</NOTE> he wolde swy<HI REND="italic">m</HI>me or gon<ABBR>g</ABBR>!</L>
<L>Anoon̄ thay brast the Chaynes alle, <NOTE PLACE="marg">They loosened the chains;</NOTE></L>
<L>That ouer the brigge were I-drawe. <MILESTONE N="2936"/></L>
<L>The Saresyns ronnen̄ to the walle, <NOTE PLACE="marg">but, the Saracens assembling on the walls of the city, many Christians were slain.</NOTE></L>
<L>Many Cristen̄ men were the<ABBR>r</ABBR> I-slawe.</L>
<L>Than came forth Dam barro<ABBR>k</ABBR>, the bolde,</L>
<L>With a sith<HI REND="italic">e</HI> large and kene, <MILESTONE N="2940"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Alagolafre's wife, Barrock the giantess, comes on with her scythe and mows down all whom she meets.</NOTE></L>
<L>And mewe a-down̄ as þikke as shepe in folde,</L>
<L>That came byforne hir by-dene.</L>
<L>This Barro<ABBR>k</ABBR> was a geaunesse,</L>
<L>And wife she was to Astragote, <MILESTONE N="2944"/></L>
<L>She did the Cristen̄ grete distresse,</L>
<L>She felled downe alle þat she smote.</L>
<L>There durst no man hire sithe abyde,</L>
<L>She grenned like a develle of helle. <MILESTONE N="2948"/></L>
<L>Kinge Charles with a quarel þat tide <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles dashes out her brains,</NOTE></L>
<L>Smote hir, that she lowde gan̄ yelle,</L>
<L><PB N="85" REF="156"/>
Euer <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'over.'</NOTE> the founte througħ-oute the brayn̄;</L>
<L>That cursede fende fille down̄ dede. <MILESTONE N="2952"/></L>
<L>Many a man hade she there slayn̄,</L>
<L>Might she never aftyr ete more brede!</L>
<L>Charles entred in the firste warde <NOTE PLACE="marg">and with 15 knights enters the outer gate of the town,</NOTE></L>
<L>With xv knightis and no moo; <MILESTONE N="2956"/></L>
<L>Of hym his oste toke no garde,</L>
<L>He wende his oste hade entred also. <NOTE PLACE="marg">thinking his army would follow him.</NOTE></L>
<L>The Sarysyns ronne to the gate,</L>
<L>And shet it wonder faste. <MILESTONE N="2960"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">But the gate was instantly closed upon him, and his men came too late.</NOTE></L>
<L>Charles men̄ come to late;</L>
<L>Tho was Charles sore agaste.</L>
<L>Betwene two wardes he was shit,</L>
<L>Defende he him if he can̄! <MILESTONE N="2964"/></L>
<L>The Sarysyns with him thay mette, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles was in great danger;</NOTE></L>
<L>Grete parel was he in than̄.</L>
<L>Tho Genelyne saie, the kinge was inne <NOTE PLACE="marg">but Genelyn, seeing him shut in,</NOTE></L>
<L>And the yates faste I-stoke, <MILESTONE N="2968"/></L>
<L>Ther myght no man̄ to him wynne,</L>
<L>So was he faste witħ-inne I-loke,</L>
<L>To his frendes he gan speke</L>
<L>And saide "the kinge is dede, <MILESTONE N="2973"/> <MILESTONE N="74" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>And alle xij peres eke. <NOTE PLACE="marg">exclaimed that the king and the 12 peers were dead, and proposed to retire,</NOTE></L>
<L>On peyne" said he "to lese my<HI REND="italic">n</HI> hede,</L>
<L>Let vs hye to Fraunce warde!</L>
<L>For I wele be crownede kinge, <MILESTONE N="2976"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">as he wished to be king himself.</NOTE></L>
<L>I shalle yoū alle wele rewarde,</L>
<L>For I wole spare for no thinge."</L>
<L>Anoon̄ thay assented to Genelyne,</L>
<L>Thay saugh, ther was no bett<HI REND="italic">er</HI> rede. <MILESTONE N="2980"/></L>
<L>The Frenssh men̄ drewe hem̄ al ayene, <NOTE PLACE="marg">They are going to return,</NOTE></L>
<L>Thay wende the kinge hade bene dedde.</L>
<L>Tho Ferumbras witħ his meyne than̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">but Ferumbras</NOTE></L>
<L>Came for to seke the kinge, <MILESTONE N="2984"/></L>
<L>And saugh hem turne eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>y man̄;</L>
<L><PB N="86" REF="157"/>
Him thought, it was a wondir thin<ABBR>g</ABBR>.</L>
<L>"Where is the kinge?" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Ferumbras.</L>
<L>Q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Genelyne "with-in the walle, <MILESTONE N="2988"/></L>
<L>Shaltowe neue<ABBR>r</ABBR> more seen̄ his face!"</L>
<L>"God gyf the an̄ yvel falle!</L>
<L>Turne agayne, thoū traytoure! <NOTE PLACE="marg">calls him a traitour,</NOTE></L>
<L>And helpe to reskowe thy lorde. <MILESTONE N="2992"/></L>
<L>And ye, sires, alle for you<ABBR>r</ABBR> honou<ABBR>r</ABBR>!" <NOTE PLACE="marg">rallies the French,</NOTE></L>
<L>Thay turned agayne with that worde.</L>
<L>Ferumbras with axe in honde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and with his axe bursts open the gate.</NOTE></L>
<L>Myghtyly brake up the gate, <MILESTONE N="2996"/></L>
<L>Ther myght laste him noon̄ yron̄ bonde,</L>
<L>He hade ne<ABBR>r</ABBR>-honde I-come to late.</L>
<L>The kinge hadde fought so longe witħ-ynne,</L>
<L>That onnethe myght he no more. <MILESTONE N="3000"/></L>
<L>Many ther were abouten̄ him,</L>
<L>His men̄ were wounded ful sore.</L>
<L>Ferumbras came with gode spede,</L>
<L>He made the Sarasyns to fle. <MILESTONE N="3004"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">He chased the Saracens and rescued the king.</NOTE></L>
<L>He reskowed the kinge at his nede,</L>
<L>XL Sarasyns sone killed he.</L>
<L>Thai ronnen a-weye by every side,</L>
<L>Thai durste nowhe<ABBR>r</ABBR> rowte. <MILESTONE N="3008"/></L>
<L>In shorte tyme was falled her pride,</L>
<L>Thay caught many a sore cloute.</L>
<L>That Cite was wo<HI REND="italic">n</HI>ne that same daye, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Mantrible is taken,</NOTE></L>
<L>And every tou<ABBR>r</ABBR> ther-ynne <MILESTONE N="3012"/></L>
<L>Of Mountreble, þat was so gaye,</L>
<L>For alle he<ABBR>r</ABBR> soubtile gynne, <MILESTONE N="75" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Fulle of tresou<ABBR>r</ABBR> and richesse, <NOTE PLACE="marg">with all its engines and treasures.</NOTE></L>
<L>Of Siluer and goolde and per<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <MILESTONE N="3016"/></L>
<L>And clothes of goolde, wroght of Saresynes,</L>
<L>Of riche aray and roialte.</L>
<L>Richarde, Duke of Normandy, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Richard found 2 children of 7 months old and</NOTE></L>
<L>Founde ij Children of .vij. monþes oolde, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">See the note.</NOTE> <MILESTONE N="3020"/></L>
<L><PB N="87" REF="158"/>
xiiij fote longe we<ABBR>r</ABBR> thay, <NOTE PLACE="marg">4 feet high.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thay we<ABBR>r</ABBR> Barrakes so<HI REND="italic">n</HI>nes so boolde; <NOTE PLACE="marg">They were sons of Barrock, begotten by Astragot.</NOTE></L>
<L>Bygote thay we<ABBR>r</ABBR> of Astragot.</L>
<L>Grete joye the kinge of he<HI REND="italic">m</HI> hade. <MILESTONE N="3024"/></L>
<L>Hethen̄ thay we<ABBR>r</ABBR> botħ, wele I wote,</L>
<L>Therfore hem̄ to be cristenede he bade. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles caused them to be baptized, and called the one Roland and the other Oliver.</NOTE></L>
<L>He called þat one of hem Roulande,</L>
<L>And that other he cleped Olyue<ABBR>r</ABBR>: <MILESTONE N="3028"/></L>
<L>"For thai shalle be myghty men of honde."</L>
<L>To kepen̄ hem, he was fulle chere.</L>
<L>Thay myght not leve, her Dam was dede; <NOTE PLACE="marg">But they soon died</NOTE></L>
<L>Thai coude not kepe hem fortħ. <MILESTONE N="3032"/></L>
<L>Thai wolde neyþer ete butt<HI REND="italic">er</HI> nere brede,</L>
<L>Ner no men̄ <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'mete.'</NOTE> was to hem worthe.</L>
<L>He<ABBR>r</ABBR> Da<HI REND="italic">m</HI>mes mylke they lakked the<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <NOTE PLACE="marg">for want of their mother's milk.</NOTE></L>
<L>Thay deyden for defaute of here dam. <MILESTONE N="3036"/></L>
<L>Kinge Charles made hevy che<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>And a sory man̄ was than.</L>
<L>The kinge lete ordeyne anoon̄,</L>
<L>The Cite to be gouerne<ABBR>d</ABBR> <MILESTONE N="3040"/></L>
<L>Of the worthyest of hem̄ ychon̄,</L>
<L>That weren of wer<ABBR>r</ABBR> best lerne<ABBR>d</ABBR>.</L>
<L>Duke Richarde of Normandy, <NOTE PLACE="marg">The king appoints Richard governor of the city,</NOTE></L>
<L>He was made chief gou<HI REND="italic">er</HI>nou<ABBR>r</ABBR>; <MILESTONE N="3044"/></L>
<L>And ij C with him in hys company</L>
<L>To kepe the brigge and tou<ABBR>r</ABBR>.</L>
<L>Fortħ he rode to laban̄ than̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and hurries on to Agremore with his army and with Ferumbras.</NOTE></L>
<L>With his Ooste and Si<ABBR>r</ABBR> Ferumbras. <MILESTONE N="3048"/></L>
<L>A spye to the Sowdon̄ fast ran</L>
<L>And tolde him al that cas,</L>
<L>How Charles was come with his ost,</L>
<L>And Mountrible hade he wonne, <MILESTONE N="3052"/></L>
<L>"Alagolofur slayn̄ is for alle his bost,</L>
<L>This game was evel begon̄."</L>
<L>Whane laban herde of his comynge,</L>
<L><PB N="88" REF="159"/>
Him thought his herte gan breke. <MILESTONE N="3056"/></L>
<L>"Shalle I never be withoute moornynge, <MILESTONE N="76" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Tille I of him be wreke."</L>
<L>He co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>maunded to blowe his Claryons</L>
<L>To assemble alle his Ooste. <MILESTONE N="3060"/></L>
<L>His counsaile to him he lete calle</L>
<L>And tolde, how kinge Charles was in þat coost, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Laban, being told by a spy that his city was taken and the bridge∣ward killed,</NOTE></L>
<L>Hadde wonne Mountrible and slayn̄ his men</L>
<L>"And dishirytħ to disheryte me, <MILESTONE N="3064"/></L>
<L>And proudely manessith me to fleen̄,</L>
<L>Or drive me oute of this contr<HI REND="italic">e.</HI></L>
<L>Me mervaylythe moch of his pride.</L>
<L>By Mahounde, moost of mygħt! <MILESTONE N="3068"/></L>
<L>Ye and my sone withe him doth ride,</L>
<L>To the develle I hem bedigħt.</L>
<L>But I be venget of hem both <NOTE PLACE="marg">swears to avenge him.</NOTE></L>
<L>And honge hem̄ on a tree, <MILESTONE N="3072"/></L>
<L>To myghty Mahounde I make myne othe,</L>
<L>Shalle I never Joyfulle be.</L>
<L>Therfore I charge yoū in alle wyse <NOTE PLACE="marg">He calls a council, and charges his barons to take Charles alive that he might flay him.</NOTE></L>
<L>That thay be taken or slayn̄. <MILESTONE N="3076"/></L>
<L>Thane shalle I py<HI REND="italic">n</HI>ne heme at my gyse</L>
<L>And don̄ hem alle qwike be flayn̄."</L>
<L>On the morowe, whan it was day, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles approaches.</NOTE></L>
<L>Kinge Charles was in the felde, <MILESTONE N="3080"/></L>
<L>Byfore Agremou<ABBR>r</ABBR> in riche aray</L>
<L>On stede witħ spe<ABBR>r</ABBR> and sheelde.</L>
<L>Floripe lay on the tou<ABBR>r</ABBR> on̄ hye <NOTE PLACE="marg">Floripas first recognises the banner of France</NOTE></L>
<L>And knewe the bane<ABBR>r</ABBR> of Fraunce. <MILESTONE N="3084"/></L>
<L>To Roulande she gan faste crye</L>
<L>Tidynges of goode chaunce:</L>
<L>"Kinge Charles is comen and Ferumbras, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and tells the others.</NOTE></L>
<L>Here baners botħ I do see, <MILESTONE N="3088"/></L>
<L>With alle her oste yonde<ABBR>r</ABBR> in þat place;</L>
<L>Welcome to vs thay alle be."</L>
<L>Roulande and Olyuere</L>
<L><PB N="89" REF="160"/>
Arayed hem for to ride; <MILESTONE N="3092"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">Roland and all his companions sally forth to meet Charle∣magne.</NOTE></L>
<L>And here felawes alle in fe<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>To Charles thay gon̄ that tyde.</L>
<L>Laban come forth with his mayne, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Laban draws up all his people</NOTE></L>
<L>Saresyns, that were ful felle, <MILESTONE N="3096"/></L>
<L>Turkes, Indens, and Arabye</L>
<L>Ye and of the Ethiopes like the develes of helle.</L>
<L>There were stronge wardes sette <MILESTONE N="77" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>By ordynaunce of dyuers batayle. <MILESTONE N="3100"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">in battle-order.</NOTE></L>
<L>Whan thay to geder were met,</L>
<L>Eythir othir sore gan̄ assayle.</L>
<L>Ther were Saresyns al to-hewe; <NOTE PLACE="marg">The French make a great slaughter of the Saracens.</NOTE></L>
<L>Roulande sloughe many one. <MILESTONE N="3104"/></L>
<L>Thay lay so thikke dede on rewe,</L>
<L>That onneþe myghte men ride or goon̄.</L>
<L>Kinge Charles met with Laban̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles encounters the Soudan, unhorses him,</NOTE></L>
<L>And bare him down̄ of his stede, <MILESTONE N="3108"/></L>
<L>He lighted down̄ and ceased him than̄,</L>
<L>He thought to qwite him his mede.</L>
<L>He brayde oute Mown̄joye wytħ gode wille</L>
<L>And wolde have smeten of his hede, <MILESTONE N="3112"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">and would have cut off his head, but for Ferumbras, who requested that his father might be baptized. The Saracens, seeing Laban a prisoner, fly;</NOTE></L>
<L>Ferumbras prayde him to abyde stille,</L>
<L>To crysten̄ him, er he we<ABBR>r</ABBR> dede.</L>
<L>The Saresyns saughe Laban take,</L>
<L>Thay fledden̄ away fulle faste. <MILESTONE N="3116"/></L>
<L>Lenger durste thay no maistryes make,</L>
<L>Thai were so sore agaste.</L>
<L>The Cristen̄ hem chased to and fro, <NOTE PLACE="marg">but the Christians pursue them.</NOTE></L>
<L>As a grehounde doth the hare. <MILESTONE N="3120"/></L>
<L>.iij. c. ascaped with moche woo, <NOTE PLACE="marg">300 escaped to Belmarine.</NOTE></L>
<L>To Belmore gan thay fa<ABBR>r</ABBR>.</L>
<L>Kinge Charles ladde Laban̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles leads Laban to Agremore.</NOTE></L>
<L>In-to Agremou<ABBR>r</ABBR> Cite. <MILESTONE N="3124"/></L>
<L>And whan̄ þat he the<ABBR>r</ABBR> came</L>
<L>A ful sory man was he. <NOTE PLACE="marg">Floripas wel∣comes her father,</NOTE></L>
<L>His doghter welcomed him</L>
<L><PB N="90" REF="161"/>
W<HI REND="italic">i</HI>t<HI REND="italic">h</HI> right gode che<ABBR>r</ABBR>. <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">These two lines are written as one in the MS.</NOTE> <MILESTONE N="3128"/></L>
<L>He loked on hir al grymme, <NOTE PLACE="marg">but he is enraged at seeing her.</NOTE></L>
<L>As he wode wroth we<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>And saide "fye on the, stronge hore,</L>
<L>Mahounde confounde the!" <MILESTONE N="3132"/></L>
<L>Charles saide "here-of no more,</L>
<L>But let us nowe mery be!"—</L>
<L>"Sir" she saide thanne, <NOTE PLACE="marg">She then bids Charlemagne welcome,</NOTE></L>
<L>"Welcome ye be into this tou<ABBR>r</ABBR>! <MILESTONE N="3136"/></L>
<L>Here I presente to you, as I can, <NOTE PLACE="marg">and presents the holy relics to him.</NOTE></L>
<L>Relikes of grete honou<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>That were at Rome I-wonnen̄</L>
<L>And broght into this halle. <MILESTONE N="3140"/></L>
<L>That game was evel bygo<HI REND="italic">n</HI>nen̄,</L>
<L>It sithen rewed us alle." <MILESTONE N="78" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>Kinge Charles kneled adown̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles kisses them, and says a prayer;</NOTE></L>
<L>To kisse the Relikes so goode, <MILESTONE N="3144"/></L>
<L>And badde the<ABBR>r</ABBR> an̄ oryson̄</L>
<L>To that lorde, þat deyde on̄ rode.</L>
<L>And þanked Floripe witħ al his herte, <NOTE PLACE="marg">he then thanks Floripas for her assistance to his knights,</NOTE></L>
<L>That she hade saued his meyne <MILESTONE N="3148"/></L>
<L>And holpe hem oute of peynes smerte</L>
<L>And kepte the Relekes so fre. <NOTE PLACE="marg">and for having preserved the precious relics.</NOTE></L>
<L>Kinge Charles did calle bisshop<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Turpyn̄</L>
<L>And bade him ordeyne a grete fat, <MILESTONE N="3152"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">He orders Turpin to prepare a vessel,</NOTE></L>
<L>To baptyse the Sowdon̄ yne;</L>
<L>"And loke what he shalle hat. <NOTE PLACE="marg">wherein to bap∣tize the Soudan</NOTE></L>
<L>Unarme him faste and bringe him ne<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>I shal his godfader be. <MILESTONE N="3156"/></L>
<L>Fille it fulle of wate<ABBR>r</ABBR> cle<ABBR>r</ABBR>,</L>
<L>For Baptysed shalle he be.</L>
<L>Make him naked as a Childe,</L>
<L>He moste plunge ther-inne. <MILESTONE N="3160"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">and to wash off his sin in the water.</NOTE></L>
<L>For now most he be meke and mylde,</L>
<L>And I-wassh awaye his synne."</L>
<L><PB N="91" REF="162"/>
Turpyn toke him by the honde <NOTE PLACE="marg">Turpin leads Laban to the font,</NOTE></L>
<L>And ladde him to the fonte. <MILESTONE N="3164"/></L>
<L>He smote the bisshope witħ a bronde <NOTE PLACE="marg">but the Soudan strikes at him,</NOTE></L>
<L>And gaf him an evel bronte.</L>
<L>He spitted in the water cle<ABBR>r</ABBR> <NOTE PLACE="marg">spits on the vessel,</NOTE></L>
<L>And cryed oute on hem alle, <MILESTONE N="3168"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">utters invectives against all Christians,</NOTE></L>
<L>And defied alle þat cristen̄ we<ABBR>r</ABBR>.</L>
<L>That foule mote him by-falle!</L>
<L>"Ye and thoū, hore serpentyne,</L>
<L>And that fals cursed Ferumbras, <MILESTONE N="3172"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">and curses Ferumbras.</NOTE></L>
<L>Mahounde gyfe hem botħ evel endyn<ABBR>g</ABBR>,</L>
<L>And almyghty Sathanas!</L>
<L>By you came all my sorowe,</L>
<L>And al my tresure for-lorne. <MILESTONE N="3176"/></L>
<L>Honged be ye both er tomorowe!</L>
<L>In cursed tyme were ye born̄."</L>
<L>Ferumbras saide to the kinge,</L>
<L>"Sir, ye see, it wole not be, <MILESTONE N="3180"/></L>
<L>Lete him take his endynge,</L>
<L>For he loueth not Cristyante."</L>
<L>"Duke Neymes" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d Charles tho, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles com∣mands Naymes to cut off his head.</NOTE></L>
<L>"Loke þat execucion̄ be don̄, <MILESTONE N="3184"/></L>
<L>Smyte of his hedde! god gyfe him woo! <MILESTONE N="79" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>And goo we to mete anoone."</L>
<L>It was done as the kinge co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>maunde, <NOTE PLACE="marg">He is executed; his soul goes to hell,</NOTE></L>
<L>His soule was fet to helle, <MILESTONE N="3188"/></L>
<L>To daunse in þat sory lande <NOTE PLACE="marg">there to dance with devils.</NOTE></L>
<L>With develes, þat we<ABBR>r</ABBR> ful felle.</L>
<L>Dame Florip was Baptysed than̄ <NOTE PLACE="marg">Floripas was baptized with all her maidens, and wedded to Guy.</NOTE></L>
<L>And here maydyns alle, <MILESTONE N="3192"/></L>
<L>And to Sir Gye I-maryed.</L>
<L>The Barons honoured hir alle.</L>
<L>Alle the londe of Spayne <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles divided Spain between Guy and Ferumbras,</NOTE></L>
<L>Kinge Charles gyfe hem̄ two, <MILESTONE N="3196"/></L>
<L>To departe bitwyxt hem twayne,</L>
<L>Ferumbras and Gȳ also.</L>
<L><PB N="92" REF="163"/>
And so thay livede in ioye and game,</L>
<L>And brethern̄ both thay we<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <MILESTONE N="3200"/></L>
<L>In pees and wer<ABBR>r</ABBR> both I-same,</L>
<L>The<ABBR>r</ABBR> durste no man̄ hem de<ABBR>r</ABBR>.</L>
<L>Kinge Charles turned home agayn̄</L>
<L>Towarde his contr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> <MILESTONE N="3204"/></L>
<L>He charged Sir Brye<ABBR>r</ABBR> of Bretayne <NOTE PLACE="marg">and charges Sir Bryer of Bretayne to take care of the relics,</NOTE></L>
<L>His tresoure<ABBR>r</ABBR> for to be:</L>
<L>To kepe the Relikes of grete pris</L>
<L>And his other tresou<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <MILESTONE N="3208"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">and to bring all his treasure to Paris.</NOTE></L>
<L>And bringe hem safe to Parys,</L>
<L>There to a-bide in store.</L>
<L>He saide "farewell, Sir Ferumbras,</L>
<L>Ye and Gye, my dere frende! <MILESTONE N="3212"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">After taking leave of Guy and Floripas,</NOTE></L>
<L>And thy wyf Dame Floripas!</L>
<L>For to Fraunce nowe wole I wende.</L>
<L>Be ye togeder as breth[e]rn̄ botħ!</L>
<L>No man̄ ye neditħ to drede, <MILESTONE N="3216"/></L>
<L>Be ye nevere to-gedere wrotħ,</L>
<L>But eyther helpe othir at his nede.</L>
<L>Vysityth me, whan̄ ye haue space;</L>
<L>In-to Fraunce makitħ your disporte, <MILESTONE N="3220"/></L>
<L>God wole you sende the bett<HI REND="italic">er</HI> grace,</L>
<L>In age to do me comforte."</L>
<L>Thai toke leve of the kinge,</L>
<L>With ful hevy che<ABBR>r</ABBR>, <MILESTONE N="3224"/></L>
<L>And turned agayn̄ botħ mornynge,</L>
<L>With wepynge water cle<ABBR>r</ABBR>.</L>
<L>Kinge Charles with the victory <NOTE PLACE="marg">he sails to Moun∣peler,</NOTE></L>
<L>Sailed to Mou<HI REND="italic">n</HI>peleres, <MILESTONE N="3228"/></L>
<L>And thanked almyghty god in glorye, <MILESTONE N="80" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>That he hade saued his Dosiperes, <NOTE PLACE="marg">where he thanks God for the victory,</NOTE></L>
<L>And fende him of the Saresynes</L>
<L>The hyer honde to have, <MILESTONE N="3232"/></L>
<L>For alle here strenghe <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">Read:</HI> 'streng<HI REND="italic">t</HI>he.'</NOTE> and he<ABBR>r</ABBR> Engynes</L>
<L><PB N="93" REF="164"/>
The Relikes of Rome to saue. <NOTE PLACE="marg">and for the relies.</NOTE></L>
<L>At oure lady of Parys <NOTE PLACE="marg">He presents the cross to Paris,</NOTE></L>
<L>He offred the Crosse so fre; <MILESTONE N="3236"/></L>
<L>The Crown̄ he offred at seynte Denyse, <NOTE PLACE="marg">the Crown to St. Denis, the three nails to Boulogne.</NOTE></L>
<L>At Boloyne the nayles thr<HI REND="italic">e.</HI></L>
<L>Alle his Barons of him we<ABBR>r</ABBR> gladd,</L>
<L>Thai gafe him grete presente. <MILESTONE N="3240"/></L>
<L>For he so wele hade I-spedde,</L>
<L>Thay did him grete reuerence.</L>
<L>The kinge hade wel in mynde <NOTE PLACE="marg">Charles well remembered the treachery of Genelyn,</NOTE></L>
<L>The tresone of Genelyne, <MILESTONE N="3244"/></L>
<L>Anoon̄ for him he dide sende</L>
<L>To yefe him an evel fyne:</L>
<L>"Thou traito<HI REND="italic">ur</HI> unkynde" q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d the kynge,</L>
<L>"Remembrist thoū not how ofte <MILESTONE N="3248"/></L>
<L>Thou hast me betrayed, þ<HI REND="italic">o</HI>u fals Genelyne?</L>
<L>Therfore thoue shalt be honged on lofte!—</L>
<L>Loke that the execucion̄ be don̄,</L>
<L>That throgh Parys he be drawe, <MILESTONE N="3252"/> <NOTE PLACE="marg">and ordered him to be drawn and hanged at Montfaucon in Paris.</NOTE></L>
<L>And honged on hye on mou<HI REND="italic">n</HI>t Fawcon̄,</L>
<L>As longeth to traytoures by lawe;</L>
<L>That alle men shall take hede,</L>
<L>What deth trayto<HI REND="italic">ur</HI>ys shałł fele, <MILESTONE N="3256"/></L>
<L>That assente to such falshede,</L>
<L>Howe the wynde here bodyes shal kele."</L>
<L>Thus Charles conquered Laban̄, <NOTE PLACE="marg">Thus Charles conquered the Soudan of Babylone.</NOTE></L>
<L>The Sowdon̄ of Babyloyne, <MILESTONE N="3260"/></L>
<L>That riche Rome stroyed and wan̄</L>
<L>And alle the brode londe of Spayn̄.</L>
<L><NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">A corner of the leaf torn off.</NOTE> . . . . . .[an]d of his Barons</L>
<L>. . . . . . .[hi]s pride <MILESTONE N="3264"/></L>
<L>. . . . . . . .eligons</L>
<L>. . . . . . . .þat tyde</L>
<L>. . . . . . .on Charles soule</L>
<L>. . . . . . .s also <MILESTONE N="3268"/></L>
<L><PB N="94" REF="165"/>
. . . . . . .Peter and Poule</L>
<L>God lete hem never wete of woo! <MILESTONE N="81" UNIT="leaf"/></L>
<L>But brynge here soules to goode reste!</L>
<L>That were so worthy in dede. <MILESTONE N="3272"/></L>
<L>And gyf vs ioye of the beste, <NOTE PLACE="marg">God give joy to all who read this romance.</NOTE></L>
<L>That of here gestes rede!</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>Here endithe the Romaunce of the Sowdon of Babyloyne and of Ferumbras his sone who conquerede Rome, And Kynge Charles off Fraunce withe xij. Dosyperes toke the Sowdon in the feelde And smote of his heede.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>
