<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE><DATE>8-29-16</DATE><RESPSTMT><NAME>lattaj</NAME><RESP>MURP</RESP></RESPSTMT><ITEM>Added TEMPHEAD, checked ID, and added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Proofed title page. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure; removed incorrect MILESTONEs; changed pars to Verbars; changed pipes to verbars; changed numerous 7s to ampersands; changed some DIV3s to DIV2s; changed some DIV4s to DIV3s; changed sub HEADs to HEADNOTE Ps; added HEAD; added some Qs. Checked placement and completeness of PBs; added some missing PBs for lengthy NOTEs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected [dollar]s. Checked for &amp;cs with incorrect spacing. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs and endqs, abq's, oes, qs, Ae's, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections. Checked italic I / J and U / V. Checked for missing page GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTS. Checked CLOSERs, OPENERs, SIGNEDs, SALUTEs, TRAILERs, BYLINEs. Checked decorated initials. Checked FIGUREs. Sample: 2 minutes. Proofing: 0 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 50 minutes. DONE.</ITEM></CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="CME00061">
<STC T="M">61</STC>
<BIBNO T="mec">CME00061</BIBNO>
<VID>CME00061</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="enm ger lat">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="collection of legends">
<PB REF="1"/>
<HEAD>PROSALEGENDEN.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="preface">
<HEAD>I. Caxton's ausgabe der h. Wenefreda.</HEAD>
<P>Diese ausgabe Caxton's, mit dem ganzen apparate einer kirchlichen legende, scheint der grossen nachfrage seiner zeit∣genossen nach dem leben dieser damals besonderer verehrung geniessenden heiligen ihren ursprung zu verdanken. In der tat war diese heilige (angeblich im 7. jhdt. enthauptet), von der die früheren historiker schweigen, wol weil sie Celtischen ursprungs (aus Wales) und als solche den Sachsen und Nor∣mannen unannehmbar war, im 14. und 15. jhdt. in ganz Eng∣land so populär geworden, dass kein wallfahrtsort besuchter war als die h. quelle der W., die an dem orte entsprungen sein sollte, an welchem bei ihrer enthauptung ihr kopf niederfiel; die zahlreichen wunderbaren heilungen mit dem wasser dieser (stahlhaltigen) quelle wurden dieser h. jungfrau zugeschrieben. Bereits im anfang des 15. jhdts. hatte Johann Mirkus, canonikus des klosters zu Lilleshul in Shropshire, in seinem berühmten (nachmals auch von Caxton zweimal 1483 [Edit. princ.] und 1490 [?] gedruckten) buche The Festiall <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Beste hs.: Ms. Cott. Claud. A II (kurz nach dem tode des ver∣fassers von drei verschiedenen händen geschrieben im dialect von Shrop∣shire); andere ältere hss.: Lansd. 392, Caj. Coll. Cambr. 168, Harl. 2403, ms. Shrewsb.; mit Caxton's ausg. stimmt am meisten überein ms. Harl. 2391; mehrere hss. sind nach drucken gefertigt (z. b. ms. John's Coll. Cbr. 9, 19 nach der ausgabe Rouen 1499). Dieses vortreffliche buch hat am ausgang des mittelalters nicht weniger als 18 ausgaben erlebt. Die ausgaben unterscheiden sich von den ältern hss. dadurch, dass in jenem die die feste Christi betreffenden sermones (das 'Temporale') ver∣einigt vorangehen, während in diesem die feste Christi und die der heiligen vermischt sind und nach dem datum aufeinanderfolgen. Die ausgaben scheinen in ihrer folge von einander abhängig zu sein und sind nicht ganz gleichlautend. Es ist seltsam, dass dieses berühmte werk des Joh. Mirkus bis jetzt so gut wie unbekannt geblieben ist. Seine quelle ist die Leg. Aur. (die, bis auf wenige, gemeinsame quelle aller legenden des 14. und 15. jhdts.), aus der er nach belieben ausge∣wählt hat.</NOTE> unter
<PB N="294" REF="2"/>
dem festtage dieser heiligen ihr leben in der volkssprache er∣zählt. Diese version scheint jedoch Caxton, der jenes buch nach einer späteren hs. edierte, worin die lokalheiligen des Mirkus: Wenefrede und Alkmond (patron des klosters zu Lilleshul) ausgelassen waren (vgl. ms. Harl. 2391), unbekannt geblieben zu sein, wenigstens zeigt sein text keine übereinstimmung mit dem des Festiall (dieser ist kürzer, fügt aber am ende drei miracula hinzu). Auch der text in der Leg. Aur., sowie der bericht Higden's in seinem Polychronicon (dieser erzählt z. b. auch das schreckliche ende der kinder des versuchers, prinzen Cradok) sind in manchen einzelheiten abweichend. Vielleicht war Caxton's quelle das Latein. leben der h. Wenefreda von Robert, prior von Shrewsbury (c. 1140); die noch ältere vita in ms. Claud. A V (c. 1100), welche dem h. Elerius, beicht∣vater der h. W., zugeschrieben wird, weicht in wichtigen einzel∣heiten ab; natürlich fehlt hier auch die Translatio nach Shrews∣bury (i. j. 1138) und die Latein. Commemoratio, welche i. j. 1380 vom erzbischof Arundel eingerichtet wurde, vgl. W. Blades Life and Typography of W. Caxton.—Caxton's ausgabe, ohne titelblatt, o. o. u. z., ist nur in 3 exemplaren vorhanden: eins im Brit. Mus. (C 11. b 11), eins in Lambeth (zusammen∣gebunden mit ms. Lamb. 306, fol. 188; an diesem fehlt das letzte blatt; fol. 194 und 195 sind verkehrt gebunden; der text ist mehrfach von anderer hand corrigirt), und eins im besitze des Earl Dysart. Der text ist nicht ohne einige fehler. Caxton wendet noch manche abbreviationszeichen an: so ̄ für n, w<SUP>t</SUP> = w<HI REND="italic">ith,</HI> þ<SUP>t</SUP> = þ<HI REND="italic">at,</HI> diese sind im nachfolgenden abdruck auf∣gelöst; die häkchen an g, d, h, n, welche ursprünglich <HI REND="italic">e</HI> bezeichnen sollen, sind so unregelmässig und ohne princip verwendet (sie fehlen fast ebenso oft in denselben wörtern und endungen), dass sie hier nicht wiedergegeben sind. Auch im gebrauch grosser anfangsbuchstaben befolgt Caxton kein festes princip. Die längsstriche theilen nicht nur sätze, son∣dern auch satzteile an, ohne die fehlende interpunction zu er∣setzen.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="legend">
<PB N="295" REF="3"/>
<HEAD>I. Caxton's ausgabe der leg. von S. Wenefreda</HEAD>
<HEADNOTE><P>nach der copie in Lamb. 306 fol. 188. (1485?)</P></HEADNOTE>
<DIV3 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>¶ <HI REND="italic">here begynneth the lyf of the holy &amp; blessid vyrgyn saynt Wenefryde.</HI></HEAD> 
<P>I-N the west ende of grete Britayn, | whiche now is callyd Englond, <MILESTONE N="(I)"/> is a prouynce whiche is named Walys. | This said prouynce was somtyme inhabyted of sayntes, of many &amp; dyuerse merytes, | &amp; em∣bellisshed &amp; decorate vnto this day with Innumerable prerogatyuys <MILESTONE N="5"/> in many wyses. | Emo<HI REND="italic">n</HI>g whom ther was an holy &amp; deuout ma<HI REND="italic">n,</HI> named Beunow, | a ma<HI REND="italic">n</HI> of hye merite, | &amp; this holy man lad <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">In Lamb. ist <HI REND="italic">a</HI> von anderer hand zugesetzt.</NOTE> religious lyf | &amp; was a monk in the said <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Von and. hand am rande nebengeschr.: <HI REND="italic">provynce of walys</HI> &amp; <HI REND="italic">a parte now of.</HI></NOTE> Englond; | he edyffyed chirches &amp; ordeyned certayn bretheren &amp; prestes, for to serue god, in many places. | &amp; hit was so | þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> by dyuyn prouydence he was warned &amp; <MILESTONE N="10"/> admonested to desyre &amp; aske of a myȝty man, named Theuith, a certeyn place to byle on a chirch for his helthe. | Which he dylig∣e<HI REND="italic">n</HI>tly dema<HI REND="italic">n</HI>ded, | &amp; the seid Theuith grau<HI REND="italic">n</HI>ted to hym gladly &amp; with good wil, | &amp; also co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>mysed <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">In L verbessert v. a. hand <HI REND="italic">commy</HI>tt<HI REND="italic">ed,</HI> das exemplar im Brit. Mus. liest <HI REND="italic">cōmysed.</HI></NOTE> to hym his douȝter, named We∣nefrede, whome he louyd tenderly, for to be instruct &amp; tauȝt, | pray∣eng <MILESTONE N="15"/> hym to biseche almyȝty god | that he wold dispose her conuersa∣cion to the wil &amp; honour of hym. | Which thyng god knowyng what shold folowe therof, wold not suffre her to be lost ne perisshed. | For the maide Wenefrede desyred by an ardau<HI REND="italic">n</HI>t desyre to be the temple of god in tyme comyng; | and suche thynges as she vnder∣stode <MILESTONE N="20"/> by heryng of her eres, she held &amp; enprynted fast in her mynde, &amp; that she conceyued in her thouȝt | purposed verily tacco<HI REND="italic">m</HI>plysshe hastely in werkes. | So thenne by thynspyracion of the holy ghost this holy vyrgyn prouffytyng in vertues shewed vnto her mayster Beunow the very purpose of her mynde, sayeng: | 'I haue deter∣myned <MILESTONE N="25"/> in my self to forsake al the lust &amp; plaisir of the world, | &amp; haue disposed to conserue &amp; kepe my virgynyte vndefowled vnto Cryst: | whiche thyng, o holy fader, I byseche the deuoutely that thou wylt impetre &amp; gete grau<HI REND="italic">n</HI>te of my fader &amp; moder'. | Whiche thynge he shewed to hem, | &amp; they gladly consentid | &amp; therwyth <MILESTONE N="30"/> were wel pleasid. | Thenne this holy vyrgyn recordyng &amp; desyryng tenprynte in her mynde suche holy wordes &amp; lesso<HI REND="italic">n</HI>s as floweden oute of the mouth of her mayster, | suffred none erthely ne worldly vanytees to entre in to her, | but laye oft in the nyȝtes in the chirche, | and oftyme she solycyted the holy man to make a sermon | <MILESTONE N="35"/> and to treate to her of her spouse Jhesu Crist | &amp; to shewe his werkes digne &amp; worthy of laude &amp; praysynge. | ¶ It happed on a sonday that her fader &amp; moder were gone to the chirche | &amp; this blessid virgyne was lefte for certayn cause at home: | &amp; one named
<PB N="296" REF="4"/>
Cradoke, sone of kyng Alane, entryd &amp; sawe this holy virgyne syttyng by the fyre. | Whiche anone, | as she sawe the kynges sone, | aroos | &amp; humbly demaunded hym what was his playsir. | And he sayd to her: | 'Thou knowest well that I am a kynges sone, | whiche haue plente of rychesses &amp; honours: | &amp; of them shalle de∣parte <MILESTONE N="5"/> | largely to the, yf thou wylt consente to my peticion &amp; de∣syre'. | She anon felyng hym to make his request for to haue a-do with her, | &amp; a lytyll cast doun shamefastly her chere, | dyssy∣mylyd her to be ashamed that he had founden her not well arrayed ne apparaylled, | &amp; sayd to hym: 'suffre a whyle, lest my fader <MILESTONE N="10"/> come, | &amp; I shal go in to my chambre | &amp; shal come to the ageyne withoute taryeng'. | To whiche the yong man graunted. | &amp; she wente in to the chambre, &amp; by a bye-dore of the chambre she wente oute | &amp; ran faste toward the chirche. | Whiche so fleyng was anone knowen to the yong man, | &amp; thenne he beyng wood wroth, <MILESTONE N="15"/> bycause she fledde fro hym, | bycause she wold kepe her virgynyte, | &amp; with a suerd hastely folowed after, &amp; ouertoke her, | &amp; holdyng hir with a sterne chere said to her in this wyse: | 'Somtyme I louyd the | &amp; desyred the | to be ioyned to myn embracementes; | &amp; now thou despysest hym þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> desyreth the? | Now know thow for <MILESTONE N="20"/> certayn | þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> either thou shalt this present tyme suffre me to haue my wyl of the, | or without taryeng I shal smyte of thyn hede with this swerd'. | The holy vyrgyn, hauyng her ful hope &amp; truste in oure lord, answerd hym is this wyse: | 'I am coupled in matrimonye | to the sone of the euerlastyng kyng | &amp; Juge of al men: | wherfor I <MILESTONE N="25"/> may haue none other; | and bycause I wyll not long abuse the: | whyle I lyue, I shal neuer leue ne forsake hym. | &amp; therfor be thou assured | that thy menaces | ne fair wordes, thretenynges | ne pro∣messes, maye departe me fro the swetenes of his loue, | to whos enbracementes | I am strayned &amp; coupled by deuocion'. | This lecher∣ous <MILESTONE N="30"/> yonge man | herynge hym self to be despysed | and put fro his voluptuous desyre, | toke oute his swerd | and smote of the hede | of this blessyd vyrgyne | .</P>
<P>¶ And anone as the hede of the virgyne fylle to the erthe, | in the same place a bryght and fayre welle beganne to sprynge vp, | <MILESTONE N="35"/> largely gyuynge oute water and plentyuously; whiche contynueth to flowe vnto this day, | gyuynge helthe by the merytes of this blessyd vyrgyn to many seke peple &amp; malades. | Now was it so that the place where her hede was smyton <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">the</HI> überschr. von anderer hand in L.</NOTE> of was (the) <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Br. Mus. deutlich <HI REND="italic">smyton.</HI></NOTE> hangyng of an hylle: | &amp; the hede rollyd doun to the chirche dore. | &amp; whan the <MILESTONE N="40"/> peple in the chirche sawe the hede, | there was a grete noyse &amp; rumour. | In so moche that her fader &amp; moder cam, | &amp; sawe how her doughter was biheded. | Wherof they were sore basshed | &amp; made a lamentable noyse &amp; sorow, sayeng that they had hoped | that she shold haue ben a seruaunt of god &amp; to haue lyued an holy lyf. | &amp; <MILESTONE N="45"/>
<PB N="297" REF="5"/>
whan Beunowe herd this noyse and rumour, he cam &amp; sawe this hede of the holy vyrgyn; | &amp; anone he took it vp, | &amp; sawe where the kynges sone stode &amp; wyped his swerd on the grasse. | To whom he said, lokyng in his visage, these wordes: | 'O thou wycked man, | whiche hast defouled thy fair yougth | &amp; arte sone of the <MILESTONE N="5"/> lygnage of a kyng | &amp; hast slayn by cryme as an homycyde this noble vyrgyn, | why repentest the not | that hast commysed so grete a synne? | thou hast troubled the pees | &amp; hast defowled the chirche | by thy sacrylege &amp; hast gretely trespaced &amp; wratthed our lorde, | &amp; repentest the not? | Now for as moch as thou hast not spared the <MILESTONE N="10"/> chirch | ne hast gyuen reuerence to the sonday, | I byseche my lorde god, | to whom thou hast commysed synne vnworthely, | that he rewarde the by digne recompensacion'. | &amp; these wordes said &amp; expressid, | the yong man forthwith fyll doun to therthe &amp; exspyred &amp; deyde. | &amp; incontynent wonderfully the body of hym, so dede, in <MILESTONE N="15"/> the syght &amp; presence of many was molten &amp; vanisshed awey &amp; son∣ke<HI REND="italic">n</HI> (!) in to therthe, | &amp; his soule drowned in helle. | Then<HI REND="italic">n</HI>e the fader &amp; moder hauyng no co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>fort, | but wayllyng the deth of their douhter, | desyred to make bewaillynges. | &amp; the holy ma<HI REND="italic">n</HI> Beunow we<HI REND="italic">n</HI>t to thaulter to say the masse. | Whiche beyng fynysshed | &amp; al <MILESTONE N="20"/> the peple awaityng on hym, | &amp; hauyng hope vnto god, | he went to the body lyeng dede, | &amp; vnto the peple made a sermon, | &amp; emong al other wordes he said how this blessid virgyn had made a vowe to almyȝty god, | but for tacco<HI REND="italic">m</HI>plisshe the same bycause of her deth she had not tyme co<HI REND="italic">n</HI>grue to fulfylle it: | '7 therfor I ex∣horte <MILESTONE N="25"/> &amp; desyre you to knele doun to þe grou<HI REND="italic">n</HI>d &amp; to pray deuoutely vnto almyghty god that of his grace it wold plese hym to reyse her fro deth to lyf, | to thende that many be the better | and more con∣staunt in the faythe | and that moche good shold therof enfolowe'. | ¶ After thenne this longe prayer | the holy man Beunowe aroose vp, <MILESTONE N="30"/> holdyng his hondes vp in to heuen sayde: | 'O lord Jhesu Crist, for whos loue this holy virgyn hath forsaken all worldly thynges | &amp; hath desyred heue<HI REND="italic">n</HI>ly thynges, we humbly byseche the with al oure myght &amp; deuocion that þ<HI REND="italic">ou</HI> at this tyme graunte to vs theffect of our peticion &amp; prayer. | &amp; for what cause this vyrgyne hath suf∣fred <MILESTONE N="35"/> deth, we knowe not, but, that she is in euerlastyng ioyes, | hauyng no nede of oure company; | thou neuertheles, most debonayr fader, graunte to vs, thy son<HI REND="italic">n</HI>es, | mekely besechyng the, benyngne &amp; exaudyble, | that it may please the to gyue thyn assente to oure peticions &amp; prayers: | &amp; commaunde thou that the sowle of this holy <MILESTONE N="40"/> vyrgyne may be brought ageyn to her body | &amp; that she may be restored to her fyrst lyf | and that by the grace of thy mercy may magnefye thy name, | and after longe space of lyf | she may retorne to the, her spouse, | that is the only sone of god the fader, with whome | &amp; with the holy ghost lyuest world without ende'. | &amp; whan <MILESTONE N="45"/> al had answerd amen, | he sette the hede to the body: | &amp; the holy vyrgyne aroos, | as she had arysen fro slepe, | wypyng her visage | &amp; clensynge it fro the duste &amp; swette, | &amp; replenysshed alle the
<PB N="298" REF="6"/>
assistentes stondynge with wonderfull admyracion &amp; ioye. | Neuer∣theles, in the place of her necke, where as her heede was smyten of | and after by dyuyne operacion was sett on ageyn &amp; resoly∣date, | a lytil redenes in maner of a threde wente aboute the necke | and shewed the place where as hit had be cutte of; | and that euer <MILESTONE N="5"/> after abode, for to shewe the absicycion and thostencion of the myracle, | as longe as the vyrgyn lyuyd, | and alwey abode in one maner. | And the place where as her blood was shedde, was callyd fyrst | the 'drye valeye'; | and after that the hede of the holy vyrgyne was cut of and touchyd the ground, | as we <MILESTONE N="10"/> afore haue said, sprang vp a welle of spryngyng water largely, | enduryng vnto this day, | which heleth al languours and sekenesses, as well in men as in bestes: | whiche welle is named after the name of þe vyrgyn &amp; is called saint Wenefredes welle. &amp; bycause ther was moch blood of her shed in þe welle &amp; þe descente of þe <MILESTONE N="15"/> hylle, þe stones yet in to this day appiere as wel in the welle as in the ryuer rennyng doune al besparklyd with blood: | whiche thynge is merueyllous, | ffor yet at this day is sene the droppes of blood, | lyke as hit was the fyrst day; | and the mosse that groweth vpon the sayd stones | smellyth lyke encence. | Whiche welle is <MILESTONE N="20"/> famous and of grete renomme | and well knowen | to al them that goo thyder, | and endureth as it dyd the fyst tyme, | and the stones, as we sayd tofore, ben yet dayly blody | or bespryncte with dropes of blood; | shewynge openly | that by the merytes of the sayd vyr∣gyne | alle they that calle on her for ony nede or dysease, | our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <MILESTONE N="25"/> lord shalle ease and delyuer them.</P>
<P>¶ Thenne forto knowe how this holy vyrgyne Wenefryde lyuyd <MILESTONE N="(II)"/> after that she was reysed fro dethe to lyf, | or what maner of lyf she hadde vnto the ende she departed oute of this world, | ye shalle here al alonge herafter folowynge. | <MILESTONE N="30"/></P>
<P>¶ Thenne after she was thus reysed, as afore is sayd, | alle that daye after she was abydynge at the feet of the holy fader Beunowe | and entended wyth dylygente cure and feruent deuocion vnto his sermons | and to alle thynges that apperteynen to god, | desyrynge with a ardaunt wylle for to be enformed fully to serue &amp; please al∣myghty <MILESTONE N="35"/> god. | Whiche done | &amp; she sufficiently Instructe and enfor∣med, after the lernynge of the disciplyne of the holy Chirche, | fyll doun on her knees &amp; desyred humbly of her mayster to be professyd and to receyue the holy veyle, | sayenge: | 'I may in no wyse departe fro thy feet, vnto the tyme | that thow hast accomplysshed in me <MILESTONE N="40"/> theffect of this holy profession: | &amp; so thou to clothe me outward in thabyte of relygyous disciplyn | &amp; that I may be blessyd by thyn hondes, in suche wyse that I may in the inward thouȝt of my soule perseuere in the seruyse of our blessid lord. Wherfor, holy fader, I hu<HI REND="italic">m</HI>bly byseche the | that thou wil not lenger differre my peticion <MILESTONE N="45"/> ne desyre, | but to fulfylle my requeste, | &amp; incontynent late me make myn auowe, as it apperteyneth'. | ¶ The<HI REND="italic">n</HI>ne this holy man shewed the desyre &amp; wil of this blessid vyrgyn to her fader &amp; moder |
<PB N="299" REF="7"/>
7 said to them | that they shold satisfye the desyre of her, | for she was chosen of god, | &amp; had gyuen to her hys dyuyn grace. | They then<HI REND="italic">n</HI>e benyngnly consentid to þe same, &amp; the holy man thenne to-fore moche peple gaf to her the holy vayll | &amp; professyd her | &amp; halowed in the presence | of them alle. | Whiche blessyd vyrgyne <MILESTONE N="5"/> after thaccomplysshement and vowe made of her holy desyre | anone she flouryd in alle vertue | and deuoutely studyed | how she myght best obserue the rewlys of the disciplyne of Relygyon, | and in short space she acquyred and was ful Instructe in the perfection of alle the obseruaunce that therto bylongeth. | After this this holy man <MILESTONE N="10"/> Beunow was admonesshed by a vysyon | that he shold departe thens | and goo dwelle in another place, | to thende that he myght auaylle and do moche prouffyte to moche peple. | And ther-vpon he called the fader and moder of the blessyd vyrgyne | &amp; sayd to them: | 'Ye shall vnderstande that I must departe from hens | and <MILESTONE N="15"/> may no lenger be here with yow, | ffor god hath callyd me to another place. | Wherfore | I exhorte yow | that ye besyly entende vnto the admonycions and ensamples of youre doughter, | knowynge for certayne that she is not ordeyned an only ensample to yow, | but also a very ensample of helthe vnto alle peple herafter for to <MILESTONE N="20"/> come'. | Thenne he torned hym to the holy vyrgyne | and sayd to her: | 'Our lord, almyghty god, hath commaunded the forto succede and folowe my labours and exercysitees and to honoure this habyt∣acle, | to folowe the weye of lyf | by me to the shewed, | and the same to shewe to other. | Thy charge shall be from hens forth for <MILESTONE N="25"/> the loue of god to haunte and dwelle in this place | and to gadre and assemble vyrgyns to lyue here in the seruyse of god with the. | But one thynge knowe thow for certayne, | that thow shalte not fynysshe thy lyf in this place: | for, whan thow hast seruyd god here in besy abstynence of the body and afflyction of spyryte | by <MILESTONE N="30"/> the space of seuen yere, | hit behoueth the to goo to another place, | whiche shall be shewed to the by oure lord, | and he shal adresse the thyder | where thow shalt enlumyne the derkenesse of many hertes. | And reteyne well | that thy memorye and remembraunce shall be clerly spred in this world, | &amp; as moche thow shalt be more <MILESTONE N="35"/> of meryte | so moche more shall many be remedyed by the of their myseryes and hurtes'. |</P>
<P>Whanne this hooly vyrgyne vnderstode the departynge of her mayster and doctour, | she was moche sorowful and heuy | and wepte sorowfully for his departynge and absence. | Thenne the holy <MILESTONE N="40"/> man Beunowe ladde her by the ryght honde to the welle whiche sprange at the place where her hede fyll<HI REND="italic">e</HI> | whanne hit was smyten of, | wherof we haue tofore remembryd, | and made her to sta<HI REND="italic">n</HI>de vpon a stone | which lyeth there on the brynk of the sayd welle vnto this daye | and is callyd the stone of saynt Beunowe of them <MILESTONE N="45"/> that dwelle there, | and he sayd to her these wordes folowynge: | 'Beholde, sayd he, and see here the steppes of thy passion! | loo, these stones here besprynct with thy blood shewe that thow hast
<PB N="300" REF="8"/>
for goddes loue suffryd here martirdome, | &amp; to the perpetuel honoure of the | &amp; to the monumente of many other they kepe the shedynge of thy blood, of whiche they ben besprynct, | fresshe and rody. | Now, therfore, with a dylygent and good mynde reteyne and kepe my wordes, | that they maye come reuerently to the knowlege of <MILESTONE N="5"/> many other: | knowe thow for certayne | that thre yeftes ben gyuen and graunted to the of almyghty god, | whiche shall be solempnly shewed to the tytle of thy lawde and praysynge | and shalle be arettyd to the loue of thy deuocion in the myndes of them that shalle come herafter. | The fyrste is this: | that the stones besprynct <MILESTONE N="10"/> and wette by sprynclyng of thy bloode | shalle neuer in this world be wasshen awey and putte oute | ne by the swyfte cours of this water be taken awey, | but for euydence and shewyng of thy passion shullen alwey appiere rede and blody, | doynge myracle vnto the glorye of god and of his mageste | and also to the tryumphe of thy <MILESTONE N="15"/> chastyte. | The second yefte or graunt is this: | that, who someuer he be | that is hurte by ony Infortune | and requyreth the <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">the</HI> ist in L. ausgestr.</NOTE> and desyreth to be delyuerd by the | fro his dystresse or oppressyon, | the fyrst, | the second | or the thyrd, | certaynly the thyrdde <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">certaynly the thyrdde</HI> ist in L. ausgestr.</NOTE> tyme, | <MILESTONE N="20"/> yf it be done effectuelly with a good wyll, | he shall enioye that thynge that he demaunded and asked; | and yf hit so happe | that he gete ne haue not that thynge that he desyred | ne that it folowe not after his peticion, | knowe he for certayne | that, yf ther be ony thynge more godly for the helthe of his sowle | than hit that he demaunded, | <MILESTONE N="25"/> þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> it shal folowe &amp; come to hym for his good: | for oftymes we of our frelnes aske and desyre thynges | whiche parauentur shold torne more to our hurte | than to our wele; | god knoweth what is best for vs. | The thyrd yefte is thys: | that, whan now I shal departe &amp; go fro <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">Caxt. <HI REND="italic">for</HI> statt <HI REND="italic">fro.</HI></NOTE> the forto dwelle in a conuenyent place stondynge <MILESTONE N="30"/> on the see-syde, | whiche god of his benygne grace hath graunted to me; | and though hit be soo | that I shalle be ferre fro the, | yet almyghty god hath commaunded the to remembre me euery yere with thy yeftes: | wherfor, when thow wylt adresse to me suche a thynge | as thow shalt make redy for me, | thow shalt hastely come <MILESTONE N="35"/> with thy yeft to this present welle; | and, what someuer it be, | commytte hit fyrste vnto god | and after put it in to this welle confidently: | and thou shalt see anone that thynge, soo putte in, be taken vp fro the welle | and be ledde forth by the myght of god by the cours of the water in to the grete floode, vnhurte; | and by <MILESTONE N="40"/> the wylle of almyghty god thorugh the flodes of the see | it shall come vnto the yate of my lytel lodge or dwellynge by the tornynge of the wawes, vndefowled; | and this behoueth the to doo euery yere, | as longe as god wylle that I shall lyue, | for god commaunded the so to do. | These thre thynges ben graunted to the of oure lord
<PB N="301" REF="9"/>
god, | assigned specially | and gyuen to the by dyuyne prerogatyf; | and as longe as the world shalle endure, | this shalle be magnyfyed to the halowyng of thy memorye and glorye of thy lawde | by the tellynge and vtterynge of moche peple'. | These thynges thus <MILESTONE N="5"/> expressyd and sayd, | the holy man fynally departed fro her. | For whiche cause euery yere the fyrst day of maye she sente to her mayster a yefte, whyle he lyued, in the maner as is afore sayd. | And though soo be that the space bytwene them | and the distaunce was more than fyfty myle, | yet neuertheles in space and tyme of <MILESTONE N="10"/> one nyght | by the rollynge of the wawes and stremes of the see it was brought to the yate of his monasterye | and was founden on the grauell of the Ryuage. | And the fyrste yefte that she sente to hym was a chesyble of her owne makynge, whiche was founden vnhurte | as afore is reherced. | <MILESTONE N="15"/></P>
<P>¶ Hit happed that after this holy man Beunowe beynge aged de∣parted oute of this world and deyde. | Whoos dethe whanne it was told vnto saynt Wenefryde, | she left forto sende more ony yefte to hym. | And she remembrynge his wordes: that she shold after seuen yere goo in to another place forto dwelle in, | and after <MILESTONE N="20"/> seuen yere complete, she departed fro that oracle and place, | lyke as she was warned by the holy man: | and wente vnto seynt Deyfere. | This man was an holy man and grete toward oure lord, kepynge his commaundementes | and not departynge from his Justyfycacions. | And after whan she was come, as he was in the nyght besy in <MILESTONE N="25"/> his prayers and perseuerynge in deuocion, | a voys from heuen souned in his eres, sayeng: | 'Saye thou to my most dere doughter Wenefryde | that she go in to the place whiche is callyd Henthlacus, | ffor there she shalle obteyne the desyre of her vowe'. | &amp; whan he had told to her this, | anone she toke leue of this holy man | and <MILESTONE N="30"/> bad hym fare well, | and gladly wente vnto that place. | And there she fyndynge saynt Saturne, | whiche knewe by dyuyne reuelacion the purpose of hyr iourneye and sayd to her theffecte of her com∣ynge | and gaf to her this answere: | 'There is a certeyne place, called Wytheryacus, | where as is Abbot Elerius, a man of grete <MILESTONE N="35"/> vertues; | he shalle telle to the what the behoueth to doo'. | whiche thynge anone as she had vnderstanden, forthwith she tooke her way and wente to that holy man. | Whoos comynge the holy man hauyng knowlege tofore by the holy ghoost, wente to mete her, | and broughte her in to the Chirche | there forto praye and saye her <MILESTONE N="40"/> deuocions. | And that fynysshed, he tooke her by the honde | and ladde her in to the Couente of vyrgyns | whiche was there, | to whome he sayd these wordes: | 'Loo, almyghty god hath ordeyned this deuoute vyrgyne forto dwelle with yow: | this is that mayde Wenefrede | whoos clere fame | now late hath (be) brought <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">be</HI> fehlt.</NOTE> to youre <MILESTONE N="45"/> eres, whiche hath despysed, for to kepe her chastyte, the bla<HI REND="italic">n</HI>dys∣shyng wordes and the concupyscence of hym that persecuted her, |
<PB N="302" REF="10"/>
and chase leuer the smytynge of | of her hede | than to lose her vyrgynyte, | and rather to deye than to consente forto do synne. Therfore now she is comen to yow for to dwelle with you and to abyde here the day of her departyng out of this world: wherfore be ye ioyefull for her comynge | and receyue ye enbracynge her de∣uoutely <MILESTONE N="5"/> | as celestyall tresoure dwellynge amonge yow, entendyng besyly to her werkes | and with all your entente folowynge her. | For this place, as longe as the worlde shalle endure, | for her sake shalle be renommed by grete fame'. | ¶ After thise wordes he torned hym vnto a lady whiche was his owne moder | and was <MILESTONE N="10"/> prelate and chyef aboue the other relygyouse nonnes, | and sayd to her: | 'O thow, my mooste dere moder, | I commytte to the specially the cure and charge of this vyrgyne, | whiche is wel byloued to god. | Thow, therfore, folowe her stappes and werkes | and take thou the charge of all thynges that long to her, | and, what thow <MILESTONE N="15"/> mayst knowe that shall please her, | that do and execute dylygently and incontynent. | These wordes fynysshed and sayd, | the holy con∣fessour departed and wente his wey. | And saynt Wenefrede re∣mayned and abode from than forthon with the maydens seruauntes of god. | Thenne was in her | grete abstynence, | kepyng her good <MILESTONE N="20"/> and hooly lyf, | prayer perseueryng | and humble conuersacion. | Other vyrgyns took of her ensample of pacyence &amp; obedyence, they made her in alle thynges that apperteyne to theyr helthe | a forgoar and ensample to them. | And in her were founden alle thynges plentyuously that were of honeste and vertue. | Wherof for <MILESTONE N="25"/> to recyte or reherce, of what abstynence that she was in her lyf, | what anguysshes or what payne that she suffryd in her body, | what scarcenes or penaunce she excercysed, it were ouer-longe to telle; | but shortely I shalle saye yow | that she lefte no thyng vndone that she knewe myght be to the helthe of her sowle | or to the <MILESTONE N="30"/> good ensample of other. | Dyuerse and many of deuoute peple cam to her by companyes, desyryng to see this blessyd vyrgyne | and to beholde the place where as the token was in her necke, | that her hede was smyten of for the loue of Jhesu Cryst | and by the prayer of the hooly confessour was reysed fro dethe and reuyued ageyne, | <MILESTONE N="35"/> and they helde the place worthy of hyhe reuerence in which she duellyd. | To somme it suffysed only to see her | and to speke wyth her; | and somme were so inportune | that they wold not be co<HI REND="italic">n</HI>tent | but they myght see the place in her neck of the cuttynge of | of her hede, | and humbly prayd her to shewe it to them: | to whoos <MILESTONE N="40"/> deuocions and requestes she dredde to warne or gayn-saye, | lest their deuocion myght therby be lassed | or that they myght depute it to the pryde of her. | And whanne they sawe in her necke the skynne and the place of the cuttynge, by a moche differente colour vnlyke to the remenaunt, | they couthe | ne myght not absteyne <MILESTONE N="45"/> them fro wepyng, | blessyng &amp; gyuyng laude to almyghty god in his grete and merueylous werkes, and retorned home with grete wondre and admyracion. | ¶ On a certayne daye the blessid Elerius
<PB N="303" REF="11"/>
thabbot, entryd in to the cloystre of the nonnes for to vysyte saynt Wenefrede. | Thenne the holy Abbot for occasion to shewe to her | that he ofte had remembryd in his mynde, sayd to the holy vyrgyne saynt Wenefrede: | 'I joye gretely, sayd he, | that god hath prouyded the to come to this place, | ffor to helpe to brynge my body to <MILESTONE N="5"/> sepulture, | and after my deth that thou remembre and haue me in thy mynde and prayers'. | To whome the holy vyrgyne answerd: | 'Not so, fader, | shall it not be, | neyther it is not so predestynate ne ordeyned of god; | but it behoueth the to lyue after me, | and fyrste thou brynge to the erthe my lady, thy moder, after that she <MILESTONE N="10"/> shall be departed, | &amp; after certayn yeres passed after that for to burye my body: | ffor thus god hath ordeyned'. | ¶ And whanne this holy man had herd these wordes, he took his leue and de∣parted fro her. | And soone after | he fonde her prophecye true: | ffor after a lytell tyme Theonia, his mo<HI REND="italic">d</HI>er <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Cax. <HI REND="italic">doughter;</HI> in L. durchstr. und <HI REND="italic">mother</HI> überschr. v. a. h. Anglia, III. band.</NOTE>, deyde and departed oute <MILESTONE N="15"/> of this world. | And after that the holy saynt Wenefrede was made prelate and vpperist of alle the couent of the nonnes | and had the rewle &amp; gouernaunce of them many yeres. | And at the laste our blessyd lord Jhesu Cryst desyrynge and wyllynge to take hys handmayde and seruaunt fro the laborouse seruytude of thys lyf | <MILESTONE N="20"/> and to brynge her to the rest of perpetuel blysse: | ¶ On a nyght, as she was in her oratorye, | our lord lete her haue knoulege of the daye of her obyte and departyng oute of this lyf, | whiche shold hastely ensiewe and folowe. | And anone as she vnderstode and felte herself called and vysyted by the grace of god, | she with an <MILESTONE N="25"/> holy deuocion beganne to make her redy vnto the ioyes that she was called to: | thenne contynuelly in the nyghtes she was prayenge in the chirche | and in the day tyme she vertuously occupyed her self in all thynges longynge to her cure and charge. | And whanne this rumour cam to the knowlege of saynt Elerius, | he anone was <MILESTONE N="30"/> in grete anguysshe and wayllynge for the departyng of this holy virgyne, | whome he entierly loued, | knowyng certaynly | that she was endowed with specialle grace; | and desyred for his synguler wele | that, as longe as he(!) shold in the pylgremage of this lyf en∣dure, | that he myght dwelle and abyde with her, and this he desyred <MILESTONE N="35"/> with grete deuocion. ¶ Thenne after this the blessyd vyrgyne be∣ganne to suffre grete sekenes in all her body. | ¶ And as the languour and maladye was vehement and encreaced dayly, | she knewe veryly that she approched toward hir last ende. | Thenne she lyfte vp her mynde toward almyghty god | and humbly prayd <MILESTONE N="40"/> hym to haue mercy on her | and that he wold be the kepar and wardeyn of her sowle, | and that the deuyll shold haue no praye of her. | Thenne she dyd do calle to her the hooly confessour saynt Elerye, thabbot, whiche houseled her with the blessid body of oure lord. | Thenne the day of the kalendes of Nouembre | she beganne <MILESTONE N="45"/> to wexe feble by the dissolucion of her body; | but for all that
<PB N="304" REF="12"/>
she rested not, for al her payne and sekenesse, to preche and en∣fourme them that were assistent, with holy and blessid exhortacions. ¶ Thenne whanne she was enfeblyd with ouermoche payne | of greuous sekenesses | and felte well that on the morne she shold departe and fynysshe her bodyly lyf, she lete doo calle to her <MILESTONE N="5"/> saynt Elerye | and prayd hym that her body myght be buryed | and put in the sepulture by the body of saynt Theonye, | his moder: | whiche request the holy man graunted benyngly. | And thenne the holy vyrgyne entendyng with all hir hole herte in prayer vnto almyghty god, the day of the thyrdde Nonas in Nouembre | <MILESTONE N="10"/> she commended her spyryte in to the handes of her maker, to be associate vnto the celestyalle companye of sayntes. | Thenne the holy man commendyng her sowle vnto god, | beganne to procure besyly | and make al thyng redy that he sawe apperteyne to the exequyes of the blessyd virgyne. | And whanne alle was done that <MILESTONE N="15"/> apperteyned to her funerall seruyse, | he buryed her in the place that she desyred, | and with grete wayllynges and lamentacions her body was leyd in the sepulture. | And in the same place the sayd | body lay vnto the tyme of kyng Steuen, kynge of Englond: | in whos tyme by dyuyne reuelacions and myracles before goynge the <MILESTONE N="20"/> bones of the blessyd vyrgyne were translated vnto thabbeye of Shrewsburye, | where moche peple comyng by the suffrages and merytes of many askyng remedye of theyr Infyrmytees and seken∣esses haue ben heled and maade all hole. <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">In L. sind fol. 194 und 195 verkehrt gebunden.</NOTE> ¶ Thus endeth the martirdome of this blessyd saynt | saynt Wenefrede, | whiche passion <MILESTONE N="25"/> and decollacion was the one and twentyest day of Juyn. | ¶ And also, as is afore sayd, the lyf whiche she after hyr decollacion lyued by the space of XV yere, | and the departyng of hyr oute of thys lyf was the thyrdde day of Nouembre. |</P>
<P>¶ And herafter by the grace of god shalle folowe the translacion <MILESTONE N="(III)"/> of this blessyd vyrgyne saynt Wenefrede, | how by grete myracle her bones were brought to thabbay of Shrewsbury, | whiche trans∣lacion is halowed the XIX day of Septembre. Whiche thre festes ben solempnly halowed in the sayd Abbaye of Shrewesbury to the laude and praysynge of almyghty god | and of this blessyd and <MILESTONE N="35"/> holy vyrgyne seynte Wenefryde, | to whome late vs praye to be a specialle aduocatryce for vs in alle thynges to vs necessarye and behoeffulle.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>The Translacion of saynt Wenefrede.</HEAD>
<P>(A)ffter that the blessyd vyrgyne saynt Wenefryde, shynynge by innumerable vertues, was departyd oute of thys lyf vnto the celesty∣all <MILESTONE N="40"/> regne and blysse, | many yeres after kynge William regnynge, | whiche fyrste of the Normannes regned in Englond, | one Rogere Erle, a noble man and shynynge in alle honeste of maner and Relygyon, beganne to edyfye a monasterye in the towne of Shrewes∣bury:
<PB N="305" REF="13"/>
to whiche entendynge for to performe hit, endowed it wyth his propre cost and expencys | and ordeyned therin an Abbot | and constytued certayne bretheren monkes, for to serue god. | By processe of tyme | that place encreacyng by the mercy of god, prouffyted moche to many the way of helthe and was renommed of good fame and <MILESTONE N="5"/> full of vertues vnto all them that dwellyd in that countreye. | Whan thenne the bretheren of that Abbeye shone by vertues | and all that was vertuous they beganne folowe dylygently: | oftymes they complayned among them self that they had nede to haue relykes, and for to gete and purchace somme they dyd alle their deuoyr <MILESTONE N="10"/> and dylygence. | And for as moche as in Wales, whiche was fast by them, | they herde saye that there were reteyned the bodyes of many sayntes, | whoos merytes were prechyd in dyuerse places, | and for to haue somme of them, they studyed &amp; sought alle the meanes they couthe, | knowyng veryly | that by the suffrages of <MILESTONE N="15"/> suche one they myght the better serue our lord and be kepte the better from alle aduersytees | whoos dayly seruyse they shold kepe with deuocion here in this world, | to thende that he shold to them be a patrone in heuen— | ffor whiche to gete, | they dylygently en∣deuouryd them. | And trouth it is | that, sythe many holy and ex∣cellente <MILESTONE N="20"/> confessours were in the sayd countrey, | they beganne to doubte whome they myght specially desyre and haue. | ¶ Hit happed afterward that one of the bretheren of that Abbaye was oppressyd by grete infyrmyte. | And the other bretheren hauyng grete compas∣syon on hym, were sore troublyd for his disease, | and for his helth <MILESTONE N="25"/> they prayd deuoutely with the Inward deuocion of their hert vnto god, | and sente vnto other howses of Relygyon, prayeng them that they the same wyse wold haue theyr seek brother recommended in their speial prayers. | And specially they lete haue knowleg of the greuous Infyrmyte of hym vnto the monkes of the chirche of <MILESTONE N="30"/> Chestre. | And thenne they in the same, astonyed in theyr mynydes(!), wente in to the chirche forto praye deuoutely for his helthe; | whiche fylle doune flatte tofore the holy Aulter | and sayd with humble deuocion the seuen psalmes. | And one of them, named Randolf, whiche was suppryour of the hows, a man of good lyf and symple <MILESTONE N="35"/> courage, fylle a slepe: | and he sawe by a vysyon an excellent &amp; fayr virgyne stondynge tofore hym, | whiche with a moche plesaunt chere sayd to hym these wordes: | 'What is this, said (s)he <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">L. <HI REND="italic">he</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">she.</HI></NOTE>, and for whome is it that ye thus prostrate praye?' | The monke an∣swerd: | 'It is for a broder of our ordre whiche is payned by grete <MILESTONE N="40"/> Infyrmyte, | and for his helthe here we lye prostrate, for to offre our prayers to god for his helthe'. | To whome she sayd: | 'I knowe wel, sayd she, that that same monke suffreth alienacion of his mynde. But &amp; yf ye desyre veryly his helthe, | late one of yow go to the welle of saynt Wenefrede | and in the chirche that is ther by | late <MILESTONE N="45"/> hym saye masse in the remembraunce of hir: | and anone the seke
<PB N="306" REF="14"/>
broder shall be delyuerd of his sekenes'. | And this sayeng she vanysshed awey. | The monk awoke 7, comyn ageyn to hymself, | remembryng what he had sene and herd in his mynde, | wold not shewe his vysion to his bretheren, | dredynge to be had in scorne | of them | &amp; that they wold depute for a fantasye that he had <MILESTONE N="5"/> sene &amp; herd. | So after this nyghe vpon a fourty dayes | the seke man was alwey gretely vexyd | &amp; lay in his bedde. | And it was shewed ageyne to the monkes of Chestre of the grete and greuous payne that the sayd monke suffred. | And forto speke of hym it gaf occacion to the monkes of Chestre, | and after many wordes, <MILESTONE N="10"/> when they bewaylled the seke man, | he that had sene the vysyon toke hardynes to hym | and told to them al by ordre what the holy vyrgyn had said to hym. | Thenne they, whiche afore tyme had herd the fame of hir, | &amp; knowyng also that many myracles had be done by her merytes, | anone made them lyghtely to bileue <MILESTONE N="15"/> to that whiche was sayd, | and also gaf faythe to the vysyon: | ffor sithe they were warned to go to her welle | and in thonoure of her to saye masse in the chirche, | they were callyd therto by saynte Wenefrede | and sayd certaynly that she had appiered to the sayd broder. | Thus thenne they takynge their counceylle togyder, | two <MILESTONE N="20"/> monkes were sente to the welle of saynte Wenefrede | and forto saye masse in the chirche that was fast by | and there to pray for the seke man. | And it was so that the same houre that the masse was ther songen, | the seke monke at Shrewesbury was made al hole, and thanked the said monkes for his helthe. | And a lytel whyle <MILESTONE N="25"/> after | the same broder that had ben seke was ladde to the same place for to gyue laude and praysynge to god and to the holy vyrgyne for his helthe. | And whanne he had fyrst made his prayers in the chirche | and after had dronken of the welle | and with the water therof wasshen, | he was parfyghtely made hole | &amp; retorned to <MILESTONE N="30"/> his monastery in good helth. And fro thenne forthon the memorye and remembraunce of this holy vyrgyn | beganne tencreace more deuoutely in the hertes of the bretheren, | in suche wyse that they estemed them blessyd and happy | yf they myght haue and gete a lytel parte or relyque of her most blessyd body. | And though this <MILESTONE N="35"/> semed to them hard and dyffycyle | and supposed shold passe theyre power, | yet they ordeyned to tempte and proue it, | knowynge that ther is nothyng may resiste the wylle of god | ; prayenge hym that he wold be debonayr and helper to bryng their purpos to effecte, | by whoos wylle alle thynges hard, diffycile &amp; impossyble withoute <MILESTONE N="40"/> doubte may lyghtely be broughte by his myght to honde, | and therof they doubted not. | ¶ That tyme that kynge Harry the fyrst, an hyhe and excellent prynce | and frende of pees, gouerned the Royamme of Englond, | by whos auctory te alle þe yle obteyned surete and pees, | in soo moche that euery man myght go and ryde <MILESTONE N="45"/> peasybly whyder-someuer he wold. | By occasion wherof the sayd bretheren sente messagers in to Wales for to knowe where the most and excellente relyques rested, | and in especiall to seche where
<PB N="307" REF="15"/>
the tombe of the forsayd vyrgyne was. | And whan they had founde that place in whiche the bones of the blessyd vyrgyn Wenefrede rested, | they were gladde and fulfylled with ouer-grete ioye. | And by the consente of the bisshop of Banguour, | in whos dyocise the place was, | they made the prynces and noble men of the countrey <MILESTONE N="5"/> to be consentynge and fauourable to them. | This thynge procedyng dayly forward gaf grete courage to the bretheren that they shold come to thentent of theyr desyre. But the dethe of the forsayd kyng Harry, sodenly comynge on, oppressyd al Brytayne by ouer grete stryf and trouble | and constrayned them a certayne tyme to <MILESTONE N="10"/> leue theyre erande and desyre. | &amp; the second yere of kynge Stephen the troubles ceased and the lond restored to tranquyllyte and pees, | ¶ Thabbot of the forsayd monasterye by the counceylle of his bretheren ordeyned for to sende in to Wales the pryour, named Roberte, with another monke his felawe, named Rychard. | This <MILESTONE N="15"/> pryour was moche (more) dylygent in the procuracion of this thynge | than the other messagers had ben, and sente his lettres and messages in the countrey. | and had answer ageyne that, yf he cam hymself, | that he shold retorne ioyefully | and haue his entente of that he desyred. | Thenne he wente | and cam fyrste to the bisshop of Banguour, | and <MILESTONE N="20"/> fro hym he was sente to the prynce of that countrey, | and of hym was benyngly receyued.</P>
<P>And whanne he had shewed to hym by ordre the cause of his iourney, | he sayd to hym | and ansuerd in this wyse: | 'I suppose that thy-self | ne thy felawes haue not taken on yow so grete a <MILESTONE N="25"/> laboure with-oute the wylle of god | and of the blessyd vyrgyne, | peraduenture seynge not due reuerence done to her of them dwell∣yng in this contrey, | wherfor she desyred to be born in to somme other place, | to thende that she be honoured of straungyers | whome they that duelle here forgete | and haue in none reuerence. | Wher∣fore <MILESTONE N="30"/> I graunte it gladly | and to her plaisyr I knowlege me to assente, | lest in resystyng and gaynsayenge of hit | I be compellyd to suffre her indignacion | ne auengyng it on me. | And though I be defowled in al vnclennesse | and am werst of all other men, | yet neuertheles I shal helpe to breke vp hir tombe; | and touchyng her <MILESTONE N="35"/> holy bones I shal delyuer them to yow, | but yf so be for the comyn prouffyte of the countreye I muste nedes otherwyse entende. | ffor your labours and vysyons manyfeste and shewe that hit is her wylle | that her bones be transported from hens. | Therfore go ye, confermed by the lycence of myn auctorite, vnto the place where <MILESTONE N="40"/> the blessyd vyrgyne resteth. | And as I suppose, ye shal fynde somme rebelles ageynst your disposicion; | but truste ye veryly that the virgyne shall appease them | whos affection hath incyted yow to so moche laboure. | Neuertheles I shal sende a messager to tho men | in whos patrymonye the body of the blessyd vyrgyne resteth, | <MILESTONE N="45"/> whiche shal enforme to them my wyll | and shall make them som∣what the more peasyble to yow'— | this sayd, gaf them leue to goo forthe in pees. | Thanne they wente strayte vnto the place where
<PB N="308" REF="16"/>
the body of the venerable Wenefred was leyd. | And they were of them seuen persones, | that is to wyte the pryour, | and with hym the pryour of Chestre, named Wulmare; | &amp; a preest, a man of grete vertue, named Idon, born of the same countrey; | a monke also whome the pryour toke with hym; | and thre other men. | And as <MILESTONE N="5"/> they wente walkynge and spekynge of the mater that they wente fore, | they met a man of the same countrey, | demaundynge of them whiche of them was priour of Shrewesbury. | To whome whanne he was shewed, sayd these wordes: | 'I haue an erand to the from tho men that duelle in the place | in whiche reste the bones of <MILESTONE N="10"/> saynte Wenefrede, | whiche is called Wytheryake, | and lete the haue knowlege | that they be moeued ageynst the by grete indyg∣nacion, | bycause that thou labourest to haue awey the bodyes of sayntes buryed by them, | to whome they haue commytted them self | and alle their goodes. | And knowe thou for certayn | that <MILESTONE N="15"/> neyther the drede of the prynce, | ne the thretenyng of his lordes, | ne þe couetyse of ony money shal not make them to consente to yow in this thynge.' | And this sayd, | he went his way. | The pryour thenne and his felawes for these wordes were heuy and soroufull, | &amp; what to doo | ne whyther to torne, they wyste neuer. | Thenne <MILESTONE N="20"/> they torned them to almyghty god and prayd to hym with alle the deuocion of theyr myndes that it myght please hym to sende to them his spyryte of counceyl, | and that he, whiche only by the commaundement of his word appeaseth the tempestes of the wyndes and the see, | that it plese hym to appease these inimytees | &amp; to <MILESTONE N="25"/> confedere the myndes and courages of these men vnto them— | they humbly praid. Thenne they hauynge very confidence in the holy ghoost, held forth their iourney as they had begonne. | Whan they cam nygh vnto the place where as were conteyned the bones of the holy virgyne, | the pryour by counceylle sente two of his felawes, <MILESTONE N="30"/> that is to saye the pryour of Chestre | and the forsayd preeste, te-fore, <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">te</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">to.</HI></NOTE> whiche were wel knowen in al the countreye, for to prouyde and solycyte all thynges that shold be necessary to them. He reteynynge his felawe with hym, abode that nyght in a thorpe bycause of the message that he had herd, | &amp; was therfor sore troubled. <MILESTONE N="35"/> | &amp; whanne he had said the laudes of his matyns, a sadde &amp; an honest persone in lykenes of a woman appiered to one his seruaunt, sayeng these wordes: | 'Aryse anone | and saye to thy lord that he put awey his heuynes | and sorowes that he is oppressyd with, | and that he lyft vp his hope in god, | knowyng for certayne that he shall <MILESTONE N="40"/> from hens with grete ioye: | she for whos loue he is comen to this prouynce, | shal accomplysshe and fulfylle theffect of his desyre: | ffor in haste he shall haue that for whiche he shalle Joyously retorne home | &amp; shal glade alle his felawes in his comynge'. | Another vysyon that same nyght happed to the same pryour; | ther was an <MILESTONE N="45"/> Abbot, a man of grete deuocion, | whiche had ben afore tyme fader
<PB N="309" REF="17"/>
of that same Abbaye of Shrewesbury | and hauyng old age &amp; ful of vertues departid oute of this lyf, named Godfrey: | whiche appiered to hym that same nyght, | &amp; of the drede that he had | blamed hym, sayeng: | 'Be thou not of faynt herte, | but haue good faythe &amp; truste, | ffor we shal well ouercome oure enemyes | &amp; with them that <MILESTONE N="5"/> shalle assiste vs by the helpe of god we shalle vaynquysshe them; | &amp; knowe thow verily that we shal shortely opteyne that thyng which we with hyhe deuocion so moche desyre'. | After these wordes he vanysshed aweye from his eyen. | Of these vysyo<HI REND="italic">n</HI>s grewe somme surete in their myndes | &amp; was gyuen to them an hope to opteyne <MILESTONE N="10"/> that they sought. And on the morne erly they told what they had sene in their slepe, | &amp; gaf grete comfort to the herers. | &amp; sodenly one of the messagers, that had ben with them the daye before, cam &amp; sayde that they myȝt surely come, | warnyng them to folowe hym, | for that they desyred they shold fynde. | Whiche anone toke their <MILESTONE N="15"/> horses and cam thyder. | &amp; fyrst their prayers sayd, | they called the preest of the sayd place secretely | &amp; prayd hym hertely that he wold be helpyng to them. | The preest paciently heryng their wordes, gaf to them an answer in this wyse: | 'I shal lyghtly accorde me to your entente with good wyll. | &amp; bycause I shal the straitlyer be con∣federed <MILESTONE N="20"/> to yow, | &amp; that I knowe the wyll of god &amp; of the blessid virgyn touchyng your desyre, I shal here in your presence shewe to yow. | On the satirday, the vigyle of ester, in the chirche whiche ye here see &amp; beholde, I was al the nyght for to syng &amp; say matyns &amp; ympnes, whan tyme was; | &amp; whan I had said the psaulter tofore <MILESTONE N="25"/> the aulter, | I leyd me doun vpon the steppes, a lytel to take my rest; | and I sawe a vysyon, whiche moche fered me | and bycause I shold not resiste ne be rebell to yow, | by thretenynge he warned me; | and, as me thought, no grete slepe oppressyd me, | but as I had be half wakyng. | A fayr yong man, hauyng an angels <MILESTONE N="30"/> chere, stode before me and callyd me, sayeng: Aryse! | I wenyng that he wold haue awaked me, | that I shold haue begonne my nocturnal offyce, | &amp; ansuerd to hym: | It is not yet tyme to begynne thoffyce, | I wyl not aryse. | And he thenne, as me semed, wente his way. | And the second tyme he cam, | &amp; callyd me ludder | &amp; <MILESTONE N="35"/> sayd: | Aryse, | aryse! | &amp; I wolde not take no hede to his wordes | &amp; ansuerd hym as I dyd before; | and with my mantell that I ware I couerd my hede and fylle in to a sadde slepe. | And after a lytel whyle the same yong man cam &amp; with his hand drewe awey by grete strength the mantel fro my hede | &amp; leyd it vnder my <MILESTONE N="40"/> sholders, sayenge to me the thyrd tyme: | Aryse, | aryse, | aryse, | &amp; folowe me! | ¶ Thenne me thought I aroos | &amp; folowed hym. | And we cam to the sepulcre of the blessyd vyrgyne saynt Wenefrede, | whiche shewynge to me with his fyngre seyd: | "Marke dylygently thys place, | and the wordes that I shalle saye reteyne faste in thy <MILESTONE N="45"/> mynde! | yf ony come hyder this yere or the nexte whiche wil remeue this stone | &amp; remeue the erthe, | in no wyse gaynsaye it not; | &amp; yf he wyll bere away with hym the bones of this blessyd
<PB N="310" REF="18"/>
vyrgyn, | repugne not ther-ageynst, | but put hond to | &amp; in all thynges that thou mayst helpe hym! | &amp; yf thou therin be neclygent | &amp; be founde a despysar of my wordes | whiche ben shewed to the by goddes commaundement, | thou shalt be payned by myserable &amp; long languour and sekenes | &amp; sone after lese thy self". | This said, <MILESTONE N="5"/> the angelyk visyon vanysshed away. | Therfore be ye assured that I shal helpe to spede your purpos and dylygently mynystre to yow after my myght. | Therfore of me be ye sure | &amp; calle the other to you | whiche ye may applye to your desyre, | for I <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Caxt. <HI REND="italic">I wyll; wyll</HI> ist zu tilgen.</NOTE>, with all the studye &amp; industrye that I may &amp; can, shall execute your playsyre, | <MILESTONE N="10"/> &amp; the good wyll of them of <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">of</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">to.</HI></NOTE> whom the ryght of this toune apper∣teyneth | I shal do my best to brynge them to your wyll. | &amp; by∣cause they now be here prese<HI REND="italic">n</HI>t, | say ye to them what ye will, | for they be redy for to here you.' | Thenne the pryour by the moyen of the preest or by his interpretacion spacke vnto alle the com∣panye <MILESTONE N="15"/> of men that were there, | and exposed to them the cause of his iourney | and desyred them by fayre wordes | that they wold gyue theyr assente, shewynge no thynge to them of theyr vysyons, ne recytynge what hadde happed to them, | but only for deuocion that they hadde to the vyrgyne they had taken the labour <MILESTONE N="20"/> on them. | After many wordes and causes leyd | and after innumer∣abre incidentes | and reasons alledged, | atte last they were al acorded, | and that they desyred | they benyngnlye consentyd. | The pryour and his felawes gyuynge thankynges to god, | desyred | that they shold shewe to them the place. | And sothly the place <MILESTONE N="25"/> where so moche tresour was reteyned is a chirche-yerde of a good distaunce fro the chircheyerd where now the bodyes of dede men ben buryed, | and in that chirche-yerd resten the bodyes of many other sayntes, | and is had in soo grete reuerence of them that dwelle in the countrey | that none of them dare presume to entre in to <MILESTONE N="30"/> it, | but yf it be | bycause for to praye. | And whan the sayd monkes with theire felaushyp were brought to that place, | the sayd pryoure, goyng before his felaushyp, by thynstynct, | as I suppose, of the hooly ghoost anone withoute ony man ledynge or shewynge cam strayte to the sepulture of saynt Wenefrede, | and he, whiche neuer <MILESTONE N="35"/> was there before ne knewe by techynge of ony man that place, by the ledynge of god withoute goyng oute of the wey cam to the tombe of the blessyd virgyne. | And standynge at the hede of the blessyd vyrgyne, abydynge his felawes, | he was admonysshed by a dyuyne reuelacion within forth | that that was the sepulture of <MILESTONE N="40"/> the blessyd vyrgyne | and there he sholde haue that he desyred. | Thenne they comyng that shold haue shewed the place, | assigned to hym that same place that he tofore had chosen | and stode-by. | Thenne the peple beyng remeued, two of the monkes | with pykoys and spades beganne to digge in the ground, | tyll they cam to the <MILESTONE N="45"/> tresour desyred, | and the other sayde and redde theyr psalmes. |
<PB N="311" REF="19"/>
¶ And whanne the body was founden, | they gaf and rendryd thankynges vnto god, | and tooke oute the bones fro the erthe and, as they thought that tyme best for them, | bonde them fair in theyr mantels | &amp; honestly leid them therin. | And they there hon∣estly toke their leue, | commendynge them that there were to god, <MILESTONE N="5"/> beganne to retorne homeward with grete ioye. | And soo they wente forth with grete ioye, | sayenge oftymes emonge other wordes that they had goten a grete tresour | whiche was better than many and grete rychesses, | and knewe not of what meryte hit was, | besech∣ynge almyghty god that they myghte haue somme token therof. | <MILESTONE N="10"/> And it was not long to | but that god wold satisfye their wylle and desyre: | ffor anone the daye beganne to faylle and to wexe derke, | and were lodgyd in a good mannes hows; | and there they beynge sette to souper, they herd in the inner parte of the hows | a seke man grone and gyuynge oute a terryble voys. | Thenne the <MILESTONE N="15"/> pryour demaunded the cause of his dysease, | and it was answerd | that ther was a man vexid with grete sekenesses; | and yf he myght be heled, | he shold gyue a grete reward therfore. | Thenne the pryour toke a lytell water | and blessyd hit, | and he took a lytell of the pouldre or dust that was in her hede, | and put therin, | and badde <MILESTONE N="20"/> to gyue it to the seke man. | Whiche anon after he hadde receyued hit, slepte, | and anone after he awoke | &amp; aroos all hoole, gyuynge thankynges to god and to the blessyd vyrgyne. | And by this myracle | they were confermed in the faythe | and were gladder than they were tofore, | &amp; more deuoute in worshippynge of the vyrgyne. <MILESTONE N="25"/> And many other signes and myracles they had by the waye, | whiche affermed that hit was a godly yefte that they bare. | And whanne they cam to a place vpon a ten myle fro Shrewesbury, | they restyd &amp; taryed there. | And whanne they sholde haue departyd, | they coude not remeue the bones: | wherfor they counceyled to <MILESTONE N="30"/> gyder | and concluded that the bones shold be wesshen at that place. | And thenne there was no water: but anone sprang vp there a fayr welle, | whiche yet renneth a grete cours contynuelly in to this day lyke to the rather welle. | In which welle they wesshe the bones of the blessyd saynt Wenefrede. | And euer after the stones that lye <MILESTONE N="35"/> and reste in that water, ben besprynet as it were with dropes of blood, in so moche that for certayne ther hath ben certayne deuoute persones | whiche haue done to be leyd certayne whyte asshen cuppes in this sayd welle, | and whanne they haue ben in the water a seuen dayes or ther-aboutes, | they haue appieryd al besprynct <MILESTONE N="40"/> as it were with blood—and this is dayly shewed: | whiche is a grete myracle. |</P>
<P>¶ Thenne they sente messagers vnto the toune of Shrewesbury, | from whens they were departed, | and sente word to the monastery | that they had that | for whiche they were sente fore. | Thenne the <MILESTONE N="45"/> congregacion herynge these tydynges, were ryghte joyeful and thankyng our lord | concluded | that the bones sholde be sette in the chirche of saynt Gyles, | whiche is in issuynge oute of the towne, |
<PB N="312" REF="20"/>
sayeng | that so holy a tresour oughte not to be receyued in to the monasterye withoute auctoryte and benediction of the bisshop | and with the grete concourse of the peple of that prouynce. | This counceylle pleased them alle. | And thenne they sente ageyne the pryour to the bisshop, | forto conferme by his auctoryte what they <MILESTONE N="5"/> shold doo with suche a relyque, | to them graunted from heuen. | ¶ And in the mene whyle the monkes were departed for to synge thoffyce of the daye and nyght before the body of the blessyd vyrgyne wyth deuoute courage. | To whome they songe besyly on the day tyme, | moche peple cam | that were dwellyng there in that <MILESTONE N="10"/> countrey, commyttynge themself to the prayers and merytes of the holy vyrgyne saynte Wenefrede | . ¶ There was in the same town a certayne yonge man whiche was gretely vexyd with merueyll∣ous sekenes | and was benomen in alle his membres, | in so moche | that his hede bowed doune almost to the erthe | and in no wyse he <MILESTONE N="15"/> myght lyfte vp his hede. | And whanne he herd of the noyse of the comyng of this holy vyrgyne, | he dyde do be made redy an hors | and by helpe of his ffrendes was sette theron | and holden on bothe sydes by the handes of two men, and soo broughte to the chirche | where the relyques of saynte Wenefrede were conteyned and kepte. | <MILESTONE N="20"/> And there abode all nyght in prayer | and there was vexyd with moche greuous payne. | And on the morne | whanne the day beganne to wexe clere, | and as the preest beganne thoffyce of the masse, | he beganne to amende | and anone was restored to his fyrst helth. And whanne the gospell was redde, | he lefte his bedde | that he <MILESTONE N="25"/> laye on, | and wente hastely to the aulter for to make his offryng to god | and to the blessyd vyrgyne saynt Wenefrede, yeuyng grete thankes to god | and hyr deuoutely | for the helthe that he had receyued, | and retorned all hole and stronge on his feet to the hows of his fader and moder, | whiche the day before was brought <MILESTONE N="30"/> thyder on an hors by the handes of other. | This grete myracle gladded the hertes of alle them that there were gadred, | and anone in short space after was shewed &amp; told this myracle thorugh alle the prouynce: whiche excyted moche the myndes of them that herd hit vnto the deuocion &amp; reuerence of the blessyd saynt. <MILESTONE N="35"/></P>
<P>¶ The name of hir grewe euery day more and more, | and the me∣morye of her. | Thenne the pryour retorned fro the bisshop, hauynge his auctoryte: | that alle they that in the worship of the holy virgyne | and in her honour were deuoute, shold haue goddes blyssyng and his. | And thenne a certayne day was named | and shewed vnto the <MILESTONE N="40"/> paroches there-aboute, | that alle they shold be warned that wold come to the venerable translacion of thys holy vyrgyne. | ¶ Thenne on the day assigned the monkes wente in procession with crosses and candellys, &amp; innumerable multitude of peple, for to fetche the holy body of the blessyd vyrgyne saynt Wenefrede, | euery man <MILESTONE N="45"/> knelynge with his knees | and many for ioye myght not absteyne them from wepyng. | The couente of the bretheren that wente out for to receyue this holy jewel, | receyued celestyall bienfaittes by the
<PB N="313" REF="21"/>
merytes of the blessyd vyrgyne saynt Wenefrede. | For hit rayned by grete shoures al aboute in the feldes therby; | and the couent that were gone oute cladde them with precious ornamentes of the chirche to mete with the blessyd body, | and dredde not a lytell | that the ornamentes &amp; munymentis shold be sore hurte by the fallyng of <MILESTONE N="5"/> the rayne; | but that they hadde begonne, in no wyse wold leue, | mekely prayd to oure lord | that by the prayer of saynt Wenefrede they myghte be kepte drye | and that they myghte be preseruyd fro the fallynge of the rayne. | Thenne in al that procession of them that went out of the monasterye | and in the receyuynge of the <MILESTONE N="10"/> holy relykes ye shold haue sene the water of the shoures, nyghe to the erthe hangynge ouer them, | and the dropes, redy for to haue fallen, | by the myght of god reteyned, | so that none fylle on them; | and where alle the peple that were there | beyng gretely aferd leste the grete rayne that was lyke to falle shold haue trou∣bled <MILESTONE N="15"/> and haue fallen, | yet by the myght and power of god | &amp; by the merytes of the holy vyrgyn they were withdrawen: | whiche caused them to gyue the more worship and lawde to the merytes of hir. And at the laste it pleasid to alle the peple that the pryour whiche had brought thyder the venerable relyques of the sayd <MILESTONE N="20"/> hooly vyrgyne, shold preche and enforme the grete multytude of the peple, of what vertue | and of what meryte this hooly vyrgyne was of | of whome that tyme was made the translacion. | And whanne he had told to them al this | a longe, | ye shold haue sene the shoures falle aboute nyghe to them | and fleyng in the ayer | and <MILESTONE N="25"/> wetyng alle the countreye by the infusion of the water, | excepte only the procession. | Thenne was the holy body taken vp of the couent and bretheren | and <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">And</HI> zu tilgen.</NOTE> with couenable reuerence, syngyng on hye preysynges and lawde to almyghty god, | and brought to the monasterye, | and sette vpon the aulter | whiche was made in thon∣our <MILESTONE N="30"/> of the holy appostles Peter and Pawle honourably. | Where, for to shewe the prerogatyf of the same holy vyrgyne, is gyuen there to sekemen helthe, | and haue ben shewed innumerable vertues there to the glorye and lawde of almyghty god, | to whome be gyuen honour, glorye and Imperye world without ende. AMEN. <MILESTONE N="35"/></P>
<TRAILER>¶ Thus endeth the decollacion, | the lyf after, | and the translacion of saynte Wenefrede virgyn and martir | whiche was reysed after that her hede had be smyton of the space <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Caxt. <HI REND="italic">the space of the space.</HI></NOTE> of XV yere(!), | reduced in to Englysshe by me William Caxton. | <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot"><P>Nach dem Englischen texte steht das folg. Lat. Officum.
<Q><P>¶ Gaude Wenefreda pura, | virgo, iuuentutis iura dei dans obsequiis. | Gaude Be<HI REND="italic">u</HI>noi preceptis | te conformans et inceptis exerce(n)s vesti∣giis. | Gaude carnis spernens luxu<HI REND="italic">m,</HI> | vanum mu<HI REND="italic">n</HI>di cernens fluxum, | corpus subdens gladijs. | Gaude post resuscitata, | multis annis vita data | sanctorum suffragiis. | Gaude ductrix puellarum, | pandens iter <MILESTONE N="5"/> 
<PB N="314" REF="22"/>
illis clarum | sacris obseruanciis. | Ora Crystum vt sequamur | vbi tecum perfruamur | sempiternis gaudijs.</P>
<LG>
<L>¶ Ora pro nobis beata Wenefreda</L>
<L>Vt per te euncta relinquamur feda.</L>
</LG>
<P>Oremus. ¶ Deus qui beatam Wenefredam virginem tuam pro te <MILESTONE N="15"/> martirisatam resuscitasti | et quindecim annis postea in hoc seculo graciosis muneribus decorasti, | concede propicius | vt qui eius im∣ploramus auxilium | omnium viciorum nostrorum senciamus reme∣dium. Per dominum nostrum Jhesum Crystum et cetera.</P>
<P>Ad primas vesperas in solempnitate sancte Wenefrede:</P>
<P>¶ Virgo cum occiditur, resanat, | vbi caput plectitur ibi fons ema∣nat, <MILESTONE N="10"/> | cuius aqua colitur, nam languores sanat, | nec sanguis vt cer∣nitur a petris euanat. | Ora pro nobis | vt digni, | et cetera. | Oremus: | Deus qui beatam—vt supra, | vel alia oracio:</P>
<P>¶ Deus qui beatam virginem et martirem tuam (egregiam) Wene∣fredam <MILESTONE N="20"/> post capitis abscicionem tua potencia rediuiuam fieri prece∣pisti, ffac nos quesumus ea interueniente vite present<HI REND="italic">is</HI> pariter et future subsidia conuenienter adipisci, | per dom. et cetera | .</P>
<P>Ad secundas vesperas:</P>
<P>¶ Ad laudes regis glorie | hoc exstat memorabile | q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d fontis scatu∣rig(i)ne <MILESTONE N="25"/> | atq<HI REND="italic">ue</HI> in riui margine | petre rubescunt sanguine, | que nullo valent tempore cruoris signum perdere, | ex quo patent per secula | Wenefrede preconia, | cuius per patrocinia ditemur celi gloria.</P>
<P>Collecta ad translacionis diem:</P>
<P>¶ Deus qui hodiernam diem beate virginis tue Wenefrede trans∣lacione <MILESTONE N="30"/> decorasti, | concede propicius | vt quam solempnibus venera∣mur officiis eius continuis muniamur suffragiis | per dominum et cetera.</P>
<P>¶ Ad missam | Officium in die passionis in (die) nouembris:</P>
<P>¶ Gaudeamus et cetera sub honore Wenefrede virginis. | psal | Do∣mine <MILESTONE N="35"/> probasti. | Gloria | et cetera. | Oracio | Deus qui beatam virginem martirem tuam Wenefredam post capitis et cetera.</P>
<P>Epistola | Domine deus meus exaltasti | et cetera. | Alleluia | Gaudeat Salopia Wenefrede memoria | laudatur preconia sua celo cum gloria | Alleluia. | Sequencia | : <MILESTONE N="40"/></P>
<P>Gaude virgo Wenefreda, | viciorum spernens feda, | sancto plena flamine. | Gaude, precor, virgo pura, | cui nulla fuit cura | de carnis propagine. | Gaude quia no<HI REND="italic">n</HI> incestum | sed feruenter ama<HI REND="italic">n</HI>s Cristu<HI REND="italic">m</HI> | passa es obprobria. | Gaude q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d te decollauit | et ad terram corpus strauit | ense manus impia. | Gaude q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d fons de tellure | mox erupit <MILESTONE N="45"/> aque pure | vbi caput cecidit. | Gaude quia te cedentem, ensem her∣baque terge<HI REND="italic">n</HI>te<HI REND="italic">m</HI> | terra mox absorbuit. | Gaude q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d te plebs de∣plorat, | Be<HI REND="italic">u</HI>nous fidens orat | celu<HI REND="italic">m</HI> pulsans fletibus. | Gaude q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d is coaptauit | caput truncat' et sanauit | cunctis intue<HI REND="italic">n</HI>tibus. | Gaude q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d resuscitata | statu<HI REND="italic">m</HI> agis vt b<HI REND="italic">ea</HI>ta, | sacru<HI REND="italic">m</HI> velum indue<HI REND="italic">n</HI>s. | <MILESTONE N="50"/> Gaude q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d es ancillarum | Cristi facta plurimarum | mater illis im∣bue<HI REND="italic">n</HI>s. | Gaude quia hac in vita | te dilexit Cristus ita | q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d fulsit miraculis. | Gaude quia sic ante fatu<HI REND="italic">m</HI> | quisquis dixit se beatu<HI REND="italic">m</HI> | qui te vidit oculis. | Gaude quia collum cingit | ictus ensis qui non 
<PB N="315" REF="23"/>
fingit | sed te probat martirem. | Gaude Wenefrede hinc est dicta, | <MILESTONE N="55"/> martir co<HI REND="italic">n</HI>sta<HI REND="italic">n</HI>s et no<HI REND="italic">n</HI> ficta, | serua<HI REND="italic">n</HI>s hu<HI REND="italic">n</HI>c carectere<HI REND="italic">m.</HI> | Gaude quia silex fortis | vsq<HI REND="italic">ue</HI> modo tue mortis | pa<HI REND="italic">n</HI>dit testimonium, | Gaude quia suo more | adhuc rubet de cruore | fo<HI REND="italic">n</HI>tis per diluuiu<HI REND="italic">m.</HI> | Gaude virgo deo grata, | de longinquo post translata | ad vrbem Salopie. | Gaude q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d te deuotoru<HI REND="italic">m</HI> | ibi cetus monachorum | collauda<HI REND="italic">n</HI>t co∣tidie. <MILESTONE N="60"/> | Gaude modo Wenefreda | sancta deo placens, reda | celo ve∣hens animas. | Gaude quia gratula<HI REND="italic">n</HI>tur | om<HI REND="italic">n</HI>es qui te venera<HI REND="italic">n</HI>tur | cir∣cum per prouincias. | Gaude quia iam cum deo | gratularis et in eo | tuum constat gaudium. | Te rogamus ergo, | dona nobis, pia virgo, | salutis gaudium Amen. <MILESTONE N="65"/></P>
<P>Euangelium | Simile est regnum celorum thesauro | et cetera. | Offertorium | Offerentur | minor | Secret | Oblata domine munera tue magestatis virtute sanctifica | et beate virginis et martiris tue Wene∣frede meritis | salubria nobis esse concede | per dominum | et cetera. | Com | diffusa | Post com | Oremus: Perceptis domine sacramentis <MILESTONE N="70"/> te suppliciter imploramus | vt que in veneracione beate Wenefrede vir∣ginis et martiris tue tibi deuote obtulimus | gaudia nobis conferant sempiterna | per dominum | et cetera. |</P>
<P>Ad missam in translacione eiusdem virginis: |</P>
<P>Gaudeamus | et cetera | sub honore Wenefrede virginis de cuius <MILESTONE N="75"/> translacione | et cetera. | psal | Venite exultemus domino | Jubilemus deo salutari nostro. | Gloria et cetera. | Oremus | Oracio vt supra de translacione. | Epistola | Qui gloriatur. | Gradale | Dilexisti iusticiam et odisti (i)niquitatem | Versus | Propterea benedixit te deus deus (!) oleo letitie. | Alleluia | versus | Veni electa mea et ponam te in thro∣num <MILESTONE N="80"/> meum | quia concupiuit rex speciem tuam | alleluia | Sequencia: Noster cetus iocundetur | atq<HI REND="italic">ue</HI> letus veneretur | Wenefrede merita: cuius sacra celebretur | celebrisq<HI REND="italic">ue</HI> predicetur vbiq<HI REND="italic">ue</HI> memoria. Hec pro Cristo, quem amauit, suum caput non negauit | gladio an∣cipiti: quam post Cristus suscitauit | et ad vitam reuocauit | sancti <MILESTONE N="85"/> prece Beunoi. Summa virtus claruit, | martir dum occubuit: | nam fons ibi scatuit, qui nequaquam deficit; homicida periit, | tellus quem absorbuit. Est et hoc mirabile atq<HI REND="italic">ue</HI> memorabile | q<HI REND="italic">uo</HI>d et omni tempore ffontis scaturigine | et in riui margine | petre rubent sanguine. Rediuiua itaque virgo hec beata, | postquam multis claruit <MILESTONE N="90"/> signis decorata, | tandem celos adiit a Cristo vocata: | a quo cum virginibus sanctis coronata, nobis poscat veniam, qua &amp; impetrata | iungat nos celiculis in sede beata. | Amen. |</P>
<P>Euangelium | Simile est regnum celorum decem virginibus. | Offertorium | Offerentur regi virgines post eam proxime cius offerentur tibi. | Secret | <MILESTONE N="95"/> Oremus.</P></Q> 
(soweit Lamb. 306, worin das letzte blatt fehlt. Das exemplar im Brit. mus. [C. 10 b. 19] ist vollständig und schliesst mit folg.):
<Q><P>Celesti benedictione quesumus domine presencia numera santifica | et intercedente beata virgine tua Wenefreda, | cuius translacionis celebramus solempnia, | nobis per hec vtriusq<HI REND="italic">ue</HI> vite largire sub∣sidia. Per dominum et cetera. |</P>
<P>Com: Diffusa est gracia in labiis tuis, | propterea benedixit te deus <MILESTONE N="5"/> in eternum. | Post com | Sumpto vitalis Alimonie sacramento | tuam 
<PB N="316" REF="24"/>
domine supplices imploramus clemenciam, | vt per hec merita sancte virginis tue Wenefrede, | cuius venerandam celebramus translacionem cunctorum adipisci mereamur peccatorum remissionem. | Per do∣minum nostrum | et cetera. <MILESTONE N="10"/></P></Q></P></NOTE></TRAILER>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="addendum">
<PB N="314" REF="22"/>
<HEAD>[Beilage zu I.] De sancta Wenefreda sermo</HEAD>
<HEADNOTE><P>(Aus dem Festiall, ms. Cott. Claud. A II, fol. 80<SUP>b</SUP>).</P></HEADNOTE>
<P>Thys day is seynt Wenefreday; it is not ordeynid to be haly day bot þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> as men han devocion. Wherefore who so eure hath devocion, comyth þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> day to chyrch<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and doth hir worchep, þe wych<HI REND="italic">e</HI> was
<PB N="315" REF="23"/>
maydyn and martir. Þan how scheo suffred martirdam, ȝe schul here—for þow so<HI REND="italic">m</HI>me knowen it, so<HI REND="italic">m</HI>me doth not. Þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> was in hir tyme an holy eremyte, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> was called Bewmow. Þe whech<HI REND="italic">e</HI> com to a gode man, was called Thewnyth, and was seynt Wynfryth fadur, and was a rych<HI REND="italic">e</HI> man of londes and rentys; he preyed þis Thewnyth <MILESTONE N="5"/> to ȝeue hym a place of erþe, vp-on þe wyche he mythe buldon a
<PB N="316" REF="24"/>
chyrch<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> to s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ue god inne and to p<HI REND="italic">re</HI>che goddys worde to þe pepul. Þan was þis Thewnyth gladde of hys askyng, and ordeyned hym a place, nygh<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to hys howne howce, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> he mythe w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> oþ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> sone com to goddys s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>uice. Þus þe mene tyme whyl þe chyrch<HI REND="italic">e</HI> was in byldyng, ofte he p<HI REND="italic">re</HI>ched goddys worde to þe pepul. And <MILESTONE N="5"/> Wenfrede com þidyr w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> hur fadur. And whan scheo herde hym spekyn of þe grete mede and ioye þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> mayden<HI REND="italic">us</HI> schuldyn haue in heven passyng alle oþ<HI REND="italic">ur</HI> orderes, þan hadde scheo so grete deuocion in hys seying, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> anone sche made a vow þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> scheo wolde neur<HI REND="italic">e</HI> han parte of man, bot abydon eur<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in hyr maydyn-heuede, whyl <MILESTONE N="10"/> scheo lyuid. Þan on a sonday, whan þis schyrch<HI REND="italic">e</HI> was made and byggydde, Thewnyth w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> alle hys mayne ȝode to þe chyrch<HI REND="italic">e;</HI> bot Wenfrede bode at home for a seknes, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> hur greuid, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> scheo mythe not gon w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> hem to chyrch<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Þan as scheo satte at home hur<HI REND="italic">e</HI>-one, com þere a kyng<HI REND="italic">us</HI> sone, was called Craddok, to lygge <MILESTONE N="15"/> be þis maydyn. But whan he spak to hyr of doing of þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> synne, scheo sayde, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> scheo wolde gon in to hyr schaumbur and makyn hyre more honest þan scheo was, and so comon anone to hym aȝeyne. And whan scheo com in to þe schambur, be anoþ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> dore scheo ran towarde þe chyrch<HI REND="italic">e</HI> as fast as scheo mythe, hoppyng to <MILESTONE N="20"/> haue sokur þ<HI REND="italic">er.</HI> But whan Craddok sagh<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hur renne to-werde þe chyrch<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> he oure-toke hur and sayde: bot scheo wolde assente to hys wylle, he wolde anone smyte of hur heued. Þan kneled Wene∣frede downe and seyde: 'I haue lever þ<HI REND="italic">ou</HI> do me to deth þan de∣foule my body, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> I haue makyd a vow to kepe in maydenhed, <MILESTONE N="25"/> whyl I lyve, to my lorde Jhesu Criste.' ¶ Þan Cradok oute w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> hys swerde, and at on strok smote of hyre heued. And for it was doun<HI REND="italic">e</HI> þe hyll<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to þe chyrch<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> þe hede stynt neure tomblyng, til it com þidur in sygh(t) of alle þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> weren þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI>e. Where-fore men weren so afryght, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> þei madon suche a noyce, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> Bewnow hadde mer∣vayle <MILESTONE N="30"/> whatte it myghte bene: and cam to ham to wyton whatte þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> was þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> þei maden suche a noyce. Þan whan he see þ<HI REND="italic">e</HI> heued, he toke it vp and cussed it ofte-tymes, sore wepyng, and bere it vp to þe body. And be-helde on Cradok, how he wypte hys swerde on þ<HI REND="italic">e</HI> gras þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> was alle blody of þ<HI REND="italic">e</HI> strok. Þan sayde Bewnow to <MILESTONE N="35"/> hym: 'þ<HI REND="italic">ou</HI> wykkyd man and vncely, aske mercy of god for þis horrybul dede, and ȝitte god wyl han mercy on þ<HI REND="italic">e;</HI> and if þ<HI REND="italic">ou</HI> wylt not, I pray god þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> he sende vengeans on þ<HI REND="italic">e</HI> anone'. And ryghte in syghte of alle þe pepul anone he fel dede to þ<HI REND="italic">e</HI> erþe. And þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI>∣wyth þe erþe openyd and swolowed hym doun, body and sowle, in <MILESTONE N="40"/> to helle. | ¶ Þan toke Bewnow þe hede and sette it aȝayne to þe body, and hyllyd it w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> hyr mantyl, and ȝode to hys masse. And whan he hadde songon and p<HI REND="italic">re</HI>ched þe pepul myche of þis maydyn,
<PB N="317" REF="25"/>
he sayde: god wolde not þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> sche schulde be dede ȝete, for he hadde ordeyned myche pepul to be holpe be hyr<HI REND="italic">e;</HI> wherefore he badde vche ma<HI REND="italic">n</HI> pray to god, to reyson hyr aȝeyne to lyve. And so dydde. And whan scheo seete vp, scheo wypte hyre face w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> hyr hande of þe duste þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> was þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI>onne, and spak to hym, hol and sounde, os scheo <MILESTONE N="5"/> was beforon. Þan god schewed þere þre grete miracles: on was wan þe erthe swolowed hym bodyly þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> hadde slayne hyr; anoþ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> was: for þere os þe heued abode, anone spro<HI REND="italic">n</HI>g a fayre welle þere, þor none was sene beforen; þe þrydde: whan scheo þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> was slayne ros aȝeyne to lyue. ¶ þe ferþe was: eure whil scheo lyvyd þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> was <MILESTONE N="10"/> a whyte serkul aboute hur nek, þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> as þe strok was, leke a whyte threde. Wherefore, þer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> as scheo was before called Brewa, fro þis day forth<HI REND="italic">e</HI> men called hyr Wenefrede: þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> is in englys a whyte threde. ¶ Þan see Wenefrede þe grete miracul þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> god wroght in hyr: scheo tok it heyly to herte and ȝaf hyr eure aftyr to holy <MILESTONE N="15"/> lyuyng, and nyghte and day was bysy to s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ue god, as Bewnaw tawthe hur. Þan whan scheo was p<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>fyte in alle doing, Bewnow ȝode to anoþ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> place to dwellyn. And as heo was warnyd be reuelacion, ȝode to anoþ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> place, þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> weren inne many holy virgines. And whan heo com þidur, heo lyved so p<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>fyttly in alle wayes, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> <MILESTONE N="20"/> alle token ensaumpul be hyr. And for þe whyte seme whas eure evedent tokyn of hyr martirdom, þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI>fore alle men and wo<HI REND="italic">m</HI>men haddyn grete devocion in hir wordys and in alle hur doinges; so þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> many lafton þ<HI REND="italic">e</HI> worldys occupacion and weren fayne to come and dwellyn in hyr company. So whan scheo hadde lyuid þere <MILESTONE N="25"/> fele ȝerus, scheo was warnyd be god þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> hyr deth day was nyghe. Wherefore scheo makyd hyr redy. And whan scheo hadde þe sacra∣mentys of holy chyrch<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in syght<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of alle hur systeres. scheo ȝaf hyr goste to Jhesu Criste, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> scheo louid w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> alle hur herte. And þan was beryed in a chyrch<HI REND="italic">e</HI>-ȝarde, þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> many oþer seynt<HI REND="italic">us</HI> were <MILESTONE N="30"/> beryed before. ¶ Now how þis holy seynte cam to þe abbey of Scresbery, ȝe schal heryn. Whan þe abbey of Scresbery (was new made) <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Diese in Cott. Claud. A II fehlenden worte sind aus Caj. Coll. hinzugefügt.</NOTE>, monkys of þe place made of(t) grete mone for þei hadde no seynte w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> hem for to ben her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> patron and berer of here prey∣eres to god, as other abbeys of þe cuntr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> haddon. Wherefore þe <MILESTONE N="35"/> abbotte of þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> houce, for he hadde herde before of seynt Wene∣frede, he made hys p<HI REND="italic">ri</HI>our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> gon in to Walys and sechyn where þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> scheo was byried. ¶ So wente þis p<HI REND="italic">ri</HI>oure forthe, and be grace of reuelacion of þis holy maydon he com to þe place where scheo lay; and so be strench of lordeschep and help þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> he hadde, he broute <MILESTONE N="40"/> hyr bonys in to seynt Gyles chyrch<HI REND="italic">e</HI> at Scresberyes tounos ende. And þer abode a serteyne tyme tyl þe day þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> scheo schulde be t<HI REND="italic">ra</HI>nslatid and w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> honure and worschep be broght in to þe abbey. Þan was þis day com, gr<HI REND="italic">e</HI>te multitude of pepul com þidur, in parte for a grete miracle þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> was don in þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> chirche of a chylde þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> was <MILESTONE N="45"/>
<PB N="318" REF="26"/>
helyd of a grete sekenesse, and also to do worchep to þis holy mayden. And so w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> þe abbote of þe place and þe couent w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> mony oþ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> men of holy chyrche þei browten hyr in to þe abbey and setton hyr þere þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> scheo is now. Wherefore in schorte tyme aftur god wroghte þritty grete myracles þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> ben wryton, w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>owtyn <MILESTONE N="5"/> mony othyr þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> ben not wryton, boþe of tho þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> scheo dyd in hyr lyue and oþ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> fele þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> ben wroghte at hyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> welle. To styre ȝoure deu∣ocion<HI REND="italic">e</HI> more to þis seynte, I wil telle ȝow a myracul þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> was done to a man of Erkal toune, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> was called Adam. Þis man was greuesly peynid w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> þe fallyng evel; and boþ<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hys handys weren tornyd <MILESTONE N="10"/> hyndewarde and lyne flatte to hys armys, so þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> þe armes weren stompes ande none armes; he hadde also suche a grevauns in hys on legge, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> he mythe not gone bot w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> myche pyne. So þis Adam w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> þeis þree woes w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> myche penaunce com to þe scryne of seynte Wenefrede, and was þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> in hys prayeres alle a nyght. <MILESTONE N="15"/> But on þe morowe, whate for wakyng and for wery, he felle on sclepe. And whan he woke, he felde hymself holle in alle hys lymes, and see hys handes strawte even, and sterid hys fyngres at hys lykyng, and sayed wheþ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> he myght<HI REND="italic">e</HI> gone: and ȝode forthe w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>oute gref, and felde wel þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> he was hol of alle hys sekenes. <MILESTONE N="20"/> Wherefore w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> hye voyce he thankyd god and þis holy maydon, and was so fayne of hys hele, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> he made a vow þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> he wolde neure gon from hyr, bot ben a s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vaunte in þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> chyrch<HI REND="italic">e</HI> alle hys lyfe aftur—and so he was. Þus ȝe haue ensaumpul to do worchep to þis holy maydon and martir; and ȝaf <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. Caj. Coll. <HI REND="italic">þof.</HI></NOTE> ȝe ben hol in body, ful <MILESTONE N="25"/> helte <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">C. C. <HI REND="italic">p</HI>er<HI REND="italic">aventur many of ȝow.</HI></NOTE> ȝe ben seke in soule—wherefore ȝe haue more nede to seke hur for to hauen hele in soule, þan to hauen hele in body—for ofte tyme god sendeth seknes in body to hele þe soule; bot seknes of soule is here deth bot it be helyd þe sonner. Wherefore prayeth to hyre to geton ȝow hele boþe in body and in soule, so <MILESTONE N="30"/> þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> ȝe may com to hym þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> is hele to alle sores and syknes: þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> is almythy god of heven. ¶ Also in þe toune of Scresbery seton þree men togydyr. And os þei seton talkyng, an atturcoppe, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> som<HI REND="italic">m</HI>e callyn an vryne, com oute of þe wowe and bote hem alle þree in þe nekke. Bot þogh<HI REND="italic">e</HI> it greuyd hen not at þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> tyme, bot <MILESTONE N="35"/> euel sone aftyr it rankelled, and so swall<HI REND="italic">e</HI> here þrotes and forsette here breth, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> too of þem weren dede. Þe þridde was so nygh<HI REND="italic">e</HI> dede, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> he made hys testament<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and makyd hym redy in alle wyse—for he hopyd not ellys but only deth. Þan os he lay in hys torment<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> he þoght on seynt Wenefrede and of hur myraclus. And <MILESTONE N="40"/> so as he myght, he badde hys modyr go þidir and offren a candul to þe schryne and bryng hym of þe wat<HI REND="italic">ur</HI> þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> hur bonys wheryn wassyn inne. And so scheo dudde. And whan he hadde þis wat<HI REND="italic">ur,</HI> he made to wasson hys sore þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI>wyth. And whan he hadde don soo, he feled þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> he amendyd. Þan he made a vow to seynte Wen∣fryth<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> <MILESTONE N="45"/> þ<HI REND="italic">at,</HI> if he myghte han lyf and hele, he wolde makyn an
<PB N="319" REF="27"/>
ymage of syluyr and offren to hyr. þus he mendud yche day aftur oþer, vnto þe tyme þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> he was alle hol. And þan he dud make an ymage of syluyr, os he behytte, and ȝode þidyr and ofred it vp to þe scryne, and becam hur seruaunte, eur<HI REND="italic">e</HI> whyl he leuid aftur. ¶ Also at þe day of hyr t<HI REND="italic">ra</HI>nslacion comyn oute of Walys knythes <MILESTONE N="5"/> and many men w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> hem, to be at þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> solempnite and to see þe maner þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI>of. And in her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> company com a grete man þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> was dome and mythe nothyng speke bot alle be synes. So whan þei comyn in to þe chyrch<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> sodeynly þis dome man fel doune to grownde and loste hys wytte. Þan os he lay, seynte Wenefryth com to hym and <MILESTONE N="10"/> badde hym drink of þe watur þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> hyr bonys weren wassyn inne, and he schuld ben hole of hys speche, and of oþ<HI REND="italic">ur</HI> evel þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> he hadde. Þan anone he woke &amp; badde ȝeuen hym holy wat<HI REND="italic">ur.</HI> Þan haddyn hys felowes grete wond<HI REND="italic">ur</HI> þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> þei hardyn hyn spekyn, and askyd whatte watyr þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> he wolde haue. Þan sayde he: þe watyr þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> seynt <MILESTONE N="15"/> Wynfryth bon<HI REND="italic">us</HI> weren wasyn inne. And whan he had dronkyn of þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> watyr, he was hol as any fysch<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and anone ȝode in to þe quere and before þe couent<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he tolde opynly þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> he com not þidur for no noþ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> þ(i)ng<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> bot only to sene þe doing of þ<HI REND="italic">e</HI> solempnite; 'bot now for scheo of hur grete curtesye hath ȝevyn to me my speche <MILESTONE N="20"/> and helud me in body also, I wil be hyr pylgrym hever wil I lyve'.</P>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="commentary">
<P>Die folgenden drei legenden sind aus ms. Lamb. 402 ent∣nommen. Diese hs., pap., 4, 99 foll., aus dem 15. jahrhundert, enthält 1. leben und wunder des h. Hieronymus, fol. 1-37, in 19 cap., nach der angabe des verf. zum teil aus der Leg. Aur. entnommen cap. 1, zum teil aus briefen des h. Augustin an Cyrillus cap. II—V, und des h. Cyrillus an Augustin cap. VI—XVIII, endlich ein capitel über das in einer vision der h. Brigitta dem Hieronymus von der mutter Gottes gespen∣dete lob. 2. here begynnyth Richard Hamppulle the Abbay of the holy goest full nessessarye; es sind aber 2 verschiedene abhandlungen dieses titels, die letzte ohne die angabe des ver∣fassers. 3. here begynnyth an Exitacion of comfort to them that be in parell of dethe, fol. 68 (ermahnungen und gebete für sterbende). 4. verba salvatoris fol. 75 über 9 tugenden, die der herr an den menschen liebt. 5. Worte der h. Maria an die h. Brigitta über die geburt und passion Christi, fol. 76; und 6. über die 1495 wunden Christi, fol. 83. 7. Gebet Bri∣gitta's, fol. 83<SUP>b</SUP>. 8. Ein gebet Beda's über die &amp; worte Christi am kreuze in Lat. 9. Marienlegenden, fol. 85. 10. S. Dorothea, fol. 90-94. Die meisten abhandlungen dieser hs. sind unter∣zeichnet: quod Fuller.</P>
<P><PB N="320" REF="28"/>
Die 15 Marienlegenden, kurz, skizzenartig gefasst, sind eines der wenigen überbleibsel dieses gebietes im Altenglischen; von den 42 ursprünglich im ms. Vernon enthaltenen legen∣den dieser art sind leider nur die ersten 9 übrig geblieben (die copie des ms. Vernon, ms. Addit. 22283 im Brit. museum, enthält bei seinen vielen lücken nichts davon); s. die ausgabe der Marienleg. des ms. Vernon in Herrig's Archiv, 1876, bd. 56, p. 221-236. Andere legenden dieser art sind einzeln hie und da zerstreut, so zwei im ms. Auchinl. (die erfindung des 'psalter of our lady' auch in Digby 86), Ashm. 61, Harl. 2251 u. a. <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Mehrere Marienlegenden sind in grösseren werken eingestreut, so nebst der legende von Theophilus in der südlichen legendensammlung des ms. Harl. 2277; am spätesten in das ca. 1572 gedichtete Marienleben des William Forrest (ms. Harl. 1703, enthält auch eine leg. von Theo∣philus), eines Oxforder dichters.</NOTE>—Leider ist der gröste teil untergegangen, so besonders die sammlung von 66 Marienlegenden, die Barbour (oder richtiger Barber) in den einleitungsversen seiner grossen legendensamm∣lung unter seinen religiösen werken nennt.</P>
<P>Dorothea ist eine prosa-umdichtung der aus der Leg. Aur. übertragenen poetischen legende dieser heiligen (gedruckt in der 'Sammlung Altengl. Leg.', Heilbronn 1878, p. 91) mit der sie im ganzen und einzelnen übereinstimmt, nicht selten im wortlaut.</P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="legend">
<HEAD>II. Marienlegenden.</HEAD>
<HEADNOTE><P>Aus ms. Lamb. 432, fol. 95.</P></HEADNOTE>
<P N="1">1. A curatt hadde in his p<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>ishe a paryshen<HI REND="italic">e</HI> rebell, vnbuxu<HI REND="italic">m</HI> and malicious, that did till him many Iniurijes and harmys: whom the curat blamyd him ofte and wold haue amendid him. But ffor-thy that he was hardennyd and evill incorigeble, he cursid him. Sone after that the curatt died. Whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he was dede, the cursid man <MILESTONE N="5"/> repentid him, dreding dampnac<HI REND="italic">i</HI>on, and habuntdantly weping and sorowing come to the preest and tolde him all the sothe. The preest sent him to the byshop, the byshope sent him to the pope. He went fforthe, sorowing and weping. But ffor he herd tell of an holy hermyte in Egipte, he went to be consaylid of hym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> When <MILESTONE N="10"/> he had told the hermyte his counseile, the hermyte said: 'iff thou do after my bidding, thou shalt goo to the ffole in Alesaundre: and he shall say the what thou shalt do'. The curssid man than be∣ganne to wepe bitterly and said: 'allas that eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> y was borne, senne that y may ffynde no remedye for my synne'. The hermyte <MILESTONE N="15"/> said: 'sonne, wepe nott! he is no ffole, as men wenyth, but he is
<PB N="321" REF="29"/>
an holy man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and a grete clerke; and for the love of god and the kingdom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of heuen he ffaynyth hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> a ffole, that he be dispisid in this world and aftir this regne in the tother w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> Crist; and he louyth mykkell the blessid virgyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> seint Marye, and he is mekill louyd of herr<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> I shall write to him for the'. He toke a lettir of <MILESTONE N="5"/> the hermyte and come to Alexaundre. And ther he sawe the ffole cum in to the cite, and many ran after him, casting stonys at hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and many Iniurijs doing to hym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> At evyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he went ffrom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the citee and come to an old chapell. And the cursid man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> com<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to hym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> weping and sobbyng, and ffell to his ffeet and gaffe him the <MILESTONE N="10"/> lett<HI REND="italic">er.</HI> Whan he had sene the lett<HI REND="italic">er</HI> and wist the cause of his comyng, he ffell downe on the erthe in prayers. And he lying long praying, at the last com goddis moder in to the chapell, and with her many gloriouse virginis, angelis and archangelis, and a multitude of þe courte of heuen, and the chapell shone as the sonne∣beme, <MILESTONE N="15"/> and the cursid hidde him in a herne of the chapell for fferd∣nesse. The ffole roese and toke (t)his <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">his</HI> statt <HI REND="italic">this.</HI></NOTE> cursid man by the hand and said: 'drede the nought!' And he led hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to seint Marye and ffell down<HI REND="italic">e</HI> byffor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> her and prayed her to haue m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>cy on that synffull man<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> telling her sothe. Than said she: 'knowist þ<HI REND="italic">ou</HI> him þat <MILESTONE N="20"/> þ<HI REND="italic">ou</HI> cursiddist, yf thou saw him?' He said: 'ye, my lady'. Than she said: 'go seke him, yf þ<HI REND="italic">ou</HI> may ffynd hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in this Couent!' He sought him and found hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and brought hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to godd<HI REND="italic">is</HI> moder. Than comaundid she hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to assoyle the cursid man<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And whan that was done, the vision<HI REND="italic">e</HI> passid away, and he, assoylid, went <MILESTONE N="25"/> home with Joye.</P>
<P N="2">2. A man was ravishid in his dome, that was opressid w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> many synnys. And the devill accusid hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that he had lyvid all his lyff-tyme in synne, that all the goed dedis that he had done, his euyll dedis wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> many-ffold mor<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> God commaundid to way his <MILESTONE N="30"/> evill dedis and the goed. Than the sinfull man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in all his hert incallid the blessid lady, Goddis moder and moder of mercy, seint Mary: and she layd her hond on the weght-scale wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the ffewe goed dedis war<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> The devill in all his myght druȝhe out the other syde. | But the moder of mercy deliu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>id the synfull man. <MILESTONE N="35"/></P>
<P N="3">3. Hit is red in Vitas patrum of a sinfull man, that all the goed dedis he did<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> all-yf thay wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffewe, he did them in the honour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of seint Marye. He was taken in siknesse, and his soule brought to the dome, and, his conscience witnessing, he wist him dampnable. His dedis wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> weyen<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> but his evill dedis wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffull mykell <MILESTONE N="40"/> hevyer. The blissid virgyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> prayed her sonne ffor that soule. Her sonne said: 'moder, thou wotest well, by rightwisnesse and dome he is worthi dampnac<HI REND="italic">i</HI>on'. His moder said: 'iff rightwysnesse aske that, y aske thy mercy, that thou yeff me a drope of thy blode'. Her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> sonne said: 'swettest moder, that y ought to do to the ffor <MILESTONE N="45"/>
<PB N="322" REF="30"/>
manhode I hadde of thee'. ‖ She laid the droppe of blode on the p<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>te of the goed dedis: and hit weyid mor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> than the evill dedis, as hitt wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> a grete mountayngne.</P>
<P N="4">4. A yong (wo)man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">man</HI> statt <HI REND="italic">woman.</HI></NOTE>, devoute in the s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vice of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lady, was wedded, and dwellid with hirr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> brother. And, by intysing of the <MILESTONE N="5"/> devill, her brother begatt on her a child; and þe secund tyme, and the thirde tyme he did so. She beholding the gretnesse of her synne, byganne to dispayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and thought for to sle her selffe: and toke a grete spider and swellowid hit in. When the woman was scalid in all her bodye and she bolnyd and drewe to the dede, <MILESTONE N="10"/> in grete sorow and turment she incallid the moder of mercy, saying: 'goed lady, haue mynde of the dayes in whicche y seruyd the, and haue m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>cy on me in this grete article of my nede!' And at that voyse the moder of god stode byffore her, and ffirst blamid hir of her synne, and sithyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> confortid hir benyngly and made her in <MILESTONE N="15"/> goed hope, and with her virgyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hond stroke her body, that was dyyng, ffro the heed to the ffete and drove away all the swelling and the venym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and made her all hole. Then the woman lefte all the world and inclosid her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and ffro that forthe lyvid in sharpe penaunce. <MILESTONE N="20"/></P>
<P N="5">5. IN the yer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord a thousand thre hundyrd and ffifty in the bishoprich of Norwiche too ffrerus p<HI REND="italic">re</HI>chours excitid and stirid a man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> languyssing, to shryve him preuely of all his synnys. He behight that he wold, but he defferrid for to do hitt. In the nyght ffolowing the syke man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thought that a man shewid him a <MILESTONE N="25"/> boke; in the whiche he sawe written these wordis: 'luff god and pray the blissid virgyn Marye, and she shall deliu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> the from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> p<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>ell'. After that vicion<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he thought besely howe he myght best shewe his synnys. Thus thinking, sodenly he ffell on slepe: and a hande sodeynly stoppid his mouthe and his nosethrillis, that he <MILESTONE N="30"/> myght not brethe, but he thought that he shuld fast dye; than a voyce sounde in his er<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> saying: 'wrecche, trowist thou now to be verray repentaunt and with a ffey<HI REND="italic">n</HI>ing contric<HI REND="italic">i</HI>on do away all thy synnys? loo, thy sleuthe of thy necligence hathe brought vengeance to the, forthi that thi mynde is hardennyd in <MILESTONE N="35"/> evill and wold not confesse the in tyme'. Than he thought on the tother vision, and swithely he incallid the blissid mayden<HI REND="italic">e</HI> for socour<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> saying in his thoughte: 'blessid moder of god, quene of heuen, do that thou hight, and deliu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> me of this parell! that thy blessid name Maria be hallowid in me'. Vnnethis had he prayed <MILESTONE N="40"/> thus in his thought, and loo, the moder of m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>cy apperid and put the hande ffrom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> his mouthe and delyu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>id him from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> opp<HI REND="italic">re</HI>ssion<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of the devill. He shroffe hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and shewid the myracle.</P>
<P N="6">6. Att Westmynster be-syde London<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> in the ffeest of Petir and Paule, com a pore womman<HI REND="italic">e</HI> with her sonne blynde fro his byrthe <MILESTONE N="45"/>
<PB N="323" REF="31"/>
and deuoutly prayd byfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the auter of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lady, goddis moder, and made the pament wete with teris. She rose and said to a monke, keper of that awter<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and of the ymage: 'the Quene of heuen apperid to me and monyshing <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">and m.</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">admon.,</HI> oder <HI REND="italic">and</HI> ist zu tilgen.</NOTE> the by me that thou shalt weshe the ffeet and bathe the ymages of seint Marie and her son in <MILESTONE N="5"/> her kne, and with that wat<HI REND="italic">er</HI> so halowid washe the yen of this blind childe with thy ffyngers!' ‖ Whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he cast wat<HI REND="italic">er</HI> in the yhen of this blinde child, a foule bl<HI REND="italic">o</HI>de passid from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> them<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and all the blyndnesse vanyshid away. And the childe wonderd in beholding of (the) <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">the</HI> fehlt im ms.</NOTE> fayrnesse of the too ymages. <MILESTONE N="10"/></P>
<P N="7">7. A man, for his sonne langwisshing to the dethe drery and so∣rowffull, made an ymage of wax of the weghte of his sonne, for to send to saynt Marye of Rochemod<HI REND="italic">er.</HI> And thus the child was laid in one scale, and the wex in a nother. And sone the childe, semyd <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">l. <HI REND="italic">semyng,</HI> oder <HI REND="italic">that semyd.</HI></NOTE> to yelde up the goest, gaff a laghter, and by the meritis of sent <MILESTONE N="15"/> Marie the child was made all hole.</P>
<P N="8">8. Hit was a knyght that drowhe to age, and his wiff w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> the assent of her husbond avowid chastite. After that a ffewe yeris, be entising of the devill, he knewe his wif, ageynis her will, and sho gaff to the devill what-sum-evir hit was that was gettyn<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> She <MILESTONE N="20"/> consayvid and bare a sunne. Whan he was of twelffe yer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> old, the devill apperid to his modir and said: 'yeld that thou behight me!' Than the moder, as often as she lokid apon her sonne, she wept bitterly. Her sonne askid why she wepte, when she byhield hym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> She said: for-thy that she gaff him to the devill, and told hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <MILESTONE N="25"/> all. | Than her sonne went to the pope, to aske counsaill. The pope sent him with letteris to the byshop of Jher<HI REND="italic">usa</HI>l<HI REND="italic">e</HI>m. And the byshop sent him to an hermyte, to whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> angellis mynyst<HI REND="italic">er</HI>id at masse and that brought him brede white as snow. The hermyte, whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he knewe the cause of commyng, said: 'hit is nedfull to the <MILESTONE N="30"/> to aske helpe of the blissid maid and moder Marye'. When<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the day was comyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in the whicche the devill monyshid to reyve hym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> the hermyte held him all that tyme besyde him. | And when he sang his masse, he sett him bytwixe him and the awter<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> p<HI REND="italic">ra</HI>ying the blissid mayden for hym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Aboute the pater noster the devill reft <MILESTONE N="35"/> him and bare him to hell. But the blissid mayden<HI REND="italic">e</HI> by the p<HI REND="italic">ra</HI>yer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of her seruand deliu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>id hym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And when the hermyte said Pax dom(ini), the yong man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> answerid: Et cum spiritu tuo. The her∣myte gaff him his blessing and sent him to comfforte his ffreendis.</P>
<P N="9">9. IN Ynglond at Licheffield was a clerke devoute to seint Anne <MILESTONE N="40"/> of custome: whan he said the Aue Maria gratia plena, dominus te∣cum, benedicta tu in mulieribus et benedictus fructus ventris tui Jh<HI REND="italic">esus</HI> <NOTE N="4" PLACE="foot">In ms. fehlt <HI REND="italic">he joinid</HI> od. <HI REND="italic">addid.</HI></NOTE>, ‖ (he joinid) Et benedicta sit sancta tua mater Anna ex (qua) sine macula processit tua scissima caro virgenia. | Eftir this clerke was ffull seke
<PB N="324" REF="32"/>
and lost his speche. His ffellawis and ffrendis were come for to visitt him. And as thay satt speking of diu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>se thing<HI REND="italic">es,</HI> the sike man had his tong, and said: 'be ye still, be ye still! loo my lady seint Anne, w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> her our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> all day (!) her blessid doughter, seint Marye'. And thus seying . . . . (unvollendet). <MILESTONE N="5"/></P>
<P N="10">10. A conuers<HI REND="italic">e</HI> suffred many temptacio<HI REND="italic">n</HI>is of the devill, | wherfore he was pynyd. He sought remedy of mony, but he ffound none. At the last he was taught of (a) religeous man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> for to say ageynyst the devill Aue Maria. When he had so done, the devill passid away as a whirlewynde, crying and saying: 'the devill strike out his <MILESTONE N="10"/> tethe that taught the thatt<HI REND="italic">e</HI>' e. cet.</P>
<P N="11">11. A noble knyght and a riche fforsoke þe world and enterid the ord<HI REND="italic">i</HI>re of Cist<HI REND="italic">er</HI>nenc<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And for he couthe no lett<HI REND="italic">er,</HI> hym was gevyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> a master forto teche him. But whan he hadde be long w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> his master, he myght not lerne, but these two wordis: Aue Maria. But <MILESTONE N="15"/> theym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he had eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> in mynde and seid them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>-outen seassing, whedd<HI REND="italic">er</HI>-so-eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> he went or what-sumeu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> he did. Whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he was dede and buried, on his grave sprang a lilly, and eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>y leeff had written Aue Maria with golden letteris: the rote therof sprang out of the dede mannys mouthe. <MILESTONE N="20"/></P>
<P N="12">12. A womman taught a child for to say the Ave Maria oft sithe to our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lady, and moest when he was dreding <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">dreding for dreding for.</HI></NOTE> ffor any thing. When the child w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> other childre was gone to play him on the see-sand, the flode come and vmbilapped them<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> The childe, dreding, said deuoutly the heylsing of the angell. Whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> other children were <MILESTONE N="25"/> drownyd, a ffayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> woman come and in her bosum<HI REND="italic">m</HI>e led him to þ<HI REND="italic">e</HI> land harmless.</P>
<P N="13">13. A nonne enformyd a wenche, her coȝyn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> ffor to say oft the Aue Maria kneling in the chirche, numering the Ju<HI REND="italic">n</HI>cturis of hir handdys. After this she dyed. Therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> her master<HI REND="italic">s</HI> <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">masters</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">mastres.</HI></NOTE> was sorou∣full, <MILESTONE N="30"/> and after sorowing and weping she ffell aslepe. To whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the blissid mayden<HI REND="italic">e</HI> apperid, leding with herr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the forsaid wenche, asking hirr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> whi she sorowid so. ‖ She answerid: 'lady, ffor the wenche is dede that was in my keping, whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> y taught to haylse the by the Juncturis of her hondis'. To whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lady said: <MILESTONE N="35"/> 'loo her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the wench<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> se the Juncturis of hir hondis!' When she bihielde the wenche, she sawe p<HI REND="italic">re</HI>cyouse stonys in the Junctures of her hondis, that made hem<HI REND="italic">e</HI> all shynyng.</P>
<P N="14">14. Abbot John<HI REND="italic">e</HI> de Bellavilla, when he <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">he he.</HI></NOTE> lay in his last day: long as he <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">he he.</HI></NOTE> had bene dede <NOTE N="4" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">dede</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">seke.</HI></NOTE>, he was ravishid in spiritt. And when<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he <MILESTONE N="40"/> com<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ageyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and was askid what he sawe, he sayd this: 'a thing y say you, that hit suffice to you: he that wilbe saf <NOTE N="5" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">ffals</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">saf.</HI></NOTE>, haylse he often
<PB N="325" REF="33"/>
the blissid mayden<HI REND="italic">e</HI>'. And so sayeng, he yelde up the goest. Full devoutly he servid the blessid virgyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and ofte sithis heylsid hir. Hit was said of this Abbott that oft sithe when he song masse and bowing his body in reuerence, he sawe the likenesse of the gloriouse virgyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> straynyng her son in her armys. <MILESTONE N="5"/></P>
<P N="15">15. A devoute womman in a day as she stode byfore the ymage of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lady Marye, haylsyng <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">hayslyng.</HI></NOTE> hirr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> said Aue Maria, with grete deuoc<HI REND="italic">i</HI>on<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> She hard a voyse of the ymagis mouthe, saying to hir: 'what doest thou?' The womman<HI REND="italic">e</HI> mekely answerid: 'lady, do y nought wele?' The voys said: 'yis; but thou may do bettir.' She <MILESTONE N="10"/> said: 'goed lady, what shall I do or say?' The voyse said: 'wote thou not that all the honour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and goednesse that y haue, I haue hit of my sonne? and ther-ffor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> haylse hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffyrst, and then me'. She said: 'lady, what shall y say?' The voyse said: 'halse my sonne saying Aue benigne Jh<HI REND="italic">esu</HI>'. <MILESTONE N="15"/></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="legend">
<HEAD>III. S. Dorothea.</HEAD>
<HEADNOTE><P>Aus ms. Lamb. 432, fol. 90.</P></HEADNOTE>
<P>The right gloriouse virgyn seint Dorothee come down<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of the noble blode off the senatours of Rome. Hir ffadir hight Dorotheo, and her modir hight Theodera. <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">Theodera</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">Theodora.</HI></NOTE> In that tyme p<HI REND="italic">er</HI>secuc<HI REND="italic">i</HI>on of crysten<HI REND="italic">e</HI> peple was passing grete in the londe of Romaynis. Wherfore this blessid Dorotheo, dispising the ydolis, forsoke Rome and all his <MILESTONE N="5"/> pocessiounys, that is to say wyffis, castellic, and housis, and saylid w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> his wyf Theode<HI REND="italic">r</HI>a <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">Theodera</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">Theodora.</HI></NOTE> and with his II doughteris, that hight Cristyne and Callestyn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> till thay come to the Realme of Capodose and in the cite of Sesaream. Where-in thay dwelling brought fforthe a doughter, of whose lyff we entend to speke now by the g<HI REND="italic">ra</HI>ce of <MILESTONE N="10"/> god. Whenne this child was bore, she was preuely baptiȝed in the maner of cristen peaple of an holy man, byshop Appollinarye, and put to her a name of the ffader name and the moder and namyd her Dorothea. ‖ And she anone ffulffillid with the holy goest, taught w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> vertu and holy discipline, and she was wond<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ly ffayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> above <MILESTONE N="15"/> all the maydennys of the regeon<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> dispising the world<HI REND="italic">e</HI> w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> all his vanyteis in a fferuent love of god w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> pouerte, and ffull of meke∣nesse and of charite. ‖ The ffende not susteynyng her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> chastite ffor envy that he had to hirr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> goddnesse, sett a-ffyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in her love ffabric<HI REND="italic">i</HI>on, provoest of that lond. The whicche the ffende styrid so <MILESTONE N="20"/> besely w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> vnforsing <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">L. <HI REND="italic">enforsing.</HI></NOTE> of vnclene luffe to this virgyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> seint Dorothea, that he sent for herr<HI REND="italic">e;</HI> ‖ behoting her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> tresour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and all man<HI REND="italic">er</HI> of goddis w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>outen no<HI REND="italic">u</HI>mbr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and for to take her as for his wyf with∣out any determynac<HI REND="italic">i</HI>on. This hering, blessid Dorothea dispising all sleame and mukke and worldly richesse, and w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>out any drede <MILESTONE N="25"/> she knowlegid her lyff openly, that she was frely and truly maried
<PB N="326" REF="34"/>
to our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord Jh<HI REND="italic">esu</HI> Crist. ‖ The whicche ffabrici<HI REND="italic">us</HI> hering was all sett on-ffyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in woddnesse, comaunding anone that she be put in a tonne of brennyng oyle. And she, withe the helpe of her spouse Jh<HI REND="italic">esu</HI> Cryst<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> abode ther-in w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>out any dissease, Joying her ther-in, as thoughe she had bene anoyntid w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> a preciouse oyneme<HI REND="italic">n</HI>t of <MILESTONE N="5"/> bawme. Wherfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> many of the paynymis, seyng this grete myracle, wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> conu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>tid to god. But verreyly this tyraunt bilievid that she didde all this by wychcrafte, and comaunded her to be reclusid in p<HI REND="italic">re</HI>son<HI REND="italic">e</HI> IX dayes without mete or drinke. But she was norishid and ffedde w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> gloriouse angelis: so that, when she come out of <MILESTONE N="10"/> the preson<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and was brought forthe byfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the Juge, she apperid more ffayrer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> than<HI REND="italic">e</HI> eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> she was byffor<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Wherfore all the peple wonderd that she myght be so ffayr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and so long kept w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>out mete or drinke. ‖ Than said the Juge to hirr<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> 'but yf thou worship my goddis, thou shalt not escape the turnament <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">L. <HI REND="italic">turment.</HI></NOTE> of þ<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Jebett'. And <MILESTONE N="15"/> she answerid: 'sadly I worship onely god, and not feendis'. And she ffell down<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffull strayte to the erthe, lyfting up her Ihen vn-to heuen, and prayed god how that he wold graunt and shewe his grete myght howe that he is only god, and none other ther besyde hym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Than ffabricius arose up ffrom his pilloir<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and sett his <MILESTONE N="20"/> ydollis ther-on. And in-contynent a gret multitude of angell<HI REND="italic">is</HI> comyng <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">comynȳ</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">comyng.</HI></NOTE> with grete myght threwe downe the Idolis, so that no part of the pillour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> myght be ffounde. And thay herd the voyse of ffendis thoroughe the erthe crying: ‖ 'O Dorothea, why doest thou distroy us and turment us?' And ffor this myracle many thous∣antis <MILESTONE N="25"/> of paynymmys wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> openly conu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>tid to our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord Jh<HI REND="italic">esu</HI> Crist and enterid in to the crown<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of martyris. | And than this holy virgyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> was hangid apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> a Jebbet, her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffete upward, and all her holy bodi all to-drawen with hokis of yryn<HI REND="italic">e;</HI> she was beten w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> roddis and scourgis, and after sett hote ffyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI>-brondis to her <MILESTONE N="30"/> tendyr brest<HI REND="italic">is,</HI> and she, halffe dede, was reclusid ageyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in to pres∣oune till the morne. The morow day ffolowing she was brought fforthe all hole w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>out spott or any dissease. Wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI>-of the Juge wondred gretly and said to her: 'O thou ffayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> maid, yett thou shalt turne ageyne, ffor thou art chastiȝed ynoughe'. ‖ And than<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <MILESTONE N="35"/> he sent to hirr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> two of her susters, Crystean<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and Callestyn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> the whicche for drede of deth wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> turnyd away ffrom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Crist Jh<HI REND="italic">esu:</HI> and thay shuld labour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to her suster Dorothea ffor to withdrawe her from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the ffeythe. Than blessid Dorothea spak to her susteris so swetly and so graciously, that she toke ffrom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> all the blynd∣nesse <MILESTONE N="40"/> of her hertis and conuertid them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffully to god. Knowing this ffabrici<HI REND="italic">us</HI> by her two susters, he bound her bakkis to ged<HI REND="italic">i</HI>r and threwe them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> bothe in grete ffyr<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And than he said to Dorothea: 'how long wilt thou drawe us long w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> thy whicche∣crafte? othir do sacreffice and lyffe, or ellis resayue the sentence <MILESTONE N="45"/> of thyne hede smytten<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of'. And she answerid w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> a gladde cher<HI REND="italic">e:</HI>
<PB N="327" REF="35"/>
'what-eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> thou wilt, y am redy to suffre for my lord Jh<HI REND="italic">es</HI>u Crist, my spouse, in whose gardeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffull of delytis I haue gaderid rosis and appelis'. Hering this the tyraunt, trembling for anger with-in him-selffe, comaundid that her ffayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> vysage shuld be bete w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> stavis, and so, that ther shuld no-thing aper<HI REND="italic">e</HI> no maner ffetur<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in <MILESTONE N="5"/> her vysage, and so kept on to the morow. ‖ The day following she was brought ffully curid and made hole and full of beaute by her trusty spouse and saviour<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> ffor whose worship and luff she toke apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> her this hard and travellous battayle. And then he gaff the sentence that her hede shuld be smytten<HI REND="italic">e</HI> off. And she was ledde <MILESTONE N="10"/> without the towne-wallis of the cite. Moreovir Theophilus, the grete notarye of that Realme, sawe and bihilde these thingis: and, as in scorne, he prayed her that she wold shewe him rosis and appellis of the gardeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of her spouse, and gretly he prayed her therof. The which prayer she grauntid him, not-w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>stonding that tyme <MILESTONE N="15"/> was right grete cold, bothe ffrost and snowe. And when she come to the place of her martirdom, she prayed to our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lorde ffor all tho that in worship of her name hallowithe her passioune, that thay be kept in every tribulac<HI REND="italic">i</HI>on, and specially to be delyu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>id ffrom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the shame of pouerte and ffals fame, and in thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> end that thay may <MILESTONE N="20"/> haue verray contric<HI REND="italic">i</HI>on <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">contrucon̄.</HI></NOTE> and remission<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of all her synnys; ‖ and wommen<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. A <HI REND="italic">womman</HI>e.</NOTE> with child, that callid to hir name ffor thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> helpe, that thay may ffynde comfort and p<HI REND="italic">ro</HI>ffitte in her sorowis and tribula∣c<HI REND="italic">i</HI>o<HI REND="italic">n</HI>is; ‖ also she prayed that, where her lyff wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> writtyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in ony place or house, that hit myght be kepte from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> all maner of parellis, of <MILESTONE N="25"/> thund<HI REND="italic">er,</HI> lightenyng or any other myschaunce, and ffrom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the parellis of thevis and all soden<HI REND="italic">e</HI> dethis, and that <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">thay that.</HI></NOTE> thay shall resseyue the holy sacrament at her ende ffor herre souerayne diffence agaynys all goestly parellis. ‖ And also sone as she had made her prayer, ther come a voyse from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> heuen, and said to hirr<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> 'cum, my desyrid <MILESTONE N="30"/> spouse! ffor all that ye askid and prayid ffor, hit is grauntid yow, and thay that ye pray ffor, shalbe savid'. | Than this blessid virgine bowid her hede vn-to the stroke of þe swerd: and ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> apperid a ffayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> child, clothid in purpur, barffote, with cryspe her<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> whose clothis were all springelid w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> bright sterris; bering in his hand a <MILESTONE N="35"/> litill panyer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> whith thre rosis and thre appellis, and he p<HI REND="italic">ro</HI>ferid them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to the virgyn<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> To whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the blissid virgyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Dorothea said: 'I pray yow, my lord, that ye will bere hem<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to Theophile, the scrybe'. And anone she resayuyd the martirdome by ffabricion<HI REND="italic">e</HI> preffect<HI REND="italic">e</HI> vnder Dyoclusyon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and to Maxemyane Emp<HI REND="italic">er</HI>our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of Rome, <MILESTONE N="40"/> CClxxx VIII yere of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord god. ‖ Theophile than stonding in the pallice of the p<HI REND="italic">re</HI>cedent, this child apperid to hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and toke hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> this baskett, saying to him here thus: 'these rosis and appellis my suster sendith to the from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> paradyse of her spouse' and anone the
<PB N="328" REF="36"/>
the child vanyshid away. Than all ffor-wondred Teophile brake out in praysing J<HI REND="italic">hesu</HI> Crist, God of Dorothea, 'that in that tyme of so grete colde as ther was than in ffebruarij, that the lond was ou<HI REND="italic">er</HI>-covirde w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> ffrost and snowe and no grene appering in noone (place, hath sent this) <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Diese worte fehlen im ms.</NOTE>; truly, truly, he that hathe sent this is of <MILESTONE N="5"/> grete power, of whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the name be blissid withouten end, amen'. And so by his p<HI REND="italic">re</HI>ching and affermyng all that cite was co<HI REND="italic">n</HI>u<HI REND="italic">er</HI>tid to our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord Jh<HI REND="italic">esu</HI> Crist. Perseyuyng this the tyraunt, he turmentid Teophile, the scribe, w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> many moo cruell man<HI REND="italic">er</HI>es of turmentours than Dorothea resayuyd, and at the last he was cutt in smale pecis <MILESTONE N="10"/> and comaundid to be cast to wilde beestis and byrdis, to be deuourid. But ffirst he resayuyd baptyme and the holy sacrament of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lordis bodye: and so ffolowing the blissid virgyne Dorothea he come to Crist that gloryfied his sayntis, and be gloreffied in hem<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> the consubstanciall and coeternall with the ffader and the holy <MILESTONE N="15"/> goest, lyvith and reynyth god by all the worldis of worldis Iblessid amen. <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Darunter steht in der hs.: 
<Q><P>Gaude virgo Dorothea, ex stirpe nata nobili: Esto aduocatrix, queso, mea, in hac valle flebili. Gaude quia reliquisti prefectum ffabricium Et in sponsu assu<HI REND="italic">m</HI>pcisti Cristum dei ffilium. Gaude quia in feruen∣tis olei missa doleu<HI REND="italic">m,</HI> De calore nichill sentis dei per auxilium. Gaude carcerata fameque cruciata Pulcryor &amp; [ms. <HI REND="italic">a</HI> st. 7] magis grata sis <MILESTONE N="5"/> quam vnquam antea. Gaude quia, columpna facta et distrecto ydoleo, Demonum gen(s)est subacta, conuersio multo populo. Gaude quod post exquisita tormentorum genera ffax fferuenter et ignita appo<HI REND="italic">ni</HI>tur ad v(is)cera. Gaude quia conuertisti sorores ad dominum Et ffactas mar∣tires misisti ad ipsum patrem hominum. Gaude ffacie vulnerata seuo <MILESTONE N="10"/> ictu ffustiu<HI REND="italic">m,</HI> In crastino sic es sanata quod no(n) paret vestigeu<HI REND="italic">m.</HI> Gaude quia propter ffructus &amp; rosas temporandas P<HI REND="italic">er</HI> te scriba est adductus ad Cristi ffamulias. Gaude quia impetrasti cunctis te neuer∣antibus Quidquid eis . . . . . (wort fehlt) et precipue pregnantibus. O preciosa margarita, virgo sancta Dorothea, cor mundum in nobis <MILESTONE N="15"/> crea.</P>
<P>O omnipotens sempiterne deus, in cuius nomine gloriosa virgo &amp; martir Dorothea multorum tormentorum genera superauit, te supplices exoramus ut eius meritis et precibus cuncta pericula devitamus et ipsam scelerem adiutricem nostris nessessitatibus senciamus, per <MILESTONE N="20"/> xpm dominum nostrum amen. quod Fuller.</P></Q></NOTE></P>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="legend">
<HEAD>IV. S. Hieronymus.</HEAD>
<HEADNOTE><P>Aus ms. Lamb. 432, fol. 1.</P></HEADNOTE>
<DIV3 TYPE="introduction">
<HEAD>(Einleitung.)</HEAD>
<P>RIght nobill and worthy lady and my full reu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ent and dere goestly doughter in oure lord Jh<HI REND="italic">esu,</HI> I haue mynd how on seint Jerommys day, that is the morow after Myhelmasse-day, after y had told you sumwhat of the lyf and miracles of seint Jerom, I said that with our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lordis helpe, when y had leysour<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> y wold write his lyf and <MILESTONE N="5"/>
<PB N="329" REF="37"/>
myraclis in ynglyshe, to praysyng and honour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord and of hym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> | and that not only ye shuld knowe hit the more clerely to yo<HI REND="italic">ur</HI> gostely p<HI REND="italic">ro</HI>fecte, but also hit shuld mow abyde and turne to edificac<HI REND="italic">i</HI>on of othir that wold rede hit and do to copy hitt, for your<HI REND="italic">e</HI> selffe, and sithe to lat other to rede hit and copy hit, who so will. For <MILESTONE N="5"/> ther is ther-in nedfull to be had and know and had in mynd of all ffolke. For in the ffyrst V <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Die zahl ist im ms. undeutlich.</NOTE> chapitres we may lerne and take ensampill to lyffe in crystynma<HI REND="italic">n</HI>nis lyff in penaunce and straytnesse, and in the VII<SUP>the</SUP> and in the IX<SUP>the</SUP> chapiters we may lerne to dye. | And what is more nessessarye to any man or womman in erthe than con lyve and dye? <MILESTONE N="10"/> Sothely all ffolke lyve and dye, and eche man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that lyvith not well he shall dye. ‖ But ffull fewe ther bene that can lyve and dye. What is it to conne lyve and dye, but to <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">the</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">to.</HI></NOTE> lyue so that we be alwey redy to dye; so to haue our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hert and our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> soule redy vnto god, that we abyde dethe as the cummyng of a lovid ffrend þat we <MILESTONE N="15"/> desyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to goo with from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> wrechednesse vn-to delycio<HI REND="italic">us</HI> <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">Fehlt <HI REND="italic">lyfe?</HI></NOTE>? Than lerne we to lyve and dye; ffor hit is so gret dulness not to cun do, ne be about to lerne, that thing that euery man dothe and must nedis do. But yf hit seme over-hard to vse the sharpe discipline of this scole where we shull lerne this holsom lesson; than we may <MILESTONE N="20"/> loke in the thirde, ffourthe, and ffyfte chapitres and se the grace and the reward that is yeven<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that fferuently lobour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> about this lernyng. ‖ And yf the comfort of so gret reward make not our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hard hertis to melt, then we may se in the VIII<SUP>the</SUP> and X<SUP>the</SUP> chapitres the strayt<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <NOTE N="4" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">straito.</HI></NOTE> dome we go to, and the gret paynys <MILESTONE N="25"/> that bene put after this lyf vnto all truant<HI REND="italic">is;</HI> that we beholding therof may breke oure dulnesse, and hast us to go lerne and tra∣veyle in the scole of penaunce. And yf we behote our<HI REND="italic">e</HI>-selffe long lyf, thinking that hit wolbe long or this reward or paynys com, and so wex wery to abyde so long in straytnesse and tribu∣lac<HI REND="italic">i</HI>on <MILESTONE N="30"/> without comfort, and þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI>for<HI REND="italic">e</HI> begynne to play wanton<HI REND="italic">e</HI> among the lustis of the world and of the fflesshe, while we shull studye in the scole: than loke in the VI<SUP>te</SUP>, XII, XIII, XIIII, XV, XVI, XVII, and XVIII chapitres, and we shall see how mercyfull our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord, after he hathe suffred his scolers to be chastiȝed a litill while, <MILESTONE N="35"/> anone he helpeth than<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and deliu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ith them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> dissease, not only in theyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> dethe but also in this present lyff; and ageyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI>∣ward he ffrely <NOTE N="5" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">he frely he.</HI></NOTE> betith all truantis as well with temporall vengeaunce as w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> endles payn<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And so he gynyth in (t)his lyf to bothe her reward and punyshing, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> we shuld oþ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> for love of joye or for <MILESTONE N="40"/> drede of payne, temp<HI REND="italic">or</HI>all <NOTE N="6" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">temp</HI>er<HI REND="italic">all</HI> mit der abbrev. für <HI REND="italic">er.</HI></NOTE> or eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>lasting, stabely and hastely sett
<PB N="330" REF="38"/>
us to entre and to abyde in þis scole to lerne to lyve and to dye, and so we shalbe the bett<HI REND="italic">er</HI> willid þerto. At the last in the XIX chapitre our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> mercifull lady yevith herr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> blessing to all sucche scolers. ‖ And in all these chapitres we may se the grete worthi∣nesse and holynesse of him that was bothe a disciple and a master <MILESTONE N="5"/> in this scole: seint Jerome; how holy and strayte he was in lyving, and how myghti and m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>velous aftir his deth; and p<HI REND="italic">ro</HI>fitable hit is to do aftir him and to do him s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vice. ‖ Thus is this warke devidid in to XIX chapitres, that ye shull not ovir-wery to rede hit, while ye may at eche chapitres ende haue a resting place, yf <MILESTONE N="10"/> ye haue leysour<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> to rede no more at onys, and anoþ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> tyme rede anoþ<HI REND="italic">er.</HI></P>
<P>The ffyrst chapitr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> is of the lyff of seint Jerome, as hit is take of legendea aurea.</P>
<P>The secund is of his lyf as seint Austyn writith in his pistell. <MILESTONE N="15"/></P>
<P>The thirde is that seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> apperid to seint Austyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in gret joye and swetnesse the same oure of his dethe.</P>
<P>The IIII<SUP>te</SUP> is howe IIII other men had a m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>uelouse vision of seint Jerome þe same our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> þat he dyed.</P>
<P>The V<SUP>te</SUP> is how seint John<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Baptist and seint Jerome, arayed <MILESTONE N="20"/> bothe alyke, apperid to seint Austyn<HI REND="italic">e.</HI></P>
<P>The VI<SUP>te</SUP> is howe be m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>itis of s. Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> th(r)e <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">the.</HI></NOTE> men wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> areysid from dethe to lyff in distrucc<HI REND="italic">i</HI>on of an heresye.</P>
<P>The VII<SUP>te</SUP> is of mervelous and fferfull deth of an holy man, callid Euseby, and how s. Jerom aperid to him and comfortid him in <MILESTONE N="25"/> the our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of his deth.</P>
<P>The VIII<SUP>te</SUP> is how the said III men that were areysid, told of the paynys of hell and of purgatory.</P>
<P>The IX<SUP>te</SUP> is of the dying of the same III men and how s. Jerom helpid them in thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> dying. <MILESTONE N="30"/></P>
<P>The X<SUP>te</SUP> is how the soulis of the same men after thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> dethe stode tofor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the dome, and howe s. Jerom led them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to the joyes of heuen, the paynys of purgatorye and of hell, and sithe bad them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> go ayeyne to thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> bodies.</P>
<P>The XI<SUP>te</SUP> is of two myraclis of seint Euseby that wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> do, or his <MILESTONE N="35"/> body wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> buryed.</P>
<P>The XII<SUP>te</SUP> is howe an heretik, callid Sabinian, was m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>velous be∣hedid, and a byshop, callid Silvan, deliu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>id from dethe by help of seint Jerom.</P>
<P>The XIII<SUP>te</SUP> how the fende apperid in the liknesse of the same <MILESTONE N="40"/> byshop Syluan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and slaunderid him m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>velously, and how Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> helpid hym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI></P>
<P>The XIIII<SUP>te</SUP> how seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> savid two hethen men, that come to vysite hym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thevis and from dethe.</P>
<P>The XV. how s. Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> savid too yong men<HI REND="italic">e</HI> from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> dethe that <MILESTONE N="45"/> come from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Rome to vysytt hym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI></P>
<P><PB N="331" REF="39"/>
The XVI. is how an abbey of Nunnys was dist<HI REND="italic">ro</HI>yid for symony and for couetyse, and how s. Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> saued one of those Nunnys that was not gylty in that synne, when all other wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> kyllid be vengeaunce,</P>
<P>The XVII. is how III heretikes wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ue(lou)sly punyshid for <MILESTONE N="5"/> offence ayeynys s. Jerome.</P>
<P>The XVIII<SUP>te</SUP> is how s. Jerom deliuerid a man out of preson<HI REND="italic">e</HI> fro one lond to anoþ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> on one nyght.</P>
<P>The XIX. is how our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lady praysith s. Jerom as is writt in the reuelaciounys of s. Brigithe.— <MILESTONE N="10"/></P>
<TRAILER>Explicit capitula.</TRAILER>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>(I.) This in the lyff of seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> as hit is take of legenda aurea. Capitulum primum.</HEAD>
<P>SEnt Jerome come of noble kynne. And in his childhode he was sent to Rome to lerne, and ther he lernyd grew, latyn and ebrew. ‖ <MILESTONE N="15"/> And on a tyme, as he writith him-selffe to the holy mayde Eustace: whan he studied besely nyght and day in bokis of poetis and of philosofres, bycause thay sauour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> him bett<HI REND="italic">er</HI> than bokis of holy scriptur<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> hit happennyd that about mydlent he was smyttyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> with a soddeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and a fferuent ffeu<HI REND="italic">er,</HI> in so muche that all his body was <MILESTONE N="20"/> dede and cold vnto the hert. And whan his frendis wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> besy to dispose for his buriyng, sodenly he <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">ho.</HI></NOTE> was ravishid tofore the dome of god: and ther was he askid what man he was; and he answerid that he was a crystynman. ‖ Than said the iuge: 'thou saist not sothe; for thou art an hethen man, and not a crystyn man. ffor <MILESTONE N="25"/> wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thy tresour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> is, ther is thine hert: ‖ and thy hert is mor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> worldly bokis than apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> holy writt'. Seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> couthe not answer<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> but anon cryed and said: 'haue m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>cy apon me, lord!' and thay that stode be-syde, prayed that he myght haue foryef∣nesse, for he was but yong. ‖ And than seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> swore tofore <MILESTONE N="30"/> the iuge, almyghti god, and said: 'lord, yf y haue eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> ony seculer or worldly bokis to rede apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> theym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> herafter, than forsake thou me for a crysten man!' And by this othe he was let goo. Anone he levyd ayeyne and found him-selffe al bewepte, and his body sore and full of wondis of the betingis that he suffred toffore the <MILESTONE N="35"/> iuge. ‖ And from thennys forthe he studied and red as besely apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> holy bokis as he had do toffore apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> worldly bokis. Than he made himselffe a monke, and þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> he lyvid so holye, chastising his body w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> the lust þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI>of and w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>standing the desyris therof and of the world, that he causid other that were relygeouse to be the <MILESTONE N="40"/> bett<HI REND="italic">er</HI> for his ensampill. ‖ Whan he was XXXIX yer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of age, he was made a cardenall prest in the chirche of Rome. ‖ And after the pope was dede, all ffolke cryed and sayd that Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> was worthy to be pope. But for-asmuche as he had vsyd to blame the ffleshly∣nesse of mysgou<HI REND="italic">er</HI>nyd clerkis and religeouse peple, thay w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> gret <MILESTONE N="45"/>
<PB N="332" REF="40"/>
indignac<HI REND="italic">i</HI>on lay in wayte to do hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> repreve. And on a nyght, whan seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> shuld ryse to matennys, as he was wont to, he did apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> a wommannys cloþ<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and so went in to the chirche, wenyng hit had bene his owne: which his enmyse had layd by his beddis syde, to make folke wene that he had a womman<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in his <MILESTONE N="5"/> chamber, and so to scorne hym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> ‖ And whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he sawe that malice, he fledde thens, and come vnto Costantyne-noble. And ther he comende w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> the byshop of holy scryptur<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and sithe went into desert, and ther he suffred grete penau<HI REND="italic">n</HI>ce and dissease IIII yer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to-gedyr. Wherof he writith vnto the holy mayd Eustace and sayth: <MILESTONE N="10"/> 'Whan y was in desert in that gret wildernesse, wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> is a ffoule horryble dwellyng place, all to-brent w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> the sonne, me thought y was amongis the delic<HI REND="italic">is</HI> of Rome. All my body was defformyd and cladde in sakke, and my skynne made blak like a man of Ynd<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>y day weping, euery day wayling; and whan sleping come <MILESTONE N="15"/> apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> me, vnnethe y wold suffre my dry bonys to rest apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the bare erthe. Of mete ne drink y speke not, whan thay that bene seek vse but cold watyr and hit semyth glotony to ete any thing. Sothe, y was ffelow of scorpyonnys and of wild beestis. And yet in this cold body and in my dede fleshe y ffelt brennyng and ste∣ring <MILESTONE N="20"/> of vnclennes. And therfor, sithe thay fele sucche temptac<HI REND="italic">i</HI>onis that so dispise ther bodies and ffyhttyht only with thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thoughtis, what suffryth tho men or wommen that lyven in delit<HI REND="italic">is?</HI> Sothely as the apostell sayth that þay lyve in body but thay bene dede in soule. ‖ But our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord is my witnesse, that after many wepingis ffull <MILESTONE N="25"/> often-tyme me semyd that I was amongis the company of angelis'. ‖ After he had lyvid thus in desert IIII yer<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> he went ayeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> vnto Bethelem, and there offrid him-selffe as a wyse beest to abyde by the crybbe of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord. And th<HI REND="italic">er</HI> <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">that</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">ther.</HI></NOTE> gaderyd many disciplis and foundid a Monastorye and lyvid vnder the rule of the apostelis. <MILESTONE N="30"/> And lv yer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and a halff he travellid about translac<HI REND="italic">i</HI>on of holy writt, and to his ende he lyvid a virgyn<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> | Also he wrote the lyvis of holy ffathers in a boke that is callid Vitas patrum. He was also so wyse, that, what man had askid hym any questione, he shuld anone w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>out tariing yeff hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> a resonable answer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and sufficiant. <MILESTONE N="35"/> And when þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> had yet <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">bene</HI> fehlt oder <HI REND="italic">þ</HI>er st. <HI REND="italic">þei.</HI></NOTE> (bene) neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> no s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>teyne s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vyse in holy chirche, but eue<HI REND="italic">r</HI>y body song and redde what he wold: | the emp<HI REND="italic">er</HI>∣our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> prayed the pope that he wold ordeyne sum wyse man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to set diu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>se s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vice. And then the pope knew weell that seint Jerom was p<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>ffitt and moest exellent in latyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> tong, grewe and ebrewe, <MILESTONE N="40"/> and in all wysdom<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> he comitid to him the office. | And seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> then devydid the sawter in to noct<HI REND="italic">ur</HI>nys, and assynyd to eche day in the weke a propir nocturne, and ordeynyd that Gloria patri shuld be said at eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>y end of euery psalme; he ordeynyd also pystolis and gospellis for all the yer<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and other thingis that longyn to <MILESTONE N="45"/>
<PB N="333" REF="41"/>
devyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vice: and sent them from Bethelem vnto the pope. Whiche he and all his cardynallis reseyuyd and apprevid and auctoriȝed for eu<HI REND="italic">er.</HI> Then with abstynence and labour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he wex so wery and ffebill, that, when he lay apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> his bedde, he myht not aryse but as he pullid up him selffe with a rope tyed apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> a wall, for <MILESTONE N="5"/> to go do the s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vice that longid to be do in the monastorye. After this he made himselffe a grave in the mouthe of the cave wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord lay whan he was bor<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And ther, after he had lyvid ffour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> scor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> yer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and XVIII and VI monethis, he dyed and was buryed the yer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord CCC and XVIII. <MILESTONE N="10"/></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>(II.) Off the lyff and passing of this holy doctour seint Jerom seint Austyne wrytith vnto Ciryll, byshop of Jherusalem, in this wyse. Capit. II.</HEAD>
<P>O thow worshipffull preest Cirill, trowist thou that scilence is to be kepte from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the praysing of þe holy preest Jerom, that was <MILESTONE N="15"/> moest gloriouse s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vaund of crysten<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffeithe and a cornerstone of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> moder, holy chirche, in whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hit is in man<HI REND="italic">er</HI> gou<HI REND="italic">er</HI>nyd and made sur<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and now a shynyng sterr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in heuenly blisse? Or ellis thou dredist that y shuld speke of hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> as a lysping child, or as a man with foule lippis? ‖ But for hevennys tellith the glory of god, and <MILESTONE N="20"/> all that god made prayse him in his dedis, why shuld a resonable creatur<HI REND="italic">e</HI> be still from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> praysing, while all vnresonable creaturis are not still? Therfor other y shall speke or be still; yf y be still, y shalbe bode speke w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> stonys. Forsothe y shall speke, and not be still, to prayse the hyghe and worthy Jerom<HI REND="italic">e;</HI> ffor thoughe y <MILESTONE N="25"/> be an vnworthy and insufficient prayser, yet y shall not cease of his praysing. Therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> tung and our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hond be made sur<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and the tung mot not cleve to the palate. For, serteynly, this man is grete, right holy, mervelouse, and to be dred, aboue all that be about us. Grete he is in holynesse of his right excellent lyff, grete <MILESTONE N="30"/> in depnesse of his vnspekable wysdom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and in quantite of his right grete joye; mervelouse is he in vnwont myraclis; and to be dred, for the grete power gheuyn hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of god. But how grete this gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> is in holynesse of his lyf, howe shuld oo tung make knowing, whan vnnethe all tungis of all that bene on lyve <MILESTONE N="35"/> in erthe may suffice to tell his excellence? Be hit leffull therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to call another Samuel, another Hely, another John<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Baptist, dwelling in desert and made ly <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">ly</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">lene.</HI></NOTE> her <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">hes.</HI></NOTE> bodies w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> sharpnesse of mete and of clothing; but gloriouse Jerom was not of ies lyving: whiche is an hermyt<HI REND="italic">e</HI> dwelling IIII yer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in deserte, had no ffelow but wild beestis <MILESTONE N="40"/> and scorpyonnys, and ffourty yer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to-gedr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> dranke wyne ne syder, but fled thaym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> so muche, that vnnethe he wold her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thaym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> namyd; he ete no mete that come nere the ffyr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> but only twyes in the wittest(!) nede of his sekenesse; nexte his fleshe he weryd a sakke of her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and hillid him above with a clothe moest vile; ‖ he <MILESTONE N="45"/>
<PB N="334" REF="42"/>
knew neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> other bedde but the erthe; onys on the day only after euensong-tyme he ete ffruyte or levis of herbis or rotis, and after, yeving hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to p<HI REND="italic">ra</HI>yr, he woke till two houris w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>in nyght; and than he slepte apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the ground till mydnyht; and than anone he rose and till day he entendid to redingis and to holy scripturis. <MILESTONE N="5"/> He wepte for right small veniall synnys so bitterly, that men myght haue wend he had slayn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> a man<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Eche day thries he bete his ffleshe with so harde betingis, that ryvers of blode flowid from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> his body. He eschewid as a tempest to speke any ydell word; idell was he neu<HI REND="italic">er,</HI> but alway ocupied in holy wrytyngis and reding<HI REND="italic">is</HI> <MILESTONE N="10"/> or techingis of other. What shall y say mor<HI REND="italic">e?</HI> yf y shuld speke the lyvis of all sayntis, I wene y shuld ffynde no more holy than he. But for we namyd Samuell tofor<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> we may shewe clerely that he was Samuell: ffor fro his mothers tetis he was clepid to studye of lecture <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">lectury.</HI></NOTE> and sett s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vice of holy scripture; so that in the light <MILESTONE N="15"/> of his cher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> albeflowid with godly wysdom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> we se the lightis of bothe testamentis, and in strengthe of his arme a grete p<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>ty of heretikis is disp<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>lid <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">L. <HI REND="italic">disparplid</HI> od. <HI REND="italic">dispersid?</HI></NOTE>; he is the glorie of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> vertu, translating the old lawe and the newe from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the langage of ebrew in to latyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and in to grew, bothe to abyde for eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> vnto all that com<HI REND="italic">e</HI> aftyr; <MILESTONE N="20"/> declaring many p<HI REND="italic">re</HI>uyteis and dowtes, and araying the ordre of dyuyne s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vice. ‖ He edefyed nye all the chirche, so that he apperid gretly in depnesse of vnspekable wysdom<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> He couthe all liberall s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vice so p<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>fytly that all men say noon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> apperithe like hym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and as y lernyd my-selffe by experyence of other pistelis of holy writt <MILESTONE N="25"/> that he sent vnto me, I ffynd neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> none like vnto hym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> for he couthe the langage and letters of Ebrew, Grew, and Caldy, P<HI REND="italic">er</HI>se, Mede, Arabi and ny of all nac<HI REND="italic">i</HI>onis, as thoughe he had be bor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and norishid amongis them<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Here what shall y say mor<HI REND="italic">e?</HI> Neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> man couthe nor knew in kynd that that Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> couthe. | But, worshipfull <MILESTONE N="30"/> ffader, wene thou nott that y say these thingis wenyng that thou knew nott the lyf and vertuouse of Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> but by me, while thou thy-selffe were his felowe a long tyme. But y call god to witnesse, that for the holynesse of so vnspekable a man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> y may not be still, thoughe y wold; for merveylis and myraclis knowleche his holy∣nesse, <MILESTONE N="35"/> | and also the selffe heuennys, in whiche he is grete and of mor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> blisse than many of the sayntis that ar<HI REND="italic">e</HI> theryn<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> No man doute that he hathe one of the gretest and hyghest siteis among the mansyonnys of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>-lasting ffadir; ‖ ffor, while eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>y man is rewardid ther after his lyf and meritis, and he was of moest <MILESTONE N="40"/> p<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>ffit lyf: hit shewith that he is one of the grettest and highest citeȝeynnys of heuenly Jherusalem. Whiche that shull more sykerly and playnly be bylievid of us: tofor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> all men that our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> age hathe mynde of, he apperid moest m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>uelouse in vnwont tokennys and vnnum<HI REND="italic">er</HI>able miraclis. Of whiche the worshipfull man Eusebye de∣clared <MILESTONE N="45"/> som<HI REND="italic">m</HI>e vnto me by his letteris. But of other wondris that be
<PB N="335" REF="43"/>
do ther eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>y day m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>velously, as y her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> by contynuall relacion, I pray the, right dere ffader, that, whan thou mayst haue leyser<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> thou woldest gadre as many of thaym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> as thou may, and send them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> vnto me, that am<HI REND="italic">e</HI> so desyrouse to her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of so worthi dedis and so p<HI REND="italic">ro</HI>ffitable. e. c. <MILESTONE N="5"/></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>Howe seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the same our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that he dyed apperid to seint Austyn. Capit. III.</HEAD>
<P>That the meretis of moest holy Jerom be not hidde, I shall tell that byfell me thoroughe goddis grace the same day of his passing. For the same day and hour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that holy Jerom did of the cote of <MILESTONE N="10"/> ffilthe and vnclennesse and was cladde w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> the clothing of joye and vndedlynesse: while y was in my sell, thinking besely what glory and myrthe was in tho blissid soulis that Joyed w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> Cryst, desyring to make therof a shorte tretis, as y was prayed; y toke penne and ynke, to write a pistell þerof vnto moest holy Jerom, <MILESTONE N="15"/> that he shuld write ayeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> vnto me what he ffelith in (t)his <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">his.</HI></NOTE> mat<HI REND="italic">er—</HI>ffor y knewe wele þat in so hard a question<HI REND="italic">e</HI> y myght not be lernyd so evydently as of him of no man alyve. And whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> y beganne to write the begynnyng of my lett<HI REND="italic">er:</HI> | sodenly and vnspek∣able light, with a mervelouse swetnesse of swete smell, entirid <MILESTONE N="20"/> into my cell, at complyne-tyme. And whan y see hitt, y was so gretly astonyed, that y lost all my strengthe bothe of hert and of body. ‖ I wyst not yett that the marvelouse hond of god had en∣haunsyd his s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vaunt Jerom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> making his marvaylis to knowe to muche peple; I wist not that god of his wont mercys had dissoluyd <MILESTONE N="25"/> his trew s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vant Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> corrupcion of body, and arayed him so hye a cete in heuen<HI REND="italic">e.—</HI>But ffor myne yghen<HI REND="italic">e</HI> had neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> see sucche a lyght, my smelling had neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> ffelt sucche a sauour<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> y was gretly astonyed at so vnharde merveylis. ‖ And while y thouht in my-selffe what hit myght be, anone þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> sownyd a voyce out of <MILESTONE N="30"/> the light, saying these wordis: 'Austyn, Austyn, what sekist thou? Trowest thou that all the see shalbe put in a littell vessell? or wenyst thou to close all erthe in a littill ffyste? or to lett the firmament from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> contynuell meving? or to lett the se from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> his wont cours? That mannys yghe myght neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> se, shall thine se, or thine ere her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that <MILESTONE N="35"/> neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> mannys herd? wenyst thou that thou mow vndirstond that neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> mannys herd? wenyst thou that thou mow vndirstond that neu<HI REND="italic">e</HI>r mannys hert vndirstode neyther myght thinke, that shalbe the end of an endles thing? That may not be mesur<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">mesure</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">mesurid.</HI></NOTE>, how shall hit be mesurid? Rather shall all the erthe be hold in a littill ffyst, rather shall all þe see be sparryd in a littill put, rather shall the <MILESTONE N="40"/> see sease ebbing and fflowing, than thou shuldest vnderstond the leest p<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>te or porcion<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of Joyes and blisse that blessid soulis haue in heuen withouten end—but yf thou wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> tawht by experience and tastyng of the same blisse as y am<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> traveyle thou not to do thingis that bene inpossible, till the ende of thy lyf be <MILESTONE N="45"/>
<PB N="336" REF="44"/>
co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>me; seche thou not her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> tho thingis that may not be knowe but of them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that bene in blisse! ‖ But rather traveyle thou to do sucche s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vice and dedis that thou may be in posession<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">in</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">of.</HI></NOTE> sucche thingis ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> as thou desyrest to knowe her<HI REND="italic">e</HI>! ffor thay that onys entir thiddir, go neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> out ayeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI>'. ‖ Than I all astonyed for drede <MILESTONE N="5"/> and w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> strengthe of hert toke to me a littill boldnesse and sayd: 'Who art thou that drowpest so swete wordis in to my throte?' 'I am, he said, Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> preest, to whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thou hast begonne to write a pistell. I am his soule that this same our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> is in Bethelem levyng þe byrden<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of fleshe, am Joynyd vnto Crist and felaw with all cum∣pany <MILESTONE N="10"/> of heuen, cladde in light and arayed with the stole of vn∣dedly blysse, go to the eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>lasting kingdom of heven. ‖ And from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hennys forthe y abide no lassing of Joye, but mornyng <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">but mornyng,</HI> derselbe ausdruck in cap. 8: <HI REND="italic">mornyng-moryng, in∣creasing?</HI></NOTE> whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> I shalbe Joynyd ayeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to the body that shalbe gloreffied, and the glorye that y haue now alone I shall haue than with the body, in <MILESTONE N="15"/> the day of resurreccion<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> all mankynd shall aryse and our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> bodies shalbe Joynyd from corrupcion<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and we shalbe ravishid up in to the ayr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> to mete with Cryst, and so we shalbe alway with our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord'. ‖ Than I, Austyn, not cessing to wepe, answerid and said: 'O thou worthiest of men, wold god I myght be worthi to <MILESTONE N="20"/> be thy ffoet-man! But haue mynd on thy seruant, thoughe y be moest vnworthye, whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thou lovist <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">lovist</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">lovidist.</HI></NOTE> in the worlde w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> so grete affeccion<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of charite! By thy prayer y may be clensid of synne; by thy gou<HI REND="italic">er</HI>naunce y may go w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>out stombling in the right way of vertu; be thy besy deffence y may contynually be deffendid <MILESTONE N="25"/> from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> myn enmyse, and be thy holy leding y may co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>me to the hauen of helthe. And now like hit the to answer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> me to sum thingis that y shall aske of the!' Than said the soule: 'Aske what thou wolt, knowing that y shall answer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to all thy wyll.' ‖ Than I sayd: 'I wold witt yf the soulis that be in hevyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> may will any <MILESTONE N="30"/> thing that thay may not gett'. The soule answerid: 'Austyn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> know thou o þing: that the soulis in that heuenly blisse ar<HI REND="italic">e</HI> made so sur<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and stabill, that ther is no will in heui<HI REND="italic">n</HI> but goddis will, ffor thay may will no thing but that god will. Therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thay may gitt what that thay will; and what thay will, god will and fulffillith hit. <MILESTONE N="35"/> None of us is defrawdid of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> desyris ayeynyst our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> will; ffor none of us desirith any thing but god; and for we haue god alway, as we will, our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> desyris is alway fulffillid; ffor we abyde p<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>ffetly in god, and he in vs'. O fadir Cirill, hit wer to long to write in þis short pistell all thingis that that gloriouse soule answerid and <MILESTONE N="40"/> made know vnto me. But y hope w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> goddis helpe after fewe yeris to cum to Bethelem, to visitt his holy reliques, and than to declar<HI REND="italic">e</HI> mor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> openly that y herd and haue writt. Yf y shuld speke withe the tungis of all men, y myght in no wyse worthyly expresse
<PB N="337" REF="45"/>
how sotelly, how ope<HI REND="italic">n</HI>ly and how m<HI REND="italic">e</HI>ruelously that <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">soule</HI> fehlt im ms.</NOTE> (soule) expressid vnto me the vnite of the Trenyte and Trynite of the vnite, and the generacion<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of the sonne of the ffader, and the goyng forthe of the holy goest from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the ffader and the sonne, and the Je(r)archies and ordres of angelis, of blissid spiritis and her mynystracion and <MILESTONE N="5"/> blissis, Joyis of holy soulis, and other thing<HI REND="italic">is</HI> p<HI REND="italic">ro</HI>fitable and herd <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">herd</HI> = <HI REND="italic">hard.</HI></NOTE> to mannys vndirstonding. And after this the light vanyshid away; but the swete sauour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> abode many dayes after. Howe m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>uelouse is therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> this man<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> doyng so many m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>veylis and shewyng to men so vnwont wondres! Therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> cry we, and Joy we and <MILESTONE N="10"/> yef we glory vnto his praysing! And we are not sufficient to prayse him: ffor he is enterid into the house of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> (lord) <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">lord</HI> fehlt im ms.</NOTE>, bright and moest feyr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>out doute he hathe an eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>lasting sete among the hyghe mansionnys of blisse.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>How ffowr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> men had a visyon off seint Jerom in the oure of his <MILESTONE N="15"/> dethe. Capit. quartum.</HEAD>
<P>But ffor-thy that trouthe shuld be declarid by mo witnesse than be oon, I confferme more playnly the trouthe of this thing. A worthy man, callid Severe, exellent in wysdom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and cunnyng, with thre other men, being the same day and our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of the passing of seint <MILESTONE N="20"/> Jerom in the Cite of Turon, see a vysyon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> like vnto myn; of whiche the same Severe witnessith vnto me, for that the highe Joye of Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> shuld not be hidde to the worlde, leest thay that haue delyte to folowe the steppis of his holynesse, yf thay knewe not that he hathe so grete a reward, thay myght wex wery and cesse <MILESTONE N="25"/> from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the way of holynesse. Godde wold that thay shuld see and knowe how many and worthy rewardis of holynesse he hathe yeff vnto him, that thay shuld the more sikerly drawe after steppis of his vertu—ffor the hope of rewarde lessithe the strengthe of labour<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> The day of seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> passing, at complyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI>-tyme, the said Severe <MILESTONE N="30"/> was in his own<HI REND="italic">e</HI> house, and thre other goed men w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> him, of whiche too wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> monkis of seint Martyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI>s monastorye, entending to holy redingis. Sodenly thai <NOTE N="4" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">that</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">thai.</HI></NOTE> herd in heuen, in erthe and in the ayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> innum<HI REND="italic">er</HI>able voycis of moest swete songis, vnherd, vnspekable, and the sound of organys, symphanys and of instrumentis of all <MILESTONE N="35"/> musyke: with the whiche, as than semyd, heuen<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and erthe and all thing sownyd on eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>y syde; so that with swetnesse of that melody theyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> soulis wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in poynt to go out of her bodies. And thus astonyed, thay lokid up in to heuen: and see all the ayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and all that is about the firmament shyne with light brighter than<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the <MILESTONE N="40"/> sonne, out of whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> come the swetnesse of all swete odour<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And than thay prayid god that thay myght witt why all this was. Than ther come a voyse out of heuen and sayd: 'Lat no m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ueyle mene howe <NOTE N="5" PLACE="foot">L. <HI REND="italic">yowe</HI> = <HI REND="italic">you?</HI></NOTE>, nor think hit no m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>velous, thoughe ye see and here sucche
<PB N="338" REF="46"/>
thingis, ffor this day king of kingis and lord of lordis, Crist Jh<HI REND="italic">esu</HI> comythe ffeestifully ayeynyst the soule of gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in Bethelem going out of this wicked world, to lede him to the king∣dom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of heven<HI REND="italic">e;</HI> so more excellently and highe toffor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> other, as he shynyd tofore other in this world by m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ytis of more highe and <MILESTONE N="5"/> holy lyving. This day the orderis of all angelis, Joying and singing with sucche voycis as ye her<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> comyng with thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord; this day all compaynis of patriarkis and prophetis, this day all holy martyris, this day all confessoris, and this day the gloriouse and moest highe virgyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Mary, moder of god, with all her holy virgenys aboute her, <MILESTONE N="10"/> and the soulis of all that bene in blisse, comyth Joyfully and ffesti∣fully ayeynyst thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> contre-man<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> citeȝeyn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and eyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of heuen w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> them<HI REND="italic">e.</HI>' These thingis said, the voyse was still. But the light, odour<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and song abode an our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> affter, and so seasid. By this thingis, ffadir, is hit shewid, that he is of the hyest Ceteceȝns <MILESTONE N="15"/> of heuenly Jherusalem; and no-man dout but that, as his will is more ner<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to goddis will, so he may gitt ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> what he will, rather than other.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>Howe seint John<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Baptyst and seynt Jerom apperid vnto seynt Austyn in a vysyon. Cap. V. <MILESTONE N="20"/></HEAD>
<P>No-man thinke that I am so bold to say that seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> is bett<HI REND="italic">er</HI> than seint John<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Baptist—ffor as our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> savyour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> berith witnesse: none is more than he; nor, that Jerom is in the blisse of heuen to∣for<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Petir and Paule and other apostelis, that war<HI REND="italic">e</HI> chosyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and hallowid of Cryst him-selffe. ‖ Ȝett, thou reson<HI REND="italic">e</HI> forbede to <MILESTONE N="25"/> say that Jerome shuld haue more glorie in heuen<HI REND="italic">e</HI> than thay: y se no reason<HI REND="italic">e</HI> why hit shuld (not) <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">not</HI> fehlt im ms.</NOTE> be lefull to say that Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> is even in blisse w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> hem, while he was not discord∣ing from hem in holynesse. And sith god is not acceptour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of parsonys, but he dissernith <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">disservith</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">dissernith.</HI></NOTE> the meritis of eche p<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>sone— <MILESTONE N="30"/> he yevithe to eche as thay disserve—: ȝyf hit seme that <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">that þat.</HI></NOTE> Jerom shuld haue lasse Joye than John<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Baptist and other apostolis, ȝett the meryt<HI REND="italic">is</HI> of his holynesse, the grevis of his labou<HI REND="italic">re,</HI> the bokis of his writingis, the translacion of bothe the lawis, the ordinaunce of dyvyne servise, the fruytis and profitt of goednesse <MILESTONE N="35"/> that he did not only to all that be now but also to hem<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that be to comme, seme to p<HI REND="italic">re</HI>ue that Jerom is evyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to hem<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in blisse. ‖ But leest that y make a scornyng to sum man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that wold deme that for carnall affeccionis, wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI>thorough a man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> may lightely err<HI REND="italic">e</HI> from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> trouthe, or fro <NOTE N="4" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">fro</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">for.</HI></NOTE> vnkunnyng of my∣selffe <MILESTONE N="40"/> I lykennyd glorio<HI REND="italic">us</HI> Jerom to seint John<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Baptist or other apostelis: y take god to witnesse that I shall tell a thing that y lernyd neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> of man but by reuelacion of almyghti god, that honour<HI REND="italic">e</HI>the and magnefieth this chosynne. The ffourthe nyght
<PB N="339" REF="47"/>
after his passing, whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> y thoughte desyrously apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the praysing of moest blissid Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and began to write a pistyll therof to the: aboute midnyght, whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> slepe come apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> me, ther byffell me a wondirfull vicion. There come to me a grete multitude of angelis, and amonges them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> two men incomp<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>able brighter than<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the <MILESTONE N="5"/> sonne, so like that ther semyd no dyfference, saff the tone bar<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thre crownys of gold sett full of p<HI REND="italic">re</HI>ciouse stonys on his hede, and the other but two. Bothe thay war<HI REND="italic">e</HI> cladde w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> mantellis moest white and ffeyr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> all with gold and preciouse stonys. Thay wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> so ffayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that no-man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> myght emagyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hitt. Thay bothe come ner<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <MILESTONE N="10"/> vnto me and stode still in scilence. Than<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he that had thre crownys, sayd vnto me these wordis: 'Austyn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> thou thinkest what of trouthe thou shuldest say of Jerom, and after long thinking thou wost neu<HI REND="italic">er.</HI> Therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> we be come bothe vnto the, to tell the his blisse. Sothely, this is my ffellaw Jerom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thou seest, the whicche <MILESTONE N="15"/> is evyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to me in all wyse in glory, as he was even<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to (me) <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">me</HI> fehlt im ms.</NOTE> in lyving; that y may, he may; that y will, he will; and as y se god, so he sethe god, knowith god, and vndirstondith god, in whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> is all blesfulnesse of all sayntis, nor no saynt hathe more or lesse blisse than<HI REND="italic">e</HI> another, but in asmuche as one hathe more cler<HI REND="italic">e</HI> con∣templacion <MILESTONE N="20"/> and sight than other of the fayrnesse of god. That crowne that y bere mor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> than he, is the aureall of martirdom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> by whiche y endid my bodely lyff: ‖ ffor, thou Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffor the tra∣vellis and disseasis and other grevouse thingis whicche he suffred Joyfully for Cryst, and so beyng a verray mart<HI REND="italic">er,</HI> hathe not lost <MILESTONE N="25"/> the reward of martirdom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> ȝit, ffor he endid not his lyf by the swerd, he hathe not the aureall that is yevyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in tokenyng of mar∣tirdom<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> The too other crownys that bothe he and y haue, are th<HI REND="italic">e</HI> aureallis that are dew only to a virgyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and doctours, by whiche thay ar<HI REND="italic">e</HI> knowen<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffrom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> other'. Than answerid I and said: 'Who <MILESTONE N="30"/> art thou, my lord?' He sayd: 'I am<HI REND="italic">e</HI> John<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Baptyst, that am<HI REND="italic">e</HI> come down<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to teche the of the glorye of Jerom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> that thou tell hit to other peple. For knowe that the worship that is done to any saynt, is do to all sayntis—ffor ther is none envye, as is in the world, where eche man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> sechith rather to be abouen than<HI REND="italic">e</HI> vnder; not so <MILESTONE N="35"/> in heuen, but ther eche soule is as gladde of others Joye and blisse, as he had hit him-selffe. Wherfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the Joye of eche is the Joye of all, and þe Joy of all is the Joy of eche'. Whan these thinggis wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> sayd, that blissid cumpany yede ther way. And y woke of that swete slepe and ffelt in me so grete feruour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and brennyng of love <MILESTONE N="40"/> and charite, that y felt neuyr so muche afor<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thense forthe was ther neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> none appetite in me in <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">in</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">of.</HI></NOTE> envye or of pride as was toffor<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> God is my witnesse that ther is so muche feruour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of charite in me, that y Joy mor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of an others goed than<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of myne; I desyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> mor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to be vndir all than abouen any. I say not this for <MILESTONE N="45"/>
<PB N="340" REF="48"/>
to gitt me vayn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> praysing, but for no man shuld wene that these wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> vayn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> dremys, wherby we ar<HI REND="italic">e</HI> oft scornyd, but a trewe vysyon<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> by the whicche we ar<HI REND="italic">e</HI> otherwhile taught of god. Prayse we ther∣ffor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> god in his seynt, prayse we therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> moest holy Jerom, that did gret thing<HI REND="italic">is</HI> in his lyff and hathe reseyuyd grete thingis in his <MILESTONE N="5"/> dethe. Men ought not to be slewffull <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">slewfull</HI> von <HI REND="italic">slewe; desidiosus.</HI></NOTE> to prayse him, whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> god hathe magneffied; ne wene no-man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to do wrong to seint John<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and to the apostellis, evenyng Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> vnto them<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> for thay wold gladly, yf thay myght, ȝeve him of thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> glorie. Therfor thou that worshippest seint John<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and the apostelis, worship also seint <MILESTONE N="10"/> Jerom, ffor he is evyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> vnto thaym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in all thinggis. Sykerly therfor<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>outen doute, knowlege we w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> devocion that Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> is euen vnto John<HI REND="italic">e;</HI> ffor yf we say that he is lasse than John<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> we do derogacion vnto him and John<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> This tretis of the praysing of Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> y send vnto the, fader Cirell, praying the that thou scorne <MILESTONE N="15"/> not my littyll witt, but that thou rede this praysingis that y haue writtyn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> of charite; iff all tung<HI REND="italic">is</HI> of all men shuld prayse him, thay wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> not sufficient. Worshipfull ffader, haue mynd on me synner, whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thou stondist in that place wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the body of Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lieth; and comend me vnto him with thi prayers—ffor no-man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> doute but, <MILESTONE N="20"/> what eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> desyrithe in hevene, he may gitt hitt, ffor he may in no wyse be defrawdid of his desyr<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Fare weell, ffader, and pray for me!</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="6" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>(III) Here endith the pistyll of seint Austyn vnto Cirill, and begynnyth the pistyll of the same Cirill vnto seint Austyn of the myracle <MILESTONE N="25"/> of seynt Jerom. Cap. VI.</HEAD>
<P>To the worshipffull man<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> worthiest of byshoppis, Austyn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> by∣shopp of Ypon<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> Cyryll, byshop of Jherusalem, lowest of all prestis, sending greting, and to ffollowe his steppis whose holynesse ceasith nott to shyne in erthe, that is to say of gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> whose mynde <MILESTONE N="30"/> is had in eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>lasting blisse; and how worthy he is thou wotest weell thy-selffe, for thou vsest right mucche his speking and doc∣trine. But y to speke of him, sithe y am<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in all wyse wikkid and vnworthi, y hold hit to mucche boldnesse. But ȝitt, ffor thi charite compellith me to write to the sum of the mervelouse myraclis that <MILESTONE N="35"/> god lyst to do by him in our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> dayes, to shewe him gloriouse to the world and to all ffolke: trusting in thi prayers I take hit on hond and shortly y shall tell a fewe of many. And ffyrst y will begynne at an holy man, Euseby, disciple of <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">of the.</HI></NOTE> Jerom<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Affter the dethe of moeste gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ther rose an heresy among<HI REND="italic">is</HI> <MILESTONE N="40"/> the Grekis whicche come vnto us that be of Latyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> tung. Whicche heresy laborid to preve by wickyd resonnys that all savid soulis shuld not come to the sighte and knowlege of god, in which is all blysse, till the day of dome, whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thay shulbe Joynyd ayeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to the body; and also that dampnyd soulis shuld haue no payne till <MILESTONE N="45"/> that day. The reson was this: ffor like as the soule w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> the body
<PB N="341" REF="49"/>
had done weell or evill, so w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> the body hit shuld resayve mede or payn<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Thay said also that ther was no place of purgatorye, wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> soulis that had not do full penaunce ffor thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> synnys shuld be purgid. And this wikked seete encresid; we wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Im ms. ist <HI REND="italic">alway</HI> durchstr. und <HI REND="italic">we were</HI> überschrieben.</NOTE> so sory, that us yrkid to lyve any leng<HI REND="italic">er.</HI> Than y gaderid to-giddre <MILESTONE N="5"/> all our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> byshoppis and enioyned them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> fasting &amp; prayers, that the power<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of god shuld not suffre his faythe so to be trowbillid. A, m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>velouse and in happis not se tofor<HI REND="italic">e</HI>! <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Im ms. scheint <HI REND="italic">thing</HI> oder <HI REND="italic">mercy</HI> zu fehlen.</NOTE> Thre dayes of ffasting and prayers fulffillid, gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> appering <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">part.</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">verb. fin.</HI></NOTE> on<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the nyght ffolowing to his dere sunne Eusebye toforsaid in his prayers and <MILESTONE N="10"/> w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> benynge speche comfortid him and said: 'Drede the nott of this wikkid secte! ffor that shall sone haue an ende'. Than<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Euseby lokid on<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hym<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> and he shone w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> so mucche bryghtnesse, that no mannys yghen myght loke apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> him. But weping for Joye, Euseby myght vnnethe speke; but as he myght, he cryed and said: <MILESTONE N="15"/> 'Thou art my ffader Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI>' And often<HI REND="italic">e</HI> rehersing this wordis, he said: 'ffader, why forsakest thou me? why dispisist thou my cumpanye? sertayn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> y shall hold the and not leve the, nor thu shalt not go without thy sunne, whom thou lovest so mucche'. Gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> answerid: 'My swete su<HI REND="italic">n,</HI> he sayd, I shall not forsake the nor <MILESTONE N="20"/> leve the be <NOTE N="4" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">be</HI> wol zu tilgen.</NOTE> vncomfortid: ffor the XX day after thou shalt folow me and be with me in Joye w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>outen ende. But say to Syrill and to his bretheryn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> that thay all and all clerkis that be men<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of trew crysten<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffaythe, and also all that bene of the other secte, cu<HI REND="italic">m</HI> to morow to-gedr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to the crybbe of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord, wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> my body lieth; <MILESTONE N="25"/> and make thou the bodies of thre men<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that are this nyght dede in the citee, to be brought vnto the place wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> my bonys is buried; and thou shall lay apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> them the sakke that y vsid to wer<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> and anone thay shall aryse and groundly distroye this heresye'. Than gloriouse Jerom bad him far<HI REND="italic">e</HI> well and apperid no lenger. On the <MILESTONE N="30"/> morow worshipfull Euseby come vnto me that was than<HI REND="italic">e</HI> at Bethelem, and told me all that he had sene. And I, doyng thonking to god and to gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> did bring the thre ded bodies to us all gaderid to-gydder in that place wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> sauyour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> was bor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of the clene virgyn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> also lieth the body buried of gloriouse <MILESTONE N="35"/> Jerom<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> O meruelouse m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>cy of god vnto man! In howe many wyse canne he helpe thaym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that trustith in hyme! In howe many worshippis canne he enhaunse his servant<HI REND="italic">is</HI>! In this tyme men of evell desyrith to scorne men of right believe; but bethe glad, men of right ffaythe, and praysith god in voyse ioying, ffor ye haue resayvid <MILESTONE N="40"/> mercy in hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> inmyddis of his tempill! The worshipfull man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Euseby come vnto the bodies of eche of the thre dede men, and, kneling on his kneis and holding up his handis vnto heuen, he prayed, all men hering, and said: 'God, to whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> no thing is vnposs∣ible, no thing grevouse, that þ<HI REND="italic">ou</HI> doest grete m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>veylis alone, and <MILESTONE N="45"/>
<PB N="342" REF="50"/>
dispisist none that hopith in the: send to us vertu of thy grace and strengthe, and her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the prayers of thy servantis; and that the ffaythe that thou haest ȝeve me to abyde vndeffylid, and that er∣rour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of the trouthe may apper<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> by meritis and prayers of thy gloriouse lovid Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> bring ayeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in to the bodies the soulis that <MILESTONE N="5"/> thou hast made to go oute therof!' After that prayer he toke the sakke that Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> vsid, and touchid the dede bodies therw<HI REND="italic">ith:</HI> and anone thay opennyd thar<HI REND="italic">e</HI> yghenne and shewid all tokennys of lyff verreyly, and rose, and began<HI REND="italic">e</HI> with a cler<HI REND="italic">e</HI> voyse to tell openly all the Joyes of holy soulis and the paynys of synners in purgatorye <MILESTONE N="10"/> and in hell. ffor, as thay told me afftirward, seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> led thaym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> into paradise, p<HI REND="italic">ur</HI>gatorye, and to hell, that thay shuld tell to all ffolke that was tho ther<HI REND="italic">e;</HI> and after bad thaym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to go to thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> bodies ayeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and do penaunce ffor thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> synnys that thay had do: ffor the same day and our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that worshipfull Euseby shuld <MILESTONE N="15"/> dye, thay shuld passe also, and yf thay did well, thay shuld haue Joye w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> him. And so hit ffell, as y shall tell afterward. These thingis done, grete <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">of grete.</HI></NOTE> multitude of peple bothe of the true ffaythe and of this secte seing <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">saying.</HI></NOTE> openly thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> errour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and the grete meritis of Jerom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> yaffe grete praysingis vnto god, that forsakith not thaym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <MILESTONE N="20"/> that tristith in him. ‖ Thus der<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Austyn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> we be tawght not to drede the p<HI REND="italic">ur</HI>suers of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffeythe, and to knowe howe redey our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> pite∣full lorde is to helpe all tho that call apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> him in tyme of tribula∣c<HI REND="italic">i</HI>on, and how myghty gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> is to p<HI REND="italic">ro</HI>mote the praye(r)s of thaym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that in clene hert prayeth and trustith vnto hym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> <MILESTONE N="25"/></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="7" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>Of the mervelouse dethe of the said Euseby, and how seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> apperid vnto hym in the our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of his passing. Capi∣tulum VII.</HEAD>
<P>Whan tyme come that worshipfull Euseby knewe that he shuld passe, as he was enformyd by the same vicion<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of seint Jerom: <MILESTONE N="30"/> the thirde day tofor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he was myghtely smytten<HI REND="italic">e</HI> w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> a ffeu<HI REND="italic">er.</HI> And than he made his bretheryn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lay him nakid on the erthe and lay vpon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> him the sakk that gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> vsid to wer<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Than kist he his bretheryn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and, benyngly comforting them<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> he styrid them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to abyde stabely in the holy lyving; he ordeynyd by ensampill of <MILESTONE N="35"/> gloriouse Jerom that he shuld be buried nakid without the chirche in which the body of seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lieth. After this he strenghid hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI>-selffe w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> the comyng and p<HI REND="italic">er</HI>cepcion of the holy body of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord Jh<HI REND="italic">esu</HI> Crist and comendid him-selffe to god and to seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And so he lay thre dayes w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>out bodely sight or speche, <MILESTONE N="40"/> his bretheryn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> stonding about hym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> contynually saying and reding theyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> sawter, the passion<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord and other holy thingis. But for sothe hit is hard and fferefull to all that lyvith in this world, this that y shall now tell the. The day that he shuld dye, two owris tofor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the passing of that blissid soule, worshipffull <MILESTONE N="45"/> Euseby byganne to behaue him so ferefully, that the monkis, that
<PB N="343" REF="51"/>
stode about him, ffell downe to the erthe for ffer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> as men out of her mynde; ffor otherwhile he turnyd vp his yghene and wrong his hondis to-gydder, and w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> a fferefull fface and a hard voyse he satt up and cryed 'I shall not, I shall not; thou liest, thow lyest'. Aftir this he ffell down<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ayeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to the erthe and, festenyng his <MILESTONE N="5"/> fface to the ground as muche as he myghte, he cryed 'helpe me, helpe me, bretheryn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> that y perishe nott!' And thay hering this, weping and tremling for fer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> askid hym<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> 'ffader, howe is it with yowe?' He said: 'Se ye not the multitude of ffendis that wold ouer∣come me?' Thay askid hym<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> 'What wold thay that thou shuldest <MILESTONE N="10"/> do, whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thou saydest: y shall nott, I shall not?' He answerid: 'Thay labour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">L. <HI REND="italic">laboured, traveyled.</HI></NOTE> and traveyle me that y shuld blasfeme <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">blasfemei.</HI></NOTE> the name of god, and therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> y cryed that y shuld not do hitt'. And thay askid hym<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> 'Whi, ffader, haddest thou thy fface to the ground?' He answerid: 'that y shuld not see thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> loking<HI REND="italic">is,</HI> whiche be so <MILESTONE N="15"/> ffoule and orrible, that all the paynys in the worlde are right nought in co<HI REND="italic">m</HI>p<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>ison<HI REND="italic">e</HI> therof'. Amonge these wordis he bygan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to doo and to crye ageyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> as he did tofor<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and so come vnto the last ende of his lyff. His brether that stode aboute hym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> for fer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and sorow fell down as dede, not witting that thay myght do. ‖ But god <MILESTONE N="20"/> that is gloriouse in his seyntis, me<HI REND="italic">r</HI>velouse in mageste, benyng and m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>cifull to theym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that drede hym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> ‖ he fforsaketh not his s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>van∣tis in tyme of nede: ffor, whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> worshipffull Euseby com vnto the last ende, gloriouse Jerom apperid and benyngly comfortid hym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And whan he come, all that Innum<HI REND="italic">er</HI>able cumpanye of ffendis for <MILESTONE N="25"/> fer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> vanyshid away as smoke, as many of the monkis berith witnesse that by the <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">thy</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">the.</HI></NOTE> dispensac<HI REND="italic">i</HI>on of god se hit. But all that stode aboute, herd how Euseby said: 'ffrom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> whennys comyst thou, fader? why hast thou taryed so long? I pray the, forsake not thy sunne'. ‖ And sodeynly all thay herd howe Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> answerid <MILESTONE N="30"/> ageyn<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> 'Abyde, sunne, be not afferd! for y shall not forsake the, whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> y luffe so mucche'. Than after a litell while worshipffull Euseby dyed. And the same our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> dyed the thre men that wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> areysid, and, y hope, went with Euseby vnto eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>lasting Joye; ffor all tho XX dayes after thay wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> areysid, thay gaffe thaym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to so <MILESTONE N="35"/> muche penaunce, that w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>out doute thay wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> worthy to be re∣wardid withe endelesse blysse. &amp; cet.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="8" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>Howe the said thre men aftyr thay were areysyd, told Cyrill of the paynys of purgatorye and of hell. Capitulum octavum.</HEAD>
<P>I trowe, hit be not to kepe sylence of tho thingis that y lernyd <MILESTONE N="40"/> of tho thre men in tho dayes that thay lyvid, after thay wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> arerid—ffor all that tyme y was contynually with sum of thaym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> ffrom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> mydmorow vnto euensong—tyme, desyring to know the preveteis of
<PB N="344" REF="52"/>
that lyf that we abyde after this short and passing lyff. But thoughe y lernyd many thingis of hem<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> yet now because of shortnesse y may tell but a ffewe. On a tyme, whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hit happenyd me to go to one of them<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> y found him sor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> weping; and after y ffelt that he wold take no comfort by my wordis, I askid him the cause of his <MILESTONE N="5"/> weping. And whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> y had askid him often, he answerid nott. At the last compellid by my long instaunce he answerid and said: 'Iff thou knewe two <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">L. <HI REND="italic">tho?</HI></NOTE> thingis that y had experience of the last day, ther shuld evir be yn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the cause of weping'. Than said I: '(I) <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">I</HI> fehlt im ms.</NOTE> prey the, tell what thou seest'. ‖ 'O what paynis and turmentis are <MILESTONE N="10"/> ordeynid not only to the <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">be</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">the.</HI></NOTE> dampnyd soulis, but also to thaym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that be in purgatorye!' Than said I: 'Of thingis that I knowe nott, y canne yeff no certeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> sentence; but y trowe that thay be not like to þe paynys and disseasis that wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> suffred her<HI REND="italic">e'.</HI> ‖ He answerid: 'yf all the paynys, tormentis and affliccionse <NOTE N="4" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">afflicciouse.</HI></NOTE> that myght be <MILESTONE N="15"/> thoughte in this world, wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> likennyd to the leest payne that is ther<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> all that semyth payne and torment shuld be solace and com∣fort; ffor, yf any man alyve knewe the paynys by exp<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ience, he shuld rather chese to be turmentid vnto the ende of the worlde w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>outen remedye w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> all the paynys to-gedr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that all men suf∣fred <MILESTONE N="20"/> ffrom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Adam till this tyme, than be turmentid oo day in hell or in p<HI REND="italic">ur</HI>gatorie w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> the leest payne that is ther<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI>for<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> yf thou aske me the cause of so gret weping: hit is the drede of paynys that ar<HI REND="italic">e</HI> wyslye ghevyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> vnto synners; ffor y knowe weell that y haue synnyd aȝeynyst god—and I doute nott but that <MILESTONE N="25"/> he is rightwisse. And therfore m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>veyle not thoughe y sorow! But rather thou oughtest to be gretly m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>veylid why men that wote weell thay shall dye at the last by experience of other, lyvithe her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in so gret siknesse and thinketh not how so ascape so grete paynys'. ‖ Att these wordis y was touchid w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> an Inward sorowe, <MILESTONE N="30"/> so that y myght vnnethe speke. And y said: 'Alas what is this that y her<HI REND="italic">e</HI>! But y pray the, tell me what difference is ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> by∣twene the paynys of hell and of purgatorye'. He said: 'Ther is no difference in gretnesse of payne; but in oo wyse ther may be difference: ffor the paynys of hell abydith none ende, but mornyng <MILESTONE N="35"/> at the day of dome, whan the bodies shalbe turmentid w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> the soulis; and the paynys of purgatorye hathe an<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ende, ffor, after thay haue done thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> penaunce ther, thay shalbe take vnto end∣lesse Joyes'. I askid: 'Be thay that ar<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in purgatorye, turmentid all like or ellis dyuersly?' 'Su<HI REND="italic">m</HI> mor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> greuously than<HI REND="italic">e</HI> summe, after <MILESTONE N="40"/> the quantite of thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> synnys. For in hevyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> all blissid soulis be∣hold the fayrnesse of god wherin is all blisse; and, thoughe eche of them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> haue as muche Joye as thay can, will or thinke, yet thay be not all even like in Joye: ffor su<HI REND="italic">m</HI> haue more, and sum haue lasse, after the dedis that thay haue done. And yf thou merveyle <MILESTONE N="45"/>
<PB N="345" REF="53"/>
that ther may be dyuerse Joyes in sayntis, while the only cause is god himselffe, in whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> may be none diu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>site: the answer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> is this: that the knowing, beholding and vndirstonding of god is all the reward of Joye of sayntis; and þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI>for<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> yf all soulis in blisse see and knowe god as he is, yet sum<HI REND="italic">m</HI>e se and vndirstond (him) <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">him</HI> fehlt im ms.</NOTE> lesse <MILESTONE N="5"/> than other and haue lesse Joye, and sum se and vndirstond him more clerely and so haue mor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Joye. So may hit be said of the paynys of dampnyd soulis: ffor all dampnyd soulis be in one place of paynys, yet thay ar<HI REND="italic">e</HI> turmentid w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> dyuerse paynys after the qualite of theyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> synnys. For ther is so muche defference bytwixste <MILESTONE N="10"/> the paynys of crysten<HI REND="italic">e</HI> men and of hethen men, that the paynys of hethen<HI REND="italic">e</HI> men in regarde of the paynys that false crysten<HI REND="italic">e</HI> men<HI REND="italic">e</HI> suffryse, be as hit wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> no paynys, ‖ and yet thay be vnspekable and may not be thoughte of any that lyffyth in erthe—and so hit is worthy, for crysten men ressayvith the grace of god in vayne <MILESTONE N="15"/> that will not be amendid of thar<HI REND="italic">e</HI> synnys, while that thay lyve, holy scriptur<HI REND="italic">e</HI> crying apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> contynually and thay sett not therby'. ‖ I said: 'Hit is right horrible that thou sayst, and wold god hit wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> besely ffestennyd in the myndis of all that bene a lyve, that thay myght cease from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> synne for dred of payn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> yf thay <MILESTONE N="20"/> wold not for luffe of Joye'.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="9" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>Off the dying of these thre men areryd, and how seint Jerom <HI REND="italic">com</HI>fortid them in thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> passing. Cap. IX.</HEAD>
<P>'Nowe I pray the, tell me how hit was with the, the last day whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thy soule partid from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thy body.' ‖ He said: 'Whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <MILESTONE N="25"/> of my deth come, ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> come so grete a multitude of evill spiritis and ffendis in to the place ther y lay, that ffor multitude thay myght nought be nombryd. The liknesse of them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> was sucche, that ther may be thoughte no thing mor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> paynffull ne more horryble—ffor any man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> alyve wold rather put him-selffe to bryn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in the <MILESTONE N="30"/> hottest flawmys of ffyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> than<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he wold se the formys of them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in twynkeling of an yghe. These fendis come vnto me and brought vnto my mynde all the synnys that eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> y did, styring me to trust no lengher on the mercy of god, ffor y myght not ascape the with∣standing of thaym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> all the strengthe of my spirit <MILESTONE N="35"/> ffaylid, so that y was ner<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in the poynt to assent vnto them<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> gloriouse Gerom come with a grete cumpany of angelis about hym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> seuen tymys bryghter than the sonne, and comfortid me. And tho he se tho wickid spirit<HI REND="italic">is,</HI> how hard thay troubillid me, he was gretly styrid ayeyngst them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and said w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> a ferdfull voyse: 'ye spirit<HI REND="italic">is</HI> of <MILESTONE N="40"/> wickednesse and of all cursidnesse, why come ye hidder? wyst ye wele that thus he shuld be socouryd be my helpingis. ‖ Levith hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> anone and w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>drawe your<HI REND="italic">e</HI> wickidnesse fro him, as fast and as ferr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> as the eest is from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the west'. And anone withe these wordis all that cumpanye of cursid spiritis was afferde, and w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> grete <MILESTONE N="45"/> crying<HI REND="italic">is</HI> and wayling<HI REND="italic">is</HI> thay went out of the plase ther y lay. And
<PB N="346" REF="54"/>
than gloriouse Jerom bad sum of the angelis that þay shuld nought go ffrom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> me, but abyde till he come ayeyn<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> the tother angelis in hast he went his way. And whan he was gone, the angelis þat wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> left to kepe me, beganne to comforte me, behot∣yng me ffayr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> yf y wold suffre and abyde with strong peyne of <MILESTONE N="5"/> hert. ‖ And amonges these wordis of comforte an our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> past, and than<HI REND="italic">e</HI> come seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ayeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and, stonding in the durr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> he said: 'comyth in haest!' Than sodenly my soule lefte the body so grevously and so bitterly, that no mannys mynde myght vndir∣stond what angwishis and disseasis thay wer<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> but yf he had lernyd <MILESTONE N="10"/> them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> by experienc<HI REND="italic">is,</HI> as y haue: ffor yf the vndirstonding of all shuld esteme all angwyshis and sorow that thay cowthe, thay shuld acount them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> at noughte in regarde of dep<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>ting of the soule ffrom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the body'. But while he told me these and many mo thing<HI REND="italic">is</HI> ffull hard and dredfull to all men, whiche y write not her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> for lengthe, <MILESTONE N="15"/> the day began to ende and therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he must lyffe to tell tho thingis that byffell him after his dethe, whiche y desyrid moest to her<HI REND="italic">e.</HI></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="10" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>How these thre men stode toffore the dome of god, and how seint Jerom led them to see the Joyes of heuen, the paynys of purgatory and of hell, and than he bad them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> go ageyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to <MILESTONE N="20"/> thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> bodies. Cap. X.</HEAD>
<P>The nexste day ffolowing y callid þe other<HI REND="italic">e</HI> too with him, to witt howe thay acordid, that by witnesse of them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> all thre y myght be taught the mor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> surly. And whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> one bygan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to tell me that that other had told me toffore, y said: 'Thoughe these thingis be p<HI REND="italic">ro</HI>f∣fitable <MILESTONE N="25"/> and hit is not vayn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to speke them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> often<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> ȝet leving this that y haue herd, y pray you, tellith fforthe what byffell you after your<HI REND="italic">e</HI> dep<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>ting from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> your<HI REND="italic">e</HI> bodies'. Than said he that spake vnto me to <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">L. <HI REND="italic">the</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">to?</HI></NOTE> morowe toffor<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> 'What askis thou, Cirill? hit is not possible to be told, for spirituall thingis may not be comprehendid <MILESTONE N="30"/> of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> wittis. Thou knowest that thou haest a soule, and ȝitt what a soule is thou knowest not; and thou knowist that god is, but what he is thou maste not knowe in this lyffe, but by experience of example; so hit is of angelis and of all vnbodely thingis. For while ther is many thingis know in kynd that for febilnesse of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <MILESTONE N="35"/> littell vndirstonding we may not vndirstonde: howe shuld we vndir∣stond heuenly thingis and sp<HI REND="italic">iritu</HI>all that be in all wyse straunge fro the knowing of kynde?' Than y said: 'It is <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">Is it.</HI></NOTE> as thou sayst. But y pray the, tell thou me than so as these men<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that be her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> me shall ber<HI REND="italic">e</HI> witnesse, that had experience of the same thingis <MILESTONE N="40"/> as weell as thou'. He sayd: 'So shall y tell as y may. Whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> my soule was dyssolvid from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the body w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> so many angwishis and sorowis as y said toffor<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> sodenly and vnspekabli in twinkeling of an ygh<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hit was bore tofor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the presence of god demyng; but howe or of whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hit was borne I knowe not—and hit is m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vayle, <MILESTONE N="45"/>
<PB N="347" REF="55"/>
ffor now y am<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in the hevy body and than was the soule w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>out body or flesshe. Ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> tofor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the Juge was the soulis of many rightwis men, tremeling w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> vnspekable fferis what the Juge shuld doo. Alasse, why knowe not thay that be dedly, to whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> shalbe∣fall as than byfell us! certayn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> not the vnknowing therof, <MILESTONE N="5"/> thay shuld not synne so ofte as thay do! ffor we did no synne in all the tyme of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lyff that myght be hidde from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the Juge; but all that eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> we didde, was all clerely knowe to all that stode ther<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> as yf thay had be present, in so muche that the leest of all the thoughtis apperid ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> as hit was. Bethinke the, w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> howe <MILESTONE N="10"/> many and how grete fferis we wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> smytten<HI REND="italic">e</HI> with, at that tyme! | There stode many ffeendis bering witnesse of all the evillys that we had do, declaring the tyme and the place and the maner<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and we our<HI REND="italic">e</HI>-selffe myght not say nay to that that was putt apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> us; ffor eche of us knew weell that hit was trewe, and also the Juge <MILESTONE N="15"/> knewe all thingis and was moest rightfull. Alasse, alasse, what shall y say, what sentence abode we than<HI REND="italic">e</HI>! ffor mynde theron<HI REND="italic">e</HI> y quake yett and am<HI REND="italic">e</HI> afferid. Owr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> wickidnesse cryed after venge∣aunce vnto the Juge, and vnnethe apperid ther any goed, wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI>by we myght haue hope of mercy; and all that wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> cryed that <MILESTONE N="20"/> we wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> worthy to be in torment and payne. And whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffaylid nothing but oonly to yeffe the sentence ayeynyst us that is yeven ayeynyst synners: gloriouse Jerom, brighter than all sterris, with seint John<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Baptist and w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> seint Pet<HI REND="italic">er,</HI> prince of the apostellis, and w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> a grete multitude of angelis come vnto the trone of the <MILESTONE N="25"/> Juge and prayed that our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> sentence myght be taryed a while, and that we myght be gevyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> vnto him, ffor the reu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ence and deuocion<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that we hadde to him, and for nede to distroye the said heresye. And as he wold, so hit was grauntyd hym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Aftir this he with his blessid companye ledde vs with hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and declarid vnto us wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <MILESTONE N="30"/> all crystyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> soulis haue eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>lasting Joye that may not be spoke, that we shulde ber<HI REND="italic">e</HI> witnesse therof. And then he lad us to p<HI REND="italic">ur</HI>∣gatorye, and to hell, and not only he shewyd us what was ther<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> but he wold also that we shuld assay the paynys by experience. And whan this all was doo, that tyme the worshipfull Euseby <MILESTONE N="35"/> touchid our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> bodies w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> Jerommys sakke: the same gloriouse Jerom badde hem turne ayeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> bodyes, and that we shuld bere witnesse of all that we had see, and behoting that, yf we did dewe penaunce for our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> synnys, we shulde on the XX<SUP>ti</SUP> day after haue endlesse blisse w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> worshipfull Euseby, that shuld passe from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> this <MILESTONE N="40"/> worlde the same day and the same our<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And so were oure bodies Joynyd to our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> soulis ayeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI>'. O dere Austyn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> many fferfull thingis lernyd y of tho thre men<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> which, yf thay wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> impressid into mannys mynde, thay shuld vtterly rende away from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the love of all erthly thing<HI REND="italic">is</HI> and grete besynesse that is had <MILESTONE N="45"/> theraboute, that nowe make many a man to err<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> ‖ But for y abyde thy com<HI REND="italic">m</HI>yng, to vysitte the relyques of seint Jerom, as thy letteris make mynd, I leve of nowe and a while touche of
<PB N="348" REF="56"/>
the sepultur<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of worshipfull Euseby and sithe forthe speke of the myraclis of gloriouse Jerom.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="11" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>Off too myraclis that Euseby wrought, or his body wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> buryed. Cap. XI.</HEAD>
<P>Whan this holy man was dede, about mydnyght or mydmorow, <MILESTONE N="5"/> anone þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> shewid many myraclis to ber<HI REND="italic">e</HI> witnesse of the holynesse of his lyff. Of whicche y will tell twayn<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Ther was a man, a monke of the same abbay, that for waking and weping had lost his syght. And anone as he touchid the worshipffull body of Euseby, he had his sight ayeyn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> as tofor<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Another man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ther was that <MILESTONE N="10"/> had a ffende w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>in him and was out of his witt, and come and met with us, as we bare the body of holy Euseby: and anone he was deliu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>id and made hole. Thinke we inwardly how <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">how how.</HI></NOTE> this man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> was in his lyff, that myght do so grete myraclis so astely after his ende! Thinke we on his holynesse with grete drede! for, sithe he <MILESTONE N="15"/> that was so holy, had so p<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>ilouse a troubill and temptacion at his ende, howe shall we, synffull wrecchis, ascape that our<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and wote not howe sone we shall come therto? Than we buryed the bodye of holy Euseby w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> dewe worship, but nakid as his master was, by the chirche in which the holy body of gloriouse Jerom is buried; <MILESTONE N="20"/> and in the <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">L. <HI REND="italic">the same.</HI></NOTE> chirche the bodies were buried of the said thre men<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that died the same our<HI REND="italic">e.</HI></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="12" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>Howe an heretyke, callid Sabyan, was mervelously byhedid and ouircom<HI REND="italic">m</HI>e by the merytis of seint Jerom. Cap. XII.</HEAD>
<P>Ther was an heretik, callid Sabyny, and that said ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> was too <MILESTONE N="25"/> wyllis in Cryst, sum tyme discording, in so muche that he said Crist wold many thing<HI REND="italic">is</HI> that he myght not do. And w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> this heresy he did us so muche sorow, that y may not tell hit w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> any wordis; for he p<HI REND="italic">er</HI>u<HI REND="italic">er</HI>tid the ffolke that is comyttid vnto us, as a ravishing wolffe. And for he shuld maynteyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> his heresye the mor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> effectu∣ally, <MILESTONE N="30"/> he made a tretys therof and said that glorious Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> had made hitt, to make us gyff ffeythe therto. But y knewe that glori∣ouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> made a pistill ayeynyst the same errour<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> a litill tofor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he dyed. And þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI>for<HI REND="italic">e</HI> y clepe(d) <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">clepe.</HI></NOTE> the same heretike on a sunday with all his disciplis vnto the chirche in Jherusalem, for to dispute <MILESTONE N="35"/> and preve his errour<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Ther was gaderid to-geddir also all our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> byshoppis and many other trewe crysten<HI REND="italic">e</HI> men<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and so our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> disput∣acion durid from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> none till evyn<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And whan the same heretik laid agaynyst us the same tretis that he fadrid apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> gloriouse Jerom: ‖ Syluan, archebyshop of Naȝareth, myght not suffre so <MILESTONE N="40"/> muche wrong to be putt apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Jerom; ffor he lovid and worshippid seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> so muche affeccion and deuocion of hert, that at the begynnyng of any thing that he did he askid ffirst helpe of god and of gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e;</HI> and therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he was callid Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> nye of
<PB N="349" REF="57"/>
all ffolkis. He rose ayeynys this heretik and blamyd hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> sharply for the wikkednesse that he did. And whan thay had long strevyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and eche of them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> sayd agaynys other what thay myghte, att last thay accordid to-gydir thus: that, yf seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> shewid by the secund day at none that he had ffalsly made that tretys, the here∣tik<HI REND="italic">is</HI> <MILESTONE N="5"/> hede shuld be smyttyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of; | and ellis shuld Sylvanus, the archbyshop. And thus eche man went home. All that nyght we yaff us to prayer<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> asking helpe of god, þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> faylith none that trustith in hyme; but he is grete and right praysable, and ther is no numbr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of his wisdom<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> come on the nexste day, the <MILESTONE N="10"/> heretik with his disciplis come into the chirche and went about as a ramping lyon<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> seking to devour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the servantis of god. And all the peple of trewe ffaythe stode in the chirche, cleping the name of gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> But gloriouse Jerom ffarid as he had slepte and not toke kepe of thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> prayers. And I, all bewepte, stode <MILESTONE N="15"/> astonyed, and m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>veilid why gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> abode so long. And whan ther apperid no-thing of myracle, the heretik cruelly callid apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Syluan to do that he had hight. Than holy Sylvan went to the place wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he shuld be hedid, Joying as thoughe he hadde gone to a ffeest; and all byshoppis and other crysten<HI REND="italic">e</HI> men that <MILESTONE N="20"/> stode ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> weping, he comfortid and said: 'Joyeth w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> me, my der<HI REND="italic">e</HI> frendis, Joyeth and beth not hevy! ffor god levith not them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that hopith in hym<HI REND="italic">e'.</HI> Than he knelid downe and said: 'Moest holy Jerom, helpe, yf hit please the! and thoughe y be worthy muche more turment than this, yett, lesse <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">L. <HI REND="italic">leste?</HI></NOTE> falsnesse haue place, do thou <MILESTONE N="25"/> socour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to trouthe! ‖ And yf hit be not lefull that y be holpe, be m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>cyfull vnto me in the ou<HI REND="italic">re</HI> of my dethe, that y be not departid from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> endlesse blisse!' ‖ And than he hild fforthe his nekke and bad the turmentour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> smyte: and <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">he</HI> fehlt im ms.</NOTE> lyfte up his swerd on hye, desyring to smyte of the worshipffull byshoppis hede at o stroke: <MILESTONE N="30"/> than sodenly, all men seyng, come gloriouse Jerom and put up his hond and hilde still the swerde and bad Sylvan to ryse. And than he blamyd the heretyke, shewyng howe he had vntruly made þat tretise and vndirstond the scriptur<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and therfore he <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">he threting; he</HI> ist zu tilgen?</NOTE> threting hym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and vanyshid from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the sight of all the peaple. And anone as <MILESTONE N="35"/> gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> was go, the heretikes hede ffell apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the ground, smyttyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the bodye, as thoughe hit had be smyttyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> a swerd at a stroke. And whan all see this grete m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vayle sodendly, thay were astonnyed and thanked god, and the disciplis of the here∣tikis turnyd vnto the way of trouthe. ‖ Loo, how the trust that this <MILESTONE N="40"/> worshipfull byshop had vnto god and gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> was effectu∣ally, for he dred nought to dye ffor trouthe, yeffing ensampill to all cristen<HI REND="italic">e</HI> men—ffor he is no trew crysten<HI REND="italic">e</HI> man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that sparith to dye for trouthe; sithe Crist ȝaff his lyf for us to by us from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> all
<PB N="350" REF="58"/>
thraldome, we owe not to be afferde to yeff our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lyff for hym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> whan tyme is; for no-man may gitt the ground of blysse, but yf he ffyght lawfully therfor<HI REND="italic">e.</HI></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="13" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>Howe the ffeende apperid in liknesse of the said Sylvan byshop, slaunderid hym mervelously, and howe he was deliu<HI REND="italic">e</HI>rid by <MILESTONE N="5"/> seint Jerome. Cap. XIII.</HEAD>
<P>For y haue said sumwhat of Sylvan, y will say another thing of hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> as mervelous as the ffirst, wherof be as many witnesse as ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> bene ffolke dwelling in the citees of Naȝareth and of Bedlem, that sawe hitt with thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> yhen. The old s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>pent, the ffende, that <MILESTONE N="10"/> was for his pride cast <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">was cast; was</HI> doppelt.</NOTE> downe in to the depnesse of hell, hauyng envye at this worshipffull byshop Syluan, greuously he was sterid ageynyst him and gelfully <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">= <HI REND="italic">gilfully.</HI></NOTE> he travellid to slaundre hym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> that, as many as by ensampill of his holynesse had increasid in the wayes of holy conu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>sacion, so by his ffall thay myght be sterid to evill. <MILESTONE N="15"/> ‖ On a nyght he toke the liknesse of the said holy man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and apperid vnto a worshipffull and a grete woma<HI REND="italic">n,</HI> lying in her bedde, and visittid hir <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">him</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">hir.</HI></NOTE> to cum vnto her vnleafully, asking the consent of her body. Than the womman, not knowyng the man, was afferd and, seyng her-selffe alone in her chamber with a man, wist not <MILESTONE N="20"/> what for to do, but cryed loude and ofte, so þat withe her busye crying thay awoke þat were aslepe not only in the same house, but also her negborouys aboute. And all thay cum rennyng to the wom<HI REND="italic">m</HI>annys chambre and askid her what her aylid. And she, being sore afferd, told them<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> But in the mene tyme that gylefull serpent <MILESTONE N="25"/> hidde him vnder the bedde. And thay sought about long, to witt what man hit was, and at the last thay ffound him. And whan thay byhield him with many a candell light, thay went verrayly that hit had bene Sylvan, the archebishop: and than all thay stoed astonyed and in a man<HI REND="italic">er</HI> out of thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> wittis, not witting what to <MILESTONE N="30"/> say nor do, seing bothe his holynesse and that ffoule abhominable dede. At the last thay asked him whi he had do sucche wicked∣nesse. And he answerid: 'what diddy <NOTE N="4" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">diddy I. I</HI> ist zu tilgen?</NOTE> I agaynys this womman, thoughe she callid me to do this dede?' The womman hering, w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> weping answerid that he said vntrulye. Then he wylling to styre <MILESTONE N="35"/> men more agaynyst þe s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vaunt of god, to make them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to sclaundre hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the rather, he began to speke so ffoule and horryble wordis of vnclennesse, that noman myght suffre them for foulnesse, but w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> dispite and grete reprevis thay compellid him and made hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> go out of the house. And on the morow thay told about what was <MILESTONE N="40"/> ydo, &amp; cryed þ<HI REND="italic">at</HI> Syluan archebishop an ypocrite and worthy to be brent; in so muche that all Naȝareth was so sterid agaynys the byshop, that thay myght not her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> his name but yf thay cursid
<PB N="351" REF="59"/>
hym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> A m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>velous pacience of this man, a token of gret holynesse! Whan he herd all this slaundre and repreef, he mevid not onys his mouthe to speke any evill word, nor his hert was no-thing styrid to vnpaciens, but alway he thanked god and said: his synne had deservid hitt. Allas, Austyn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> what shall y say? not only y ffle <MILESTONE N="5"/> as muche as y may wrongis and reprevis, but ofte y am<HI REND="italic">e</HI> begylid w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> a ffewe wordis. I desyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the reward of heuen, vnto <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">vnto</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">and to</HI> oder <HI REND="italic">but to?</HI></NOTE> tra∣veyle þerfore I take no kepe; but yett y wott weell, ther may no∣man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> come ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> but by the way of traveyle and of affliccion and dissesis. And what shall y else deme, while I ffynde my lyff and <MILESTONE N="10"/> maners of holy men, but that y must be ffounden discording from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in my dethe? <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">L. <HI REND="italic">dede.</HI></NOTE> ‖ And in reward hit is full hevy and grevous to me to thinke on holy mennys lyffis and of myne; hit is m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>velous to here how men rede and speke of holy mennys dedis as y do, and will nothing do as thay didde. Thus y say to shewe myn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <MILESTONE N="15"/> own<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffollye. Y knowe weell that y haue often<HI REND="italic">e</HI> herd of the same Sylvannys mouthe that he thought him-selffe neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> so weell at ease as whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he sawe himselffe dispisyd and troden down<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of all ffolke. But this slaundre of hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> grewe so ffarr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> that hit went in to Alisaundr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and Cipr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and other londis and Citeis, so muche that <MILESTONE N="20"/> þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> durst noman come w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>-in his durr<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> M<HI REND="italic">er</HI>velous god, sytting above and seyng all folke, he suffrith his s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vantis to ffall in tri∣bulacion and disseasis for thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> bett<HI REND="italic">e</HI>r, but he faylith them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> not whan nede is. After a yer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> was past that the fende had vsid sucche malice ayeynys the servaunt of god, the holy byshop, the <MILESTONE N="25"/> same byshop lefte all other thingis and went prevely vnto the chirche wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the body of gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> is buried, as to an haven of refute. | And ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> at his tombe he sett him to pray; and after he had abydden<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> two ouris in his prayer, ther come a man into the churche of the spirite of malyce: and fynding the holy <MILESTONE N="30"/> man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> praying, he ranne to him as a dragonne and reprevid him, saying that he laborid contynually to styr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> womennys hert to vnleffull lustis. But the Innocent lambe, Sylvan, Joying of his owne dispite, answerid not. Than he w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> his right hond drow out his swerde that he bare by his syde, and lyfte hit up, to haue put hit <MILESTONE N="35"/> in-to Sylvannys throte. ‖ And whan the worshipfull byshop put ayeynyst hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> this word: help, gloriouse Jerom!: ‖ the man turnyd his swerd in-to his owne throte and so slowe hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI>-selffe. ‖ After that hit happenyd that another wickid man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> come into the chirche; and wenyng that þe holy byshop Sylvan had slay hym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> he toke <MILESTONE N="40"/> his swerd, to haue slayn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the byshop; and to tell shortely: he slowe him-selffe, as the other did toffor<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And vnnethe was he ffall to the ground, or other too men come yn<HI REND="italic">e</HI>-to the chirche: and seying this men ded, thay went the holy man had done hit; and therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> one of them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that was mor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> cruell, beganne to crye and callid him <MILESTONE N="45"/>
<PB N="352" REF="60"/>
theef and said: 'How long shall thy malice endur<HI REND="italic">e?</HI> Thou styrest wommen vnto foule will, and therto sleest men thus prevely. S<HI REND="italic">er</HI>∣tayn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> this day shalbe an ende of thy wickidnesse' and anone he ranne with his nakid swerd to haue slayn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And whan Sylvan had said this worde: helpe, gloriouse Jerom! this man<HI REND="italic">e</HI> slew him∣selffe, <MILESTONE N="5"/> as þe other too had do tofor<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> his owne hond. The tother man that come with hym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> seying this, was afferd, a ranne out of the durr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and cryed out and said: 'Comyth hidder, all ffolke, and se this wikkid Sylvan, that not onely diffoulith wommen, but also with his wichcrafte he sleeth men!' Then all <MILESTONE N="10"/> the peple of men and wommen come rennyng and crying that Sylvan the byshop was worthy to be brent. And whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> this come to myne eris, I went thidder, weping and full hevy. | And þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> y se how among cruell wolffis stode that meke lambe Joyfull and merye, as ȝyff he had bene in grete p<HI REND="italic">ro</HI>sp<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ite; no-thing he said ellis but: <MILESTONE N="15"/> 'y suffrid this rightwisly, for y haue synnyd ayeynist god'. All thay bett hym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> all thay pullid hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and led him vnto the torment was more grevous. ‖ But anone as he was ledde out at the chirche durr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> sodenly gloriouse Jerom was rysyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> up out of his place wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he lay, so bright, that nomannys yghen myght wele dur<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to <MILESTONE N="20"/> loke apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hym<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> and with his right honde toke Sylvan by the right hand, and w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> a-fferefull voyse he bad them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that hild hym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> leve of. ‖ Whiche voyce and visyon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> was of so grete pour<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> that all that wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> a-fferd and, all the strengthe of thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> bodies ffayling, thay ffell down<HI REND="italic">e</HI> apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the erthe as ded men<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> In <MILESTONE N="25"/> the mene tyme a woman, bounde bothe handis and ffeet, and ffull of the ffend, was brought vnto the chirche for helpe, by handis of many men<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And anone as þe womannys ffote touchid the chirche∣durr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> the feend bygan to crye fferfully by her mouthe and said: 'Mercy, mercy, glorious Jerom! for by the I am<HI REND="italic">e</HI> turmentid to-ffor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <MILESTONE N="30"/> my tyme'. ‖ Gloriouse Jerom said vnto hym<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> 'Thou wickid spiritt, go out of this s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vaunt of god and tell the wickidnesse that þ<HI REND="italic">ou</HI> hast done ayeynyst Sylvan<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> shewing thy-selffe in likenesse of Sylvan, so þat all men myght haue wend hit had ben Sylvan, the archbishop'. And he told all that he had doo ffor to slaundir the <MILESTONE N="35"/> servant of god. And sithe w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> grete crying the ffend vanyshid awaye. And gloriouse Jerom than not leving the right hond of his byshop said vnto hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> a softe voyse: 'What desyrist thou, my der<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Sylvan, that y shall do mor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> for the?' He answerid: 'My lord, he said, that thou leve me no leng<HI REND="italic">er'.</HI> Then said gloriouse <MILESTONE N="40"/> Jerom<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> 'That thou askis, hit shalbe do. Come therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> anone after me!' And thus said, he apperid no leng<HI REND="italic">er.</HI> But after the space of a short our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Sylvan the byshop paste vnto Cryst. All than the pepill was astonyed and mervaylid. Aftyr this the body of wor∣shipfull Sylvan, the archebishop, was borne vnto the chirch of Naȝa∣reth <MILESTONE N="45"/> withe dewe worshippe w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> the multitude of peple bothe of Naȝareth and of Bethelem<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in the chirche of Naȝareth we buried the body, as was semyng. But many wordis myght not
<PB N="353" REF="61"/>
expresse fully the wordis of this worshipfull byshop. But, for y haue mor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to say of seint Jerom, I leve of as nowe.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="14" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>How two hethen men that come to vysitt seint Jerom were mer∣velously dylu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>id from thevis and from dethe. Cap. XIIII.</HEAD>
<P>Tweyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> worthy hethen men, riche and goed men, and the man<HI REND="italic">er</HI> <MILESTONE N="5"/> hering of the myraclis of gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> come from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the Cite of Alysaundre withe muche richesse and fferuent deuocion<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> to vysitt the reliques of gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And goyng in thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> way hit happennyd them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to err<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> way into a grete wode, where thay sawe no steppis of men nor of horse. And therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thay <MILESTONE N="10"/> clepid apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the name of gloriouse Jerom and hole commyttid them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to his keping. In the same wode dwellid a prince of thevis, having vnder him more then V hundred, sending some o way and sum<HI REND="italic">m</HI>e another way to slee men and to bring ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> goedis vnto hym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> This prince seyng these two men<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> he clepid thre thevis and <MILESTONE N="15"/> bad them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> go sle them<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And whan thay had take thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> armur<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> nye at thaym<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thay see tofor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> but too, than thay sawe an Innumerable multitude, and one goyng tofor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> theym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> so bright, that none myght loke apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> him. Than the thevis wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> afferde and wyst nott what to doo, but turnyd ageyn<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And whan <MILESTONE N="20"/> thay wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffarr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> them<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> thay lokid ayeyn<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> and see but two, and than began to pursue theym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ageyn<HI REND="italic">e;</HI> but assone as thay come ner<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> thay sawe as thay did tofor<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Than wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thay more astonyed, and in all haste went to thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> prynce and told him. And he callid them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffolis, and clepid other XII thevis, goyng hy(m)-selffe w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> <MILESTONE N="25"/> thaym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And thay all the while thay wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> affarr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> thay see but too; and thay come ner<HI REND="italic">e:</HI> and thay sawe as meny as the other did tofor<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Than þay wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> afferde, and thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hertis trembelid, and all the strengthe of thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> bodies faylid for ffer<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And whan thay come ageyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to them<HI REND="italic">e</HI>-selffe, thai <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">that.</HI></NOTE> thought that thay wold suwe <MILESTONE N="30"/> aft<HI REND="italic">er</HI> theym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> to se prevely what shuld ffall. Whan evyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> com<HI REND="italic">m</HI>e apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> these pilgremys, thay wist not what to do ne wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to be loggid, and therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thay turnyd to the XII thevis to aske counsell of them<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> wenyng thay had bene way-ffaring men<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> as thay war<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> ‖ And whan<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thay turnyd to the thevis-ward, thay se but too, <MILESTONE N="35"/> and than<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thay wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> bold to mete w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> them<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And after that thay met, the thevis askid of whennys thay wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and whidder thay wold. Thay answerid and said: 'We be men of Alisau<HI REND="italic">n</HI>dr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> goyng to Be∣thelem, to visitt the reliques of gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e'.</HI> Thay askid what men wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thay that come with them<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> The tother merveylid <MILESTONE N="40"/> and said thay sawe none, sithe þay come into that wode, save them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and oþ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> thre. The prynce of thevis told hem all as hit was, praying them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to tell hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> what was the cause. Thay said: thay knew no cause, but yf hit wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> for thay comyttid thaym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to the keping of gloriouse Jerom. Than these thevis, sodenly enspirid <MILESTONE N="45"/>
<PB N="354" REF="62"/>
w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> the holy goest, fell downe at thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffete, asking them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> for∣yefnesse, and sithe led them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffelawis. At þe begynnyng of the nyghte thay come to the tother thevis abyding after them<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and told them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> as hit hadde beffall, praying them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to leve all thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> synnys and to go w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to visitte the gloriouse body <MILESTONE N="5"/> (of) Jerom. ‖ The tother thevis scornyd him <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">him = hem,</HI> wie 16, 41.</NOTE> and said: thay wold sle thaym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> yf evir thay spak any mor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> therof. And thay not ceassing therof, many of the thevis arose and drewe out thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> swerdis. But, thay calling after helpe of seint Jerom, thay myght nother lyft up thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> swordis nor put them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> up, tyll thay <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">day</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">thay.</HI></NOTE> whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <MILESTONE N="10"/> thay wold haue slayn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> had prayed to gloriouse Jerom for thayme. ‖ O vnspekable mercy of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> saviour<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> that in so many wisis bringgethe whom he will to knowlege of trouthe! ‖ Anone all the cumpany of thevis, seyng this, thonkid and praysid god and glori∣ouse Jerom, and made a vowe to visitt his reliques. Therfor<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> <MILESTONE N="15"/> whan morow come, mo then thre hundred thevis that wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that tyme left the wode and went w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> the said men<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of Alsaundr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> vnto the tombe of gloriouse Jerom, telling these wonders. ‖ Ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the hethen men wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> baptiȝed and, leving all the vanyte of the worlde, went in-to monastorye. ‖ And tho thevis also ȝeff them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to <MILESTONE N="20"/> holy lyving by the grace of god and by the meritis of gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e.</HI></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="15" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>Howe tweyne yong men by seynt Jerom wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> savid from dethe, that come from Rome to visytt him. Cap. XV.</HEAD>
<P>When two yong men goyng <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">were</HI> fehlt?</NOTE> ffro Rome toward Bethelem to visitt <MILESTONE N="25"/> the reliquys of gloriouse Jerome, hit happennyd thaym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to cum by a village XII myle from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Constantyn nobill. And to mile from that village, ore thay come therto, wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> too men slayn<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Wherfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> men of that towne gaderid to-gedir and beganne to seke aboute who hit shuld be that did that dede. And whan thay hadde all sought, <MILESTONE N="30"/> thay found none but onely two yong men<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that come fast bye. ‖ Whom thay toke, wenyng thay hadde slayne the tother men. Wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI>of the yong men wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> am<HI REND="italic">er</HI>veylid and swor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> as muche as thay myght that thay knewe not therof. But thay sett not ther bye thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> wordis, but ledde forthe tho yong men in all hast to <MILESTONE N="35"/> thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> village, and sithe sent them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to Constantyne noble w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> grete accusing. ‖ And ther w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> rygour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of grete turment thay wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> compellid to knowlege thaym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> gylty, wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thay wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> not gylty: and so thay were demyd to be hedid. Allas, what hert myght conteyne hitt from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> weping to so many vayling<HI REND="italic">is</HI> of Innocentis <MILESTONE N="40"/> whicche wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> arrayed bothe w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> yongthe and with ffayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI>nesse and with noble byrthe? For, weping and wayling and sighing contynu∣ally, thay said: 'Gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> is this thy rewarde that thou yevist to them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> þat serue the? is it this that we haue des<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vid
<PB N="355" REF="63"/>
with traveyle of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> way? Alas, thou Cite of Rome, thou knewe of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> birthe, we wend not thou shuldest haue bene so vnknowing of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ende'. ‖ Thus thay wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ledde to þe place wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thay shuld be hedid; ‖ mucche peple stonding ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and abyding. ‖ And ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thay knelyd downe and helde up his (!) <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">his</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">her, their</HI> verschr.</NOTE> hondis and said w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> a lowde <MILESTONE N="5"/> voyse: 'Gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> anker of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> helthe and haven of our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hope, bowe thine eris vnto our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> prayers at this tyme, so that, yf we did not this synne for whiche we be punyshid, we may ffele, of thy wont pite, the helpe of thy delyu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>aunce; and yf we be gylty, lat us be dede, as nede askith!' And whan thay sayd thus, <MILESTONE N="10"/> thay putt out theyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> nekkis to þe smyters, saying no-thing but: helpe, helpe, gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI>! ‖ What m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>veyle thoughe the mercyfull help<HI REND="italic">er</HI> Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> myght not absteyne him from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> shewyng of mercye to so many teris of them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that come vnto him, while the hertis of all þat stode aboute, ye of the said turmentours, wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> mevid vnto <MILESTONE N="15"/> compassion<HI REND="italic">e</HI>! Than thay lyft up thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> swerdis and smote on<HI REND="italic">e</HI> theyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> neckis: but thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> nekkis toke the stroke, as thoughe thay had bene of stone. And thay smote ayeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and ayeyn<HI REND="italic">e;</HI> but thay ffelt tham<HI REND="italic">e</HI> but as thay had be smytten<HI REND="italic">e</HI> w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> a strawe. Whereof ther rose a grete m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>veyle to all that stode aboute, and gret multi∣tude <MILESTONE N="20"/> come rennyng to see. At the last the Juge that demyd them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> come him-selffe and bad them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> smyte ageyn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> that he myght see. And thay smote, but thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> nekkis wold not be hurte. Than<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the Juge mervaylid gretly and wist not what hit myght be, but thoughe <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">thoughe</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">thoughte?</HI></NOTE> þat thay hadde vsid sum wiche-crafte. And therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he comaundid <MILESTONE N="25"/> that in all haste thay shuld be made nakid, and brenne them<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Thay made a grete ffyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> aboute theym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and put theryn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> oyle and picche, the rather to distroy the lyff. But he that deliu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>id them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> swerdis couthe also helpe theym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> crying contynually apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> in the ffyr<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> The ffyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> brent ffast and the flamys ascendid <MILESTONE N="30"/> up right highe; but the yong men<HI REND="italic">e</HI> by the helpe of gloriouse Jerom restid thaym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> as in a mery herber<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> At the last the Juge wold witt whedder hit be miracle or wichcraft: he bad thay shuld be hongid VIII dayes, and yf thay lyvid so, thay shuld goo whither thay wold. But the p<HI REND="italic">re</HI>sence of gloriouse Jerom ffaylid theym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> not: <MILESTONE N="35"/> for m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>velously he kepte them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> all tho dayes, holding up thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ffete w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> his hondis. On the VIII<SUP>te</SUP> day all the peple of the Cite and of townys come aboute, and the Juge him-selffe cam<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to the gallowis: and ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> openly thay sawe this gloriouse myracle. ‖ The kepers telling them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> what thay had sene. Than all m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>veylid and <MILESTONE N="40"/> praysid god and gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and did grete worship to the yong men<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and muche peple went from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Constantynoble vnto Bethelem to visitt the relik<HI REND="italic">is</HI> of gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And anone the yong men casting from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> all worldly vanyte enterid into the monastorye wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lyffyd, nyght and day entending <MILESTONE N="45"/> to prayer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and to penaunce and to holy lyffyng e. c.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="16" TYPE="chapter">
<PB N="356" REF="64"/>
<HEAD>Howe a monastorye of Nunnys was distroyed ffor couetise and for symonye. Cap. XVI.</HEAD>
<P>The myracle of these yong men tofor is <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">us</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">is.</HI></NOTE> cause of grete mervayle, Joy and deuocion. But this that ffollowith yevithe cause of grete drede, namely to religeouse peple. In a contrey, callid Thebayda, <MILESTONE N="5"/> was a monastorye of nunnys about two yer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ago, right fayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and worthy, wher-yn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> were abowt two hundred ladies, honest in religeon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and maners and in contynuall reclusion<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Nowe eu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>ichone lesseþ bothe thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> eris, that the tone lat not go out all that the toþ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> taketh in. ‖ ffor he that shall sayle in the depe see, haue he neu<HI REND="italic">er</HI> <MILESTONE N="10"/> so goed a shippe and hole; hit avaylith him not, yf an hole be lefte in the bottum<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> wat<HI REND="italic">er</HI> may cum yn and drown<HI REND="italic">e</HI> <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">drownd.</HI></NOTE> him. Why y say this, the mater of this storye shall shewe. For the said monastorye had many vertuous and holynesse of lyffyng, ‖ but hit kepte oo synne, of symonye, that causid hit to be stroyed. ffor by <MILESTONE N="15"/> þe instruccion of the ffend the nunnys had this ambicion: that, whan any shuld be resayvid anone amongest them<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> thay toke her not so muche for charite and mercy as thay didde for love of monney; ffor ther myght none entr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> to abyde in that abbay, but yf she brought a certayn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> sum<HI REND="italic">m</HI>e of monney with her. In this mon∣astory <MILESTONE N="20"/> was a nunne ffer in age, that had cast from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the love of all erthely thing and from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> her childhode entendid onely to god in prayer<HI REND="italic">s</HI> and ffasting<HI REND="italic">is.</HI> ‖ And gretly she abhorryd and hatid this vice that was amongis them<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> | To hir on a nyght, beyng in prayers, as she was wont, gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> apperid in gret light and bad <MILESTONE N="25"/> her goo on þe morow and tell the abbesse and to the toþ<HI REND="italic">er</HI> nunnys, that, but thay seasid of thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> syn, thay shuld ffele the sodeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> vengeaunce of god. And whan he was ago, she m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>velid gretly what he was that yaff her this charge. And all that nyght she abode waking. ‖ On the morowe she rang the chapitre bell, and, <MILESTONE N="30"/> whan thay wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> all gaderid, m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>veyling why thay wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> callid so hastely: this holy lady rose up among theym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and told theym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> what she had sene and herd. Ano<HI REND="italic">n</HI> all the other scornyd hir and said she was a ffole, and howe she myght in happis be dronken ovir nyght and dreme sucche thingis. But she thanking this re∣preeff, <MILESTONE N="35"/> deffendid hir withe the shild of pacience, and sorowing of thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> obstynacye, but Joying of her owne dispite, went vnto her wont prayers, beseching contynually that hit beffall not her susters, as she had herd. And X dayes she abyding in this prayer<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> on a nyght about mydnyght, gloriouse Jerom apperid to hir and bad her <MILESTONE N="40"/> go without drede and tell her susters as she had warnyd him to∣ffor<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Than she askid: 'Who art thou that biddis me do these thingis?' He said: 'I am<HI REND="italic">e</HI> Jerom'. And anon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> he was goo out of her sight. But she knowing thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> hardnesse, wist not what to do or sey; yet she thought she had lever<HI REND="italic">e</HI> be holde of them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> woed and <MILESTONE N="45"/> dronke than to do ageynyst the will of god. Therfor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> she did
<PB N="357" REF="65"/>
gadre her susters, as she did to-ffor<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> to haue told thaym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> what she see and herd. But as sone as thay see hir aryse: or she be∣ganne to speke, thay went out of the chapit<HI REND="italic">re</HI> w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> mowis and scornys. The third day at nyght after aboute mydnyght gloriouse Jerom with an vnspekable multitude of angelis apperid vnto the <MILESTONE N="5"/> lady beyng a slepe, and bad her aryse and go out of the monastorye, that she were not smyttyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> withe the soddeyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> sentence that shuld come apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> theym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> But whan she prayed w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> grete weping that thay myght be sparid: gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> bad her go in hast to the abbesse and to her susters and tell thaym<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> that, yf but thay didde <MILESTONE N="10"/> penaunce ffor thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> synnys that same nyght, thay shuld ffeele vengeance of god; and yf thay abode still obstynate, than she shuld go out and no lenger abyde in that monastorye. Than this nunne ffull of angwishe and hevynesse went in-to the chapitre and rong the bell hastely. Wherw<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> the abbesse awoke. And whan <MILESTONE N="15"/> she wist who hit was, she was wrothe and come to the chapit<HI REND="italic">re</HI> and blamyd her gretly and wold her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> no word of her saying, and said: but she lefte sucche thingis, she shuld no leng<HI REND="italic">er</HI> abyde in the place with hir<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> That lady answerid: 'Tary not to do as thou sayst! ffor y will no leng<HI REND="italic">er</HI> abide in this place. Glorio<HI REND="italic">us</HI> Jerom hathe <MILESTONE N="20"/> apperid vnto me and said that this monastorye shall anone be smytten with the wrathe of god'. Than the abesse wenyng that she had said this of madnesse, bad the kep<HI REND="italic">er</HI> of the gate dryve her out, and whan she had be a while, take her ynne ayeyn<HI REND="italic">e—</HI>hoping that þ<HI REND="italic">er</HI>by she wold haue ceasid of sucche dedis. But this <MILESTONE N="25"/> nunne was glad to goo, and ffull of sorowe and weping for the myschief comyng to þe place. O fferefull god, strong and myght∣full, and who shall w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>stond hym<HI REND="italic">e?</HI> Allasse why drede men him nott that p<HI REND="italic">ro</HI>uoke so muche his wrathe and may not ffle his hondis, but his grete dome must nedis take them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> at the last? Wrecchis be <MILESTONE N="30"/> afferd by this exampill her<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> thay that trust in herr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> richesse, what dome god sent from heuen apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> this monastorye turnyng away thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> fface fro him for luff of mony. Vnnethe was this nunne gone out of the durr<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> but sodenly anone all the monastorye ffell down<HI REND="italic">e</HI> on the grounde, sleyng all the nunnys, so that ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> abode <MILESTONE N="35"/> none alyve, but þis ladye into a monastory in a cuntre fast by and ther<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lyvid in grete holynesse. To this myracle y will Joyen<HI REND="italic">e</HI> another shewyng the fferefull domys of god, that the hard hertis of synners myght be turnyd in to softenesse of pennaunce.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="17" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>How thre heretykkis were mervelously punysshid for offence <MILESTONE N="49"/> ayeynyst seint Jerom. Cap. XVII.</HEAD>
<P>An heretik of the Grekis disputid openly apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> a sunday w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> a preest in the Cite. And whan the preest for diffence of his p<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>ty allegid an auctorite of seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> to distroy the reasonnys of the Greke: | the Greke w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> a bold voyse was not ashamyd to say that Jerom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> <MILESTONE N="45"/> light of all trowthe, lyed. And for he did suche a wickednesse with his speche, he spake nevir word after. Another heretik of þe Arryannys, whan one had brought an auctorite of seint Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI>
<PB N="358" REF="66"/>
ageynyst him in disputacion and the heretik hadde boldely said he lyed: anone he was smytten with the vengeaunce of god; ffor he hadde not ffully endid the word, but that he cryed all the day after w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI>out ceesing: 'Mercy, m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>cy, gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> ffor y am<HI REND="italic">e</HI> turmentid of the withe <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">whicche.</HI></NOTE> hard paynys!' and whan he had cryed thus <MILESTONE N="5"/> with <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot"><HI REND="italic">with</HI> ist zu tilgen.</NOTE> all the day as mucche as he myght, at complyne-tyme, all men seyng that wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ther<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> wrecchedly he dyed. Another heretik see in the chirche of Syon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> an ymage of gloriouse Jerom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and said: 'Wold god that y had hadde the in honde, while thou lyviddest, that y myght haue slayn the with my swerd!' and than he pullid <MILESTONE N="10"/> out his knyff and smote hit in the throte of the ymage. A, how grete is this Jerome doyng thus many m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>veylis! This heretik myght smyte his knyff in the ymagis throte, but he myght not gytt out his knyf agayn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the ymage, nor his honde from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the knyff, till hit was knowen<HI REND="italic">e</HI> openly. | But anone ther come blode <MILESTONE N="15"/> ffollowing out of þe wound, as of a lyving man<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Which seassid not yet in shewyng of the myracle. The same tyme that þis was do, the Juge of þe cuntre was in the chircheyerd. To whom glori∣ouse Jerom apperid w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> the knyff in his throte, asking of him to do vengeaunce for the offence, telling him how hit was. Þe Juge was <MILESTONE N="20"/> astonyed, and all þat wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ther<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> And goyng in to the chirche, þay se þe heretik stond w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> his knyff in the throte of the ymage. And also sone as thay see hit, thay myght take away his honde. Than thay toke him, and, for he did obstinatly in his evill saying: that he sorowid for no thing saeff for that he slow not Jerom by his <MILESTONE N="25"/> lyff, the multitude of peple withe stonys and stavis, swerdis and speris slowe hym<HI REND="italic">e.</HI></P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="18" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>Howe seynt Jerom delyuerid a man out off preson ffrom one lande to another in a nyghte. Cap. XVIII.</HEAD>
<P>Ihon<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> my neve, whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thou knowest arayed with all ffayrnesse, <MILESTONE N="30"/> whom y chese to me in stede of sun <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">sum.</HI></NOTE>, told the, as y wene, what byffell. But yett that it <NOTE N="4" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">I</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">it,</HI> oder <HI REND="italic">be had</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">bihed.</HI></NOTE> may the bettir be had in mynde, I will write hit. The same John<HI REND="italic">e</HI> was take two yer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> ago of men of the londe of P<HI REND="italic">er</HI>se, and sold to the offic<HI REND="italic">er</HI>s of the king of P<HI REND="italic">er</HI>se. And ffor his excellent ffayrnesse he was ordaynyd to serve the king. <MILESTONE N="35"/> And whan he had bene a yer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> with grete sorow and werynesse in þe kingis court: the same day twelmoneth serving the king at mete, he myght not for hevynesse kepe hym<HI REND="italic">e</HI> from weping. And whan the king see hit and had besely askid and knewe the cause, he bad s<HI REND="italic">er</HI>teyn<HI REND="italic">e</HI> knyghtis take him and kepe him in the castell. In the <MILESTONE N="40"/> nyght ffolowing he being <NOTE N="5" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">hering</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">being.</HI></NOTE> in the castell all bewepte in his slepe gloriouse Jerom come vnto him and, as him thought, toke him by the honde and ledde him w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> him to the Cite of Jherusalem. On the morowe John<HI REND="italic">e</HI> awoke and, wenyng that he had bene amongis
<PB N="359" REF="67"/>
the knyghtis, he ffounde him-selffe in the house ther he dwellid. And than he <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">y</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">he.</HI></NOTE> was nye madde ffor m<HI REND="italic">er</HI>vayle and couthe not well witt wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that he <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">y</HI> st. <HI REND="italic">he.</HI></NOTE> was in the castell or in my house. At the last he com to him-selffe and cryed, and so woke them<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> a slepe. Than come thay all rennyng to me withe gret Joy and said, <MILESTONE N="5"/> John was comyn<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Yet y was doutffull: till y went my-selffe and se him <NOTE N="2" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">hem.</HI></NOTE> present whiche y went had bene among the P<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>sees. Than he told us how he was holpen<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and he thankid and pray(s)ed god and glorious Jerom. By whose meritis and prayers our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord delyu<HI REND="italic">er</HI>e <NOTE N="3" PLACE="foot">L. <HI REND="italic">delyuere.</HI></NOTE> us ffrom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> all evill and bring us to the Cite of all weell, <MILESTONE N="10"/> to dwell w<HI REND="italic">ith</HI> him in endlesse blisse and Joy amen.</P>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="19" TYPE="chapter">
<HEAD>(IV) Here endith the pistill of Cirill to seint Austyn of seint Jerom. How our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lady seint Marie comendith seint Jerom in þe reue∣lacion of seint Burgitt. Capit. XIX.</HEAD>
<P>Whan seint Burgitt was on a tyme in her prayers, she said vnto <MILESTONE N="15"/> our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord: 'Blessid be thou, my god, that art thre and one, thre in p<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>sonys, one in natur<HI REND="italic">e.</HI> Thou art verray ffayrnesse and power, thou art verray rightwysnesse and trouthe, by whom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> all thingis lyvith and hathe thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> beyng. Thou art like a fflour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> growing singulary alone in ffeelde, of whiche fflour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> all that drawith therto <MILESTONE N="20"/> resayvith swetnesse in thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> tasting, relieving in thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> brayn<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> dilectacion in thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> sight and strengthe (in) all thayr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> membris. So all that drawith vnto the, are made the ffayrer: byleving synne, wiser: following the will of the and not of the ffleshe, mor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> right∣wyshe: ffollowing the p<HI REND="italic">ro</HI>fete of the soule and the worship of the. <MILESTONE N="25"/> Therfore, moest pytefull god, graunt me to love that pleasith the, myghty to withstonde temptacionis and to dispise all worldly thingis, and to be holden busye in my mynde'. The moder of god, our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lady, answerid: 'This salutacion<HI REND="italic">e</HI> gat the that goed Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> by his meritis, that went from<HI REND="italic">e</HI> fals wisdom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and founde trew wisdom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> <MILESTONE N="30"/> that dispisid erthely wisdom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> worship, and wanne god him-selffe. Blessid is that Jerom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> and blessid are thay that followith his tech∣ing and lyving; ffor he was a lover of wisdommys, a myrrowr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of all that wer<HI REND="italic">e</HI> p<HI REND="italic">ar</HI>fett <NOTE N="4" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">were parfett were.</HI></NOTE> in vertu, and a doctour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and a techer of all clennesse and trouthe'. <MILESTONE N="35"/></P>
<P>Another tyme our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lady said to seint Burgitt:</P>
<P>'Dowhter, haue mynde howe y told the that Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> was a lover of wisdommys, a ffolower of parffitte monkis, and auctour<HI REND="italic">e</HI> and deffensor of trouthe, that gate the by his meritis that prayer that thowe saydest. And nowe y adde to and say: that Jerom<HI REND="italic">e</HI> was <MILESTONE N="40"/> trompe, by the whiche the holy goest spake; he was also a fflawme, inflamyd of the fyr<HI REND="italic">e</HI> that come apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> me and apon<HI REND="italic">e</HI> the <NOTE N="5" PLACE="foot">Ms. <HI REND="italic">the the.</HI></NOTE> apostelis
<PB N="360" REF="68"/>
on pentycost-day. And the(r)for<HI REND="italic">e</HI> blissid ar<HI REND="italic">e</HI> thay that herith this trompe and folowe ther-after.'</P>
<CLOSER>Amen. <NOTE N="1" PLACE="foot">Hierauf folgt in der hs.:
<Q><P>Antiphona.</P>
<P>Iste est qui ante deum magnas virtutes operatus est, &amp; omnis terra doctrina eius repleta est. Ipse int<HI REND="italic">er</HI>cedat p<HI REND="italic">ro</HI> peccatis omnium po∣pulorum. Amauit eum [ms. <HI REND="italic">eam]</HI> dominus et ornauit eum. Stola glorie induit eum. <MILESTONE N="5"/></P>
<P>Oracio. Oremus.</P>
<P>Deus, qui per beatum Jeronimum, confessorem sacerdotemque tuum, scripture sce veritatem et mistica sacramenta reuelar<HI REND="italic">e</HI> dignatus es, presta, quesumus, ut, cuius memoriam veneramur, eius semper et erudiamur doctrinis et meritis adiuuemur per xpm dom. nostrum. <MILESTONE N="10"/> amen. Benedicamus domino. Deo gracias.</P></Q></NOTE></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>Her<HI REND="italic">e</HI> endith a Tretis of the lyf and myracle of sent Jerom<HI REND="italic">e,</HI> doctour of the chirche, preest and Cardinall of Rome, the whiche lieth at Bedlem, wher<HI REND="italic">e</HI> our<HI REND="italic">e</HI> lord was bor<HI REND="italic">e</HI> of þe blissid virgyn Mary.—quod Fuller. <MILESTONE N="15"/></TRAILER>
<CLOSER><DATELINE>MUENSTER.</DATELINE>
<SIGNED>C. HORSTMANN.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>
